<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Totum hominis, or, The whole duty of a Christian, consisting in faith and good life abridged in certain sermons expounding Paul's prayer for the Thessalonians, Epist. 2, Chap. 1, Vers. 11, 12 / by the late reverend and worthy Mr. Samuel Wales ...</title>
            <author>Wales, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 116 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41158</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19647337</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19647337</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109275</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66610)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109275)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1695:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Totum hominis, or, The whole duty of a Christian, consisting in faith and good life abridged in certain sermons expounding Paul's prayer for the Thessalonians, Epist. 2, Chap. 1, Vers. 11, 12 / by the late reverend and worthy Mr. Samuel Wales ...</title>
                  <author>Wales, Samuel.</author>
                  <author>Wharton, Philip Wharton, Baron, 1613-1696.</author>
                  <author>Wharton, Thomas, Sir.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[36], 197 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.B. for Benjamin Alsop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: p. 33-34 lacking; faded, stained, with print show-through and some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Thessalonians, 1st, I, 11-12 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
               <term>Faith.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109275:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109275:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Totum Hominis:</hi> OR THE WHOLE DUTY OF A CHRISTIAN Conſiſting in Faith and good Life. Abridged in certain Sermons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L'S</hi> Prayer for the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians,</hi> Epiſt. 2. Chap. 1. Verſ. 11, 12. By the late Reverend and Worthy Mr. <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL WALES</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Morley</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire.</hi> 1627. The Second Edition. With the occaſion of Re-printing it: AS ALSO A Prefatory Epiſtle from the Lord <hi>WHARTON</hi> and Sir <hi>THOMAS WHARTON</hi> his Brother to their Children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>Benjamin Alſop,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> in the <hi>Poultry</hi> over againſt the Counter, 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:109275:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109275:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THe Reader is to take notice of the Providence, by which the enſuing Treatiſe, and the Epiſtle before it came to be reprinted ſo many years after the firſt Impreſſion, and the Reaſon thereof, which was as followeth. The <hi>Lord Wharton</hi> in <hi>Sept. 1674,</hi> being at <hi>Leedes,</hi> and looking on the Pictures in the room, where he dined, among the reſt there was one of Mr. <hi>Wales</hi> the Author of both: A Gentleman there preſent ſpoke highly in his commendation, he having been a neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Miniſter in thoſe parts of great worth and eſteem, <hi>and ſaid he, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated a Book to your Lordſhip, which I think I have in my Cloſet;</hi> my Lord not remembring any thing of the ſaid Book or Epiſtle, was deſirous to ſee it, and finding in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>le
<pb facs="tcp:109275:3"/> ſo honourable a character of his <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Father,</hi> he begged the ſaid book. Afterwards finding alſo the Treatiſe it ſelf ſo uſeful, he communicated the ſame to his onely Brother Sir <hi>Thomas Wharton,</hi> who both of them thought fit to cauſe the ſaid Treatiſe and Epiſtle to be reprinted, both in reſpect of the memory of their ever honoured Father, and for the uſefulneſs of the Treatiſe it ſelf: and they alſo thought fit to add a few lines of their own to their Children, collecting from that word in the Epiſtle of the worthy and reverend Author, <hi>That the Domeſtical Precedent of ſuch a Father was for Admonition and Inſtruction of the ſaid Lord</hi> Whar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, that ſurely it was, and they hope and pray it may be no leſs admoniſhing and inſtructive to all thoſe who come but of the loines of the ſame holy and worthy Progenitor.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:109275:3"/>
            <head>PHILIP <hi>Lord</hi> WHARTON, <hi>and Sir</hi> THOMAS WHAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TON, <hi>his only Brother, wiſh Grace and Peace unto their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and their Childrens Children from God the Father, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, through the Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Holy Ghost.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Children,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU have been acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Original of the enſuing Diſcourſe, and the occaſion of its Revival at this time: Your eſpecial concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:109275:4"/> in it is from the Character and Account given of the Life and Death of your Grand-Father (our Father) in the Epiſtle Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory prefixed unto it: and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we had not the advantage of knowing him our ſelves, ſo as then to have had a ſenſe of the things ſpoken of him (he being taken away in our tender Age) yet we have a full aſſurance of the Truth of the Teſtimony given in the Epiſtle following unto his Zeal, Wiſdome, and Piety.</p>
            <p>The known Reputation and Integrity of the Reverend Author of that Epiſtle, with the time of his Writing of it, being after the Death of our Father, and its Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to one of us, then a Child, from whom he could expect no
<pb facs="tcp:109275:4"/> Countenance, nor Reward, do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt his Teſtimony from the common Condition of ſuch Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Dedications, even when Written by other good men.</p>
            <p>On this Account we do in the firſt place commend the Treatiſe it ſelf unto your diligent peruſal, and do leave it as a pledge of our concernment for you in the things contained therein. For being not deſigned, nor contrived by us, nor the Author for any ſuch end, the Tender of it being made unto you from that hand of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, whereof ye have heard, it ought to be had of you in eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial regard.</p>
            <p>It is a Treaſure in, and unto a Family, to have ſuch a Perſon as your Grand-father is here truly
<pb facs="tcp:109275:5"/> repreſented to have been on the Roll of its Progenitors: And we have been taught, that where Soveraign Grace hath made an entrance into any Family, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in a principal Root of it, it doth not utterly forſake that Family, at leaſt in ſome of its branches, unleſs the Covenant, whereby it is adminiſtred, be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally neglected or refuſed.</p>
            <p>On this Occaſion it is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper for us to add, what we each of us know, and can with much comfort Witneſs of the holy and exemplary Lives and Converſations of <hi>our dear Mother,</hi> and of each of <hi>our Wives</hi> from whom ye have reſpectively iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, on which Account, as the Apoſtle ſaid of <hi>Timothy, that he
<pb facs="tcp:109275:5"/> called to remembrance the unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Faith that dwelt in his Grand-mother</hi> Lois, <hi>and his Mother</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, we can truly ſay the like of your <hi>Grand-mother,</hi> and reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive <hi>Mothers;</hi> and we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in nothing more, than with the like Confidence to add with the ſame Apoſtle concerning you all, <hi>that we are perſwaded the ſame Faith dwells in you alſo,</hi> as we hope we can ſay of ſome of you.</p>
            <p>It becomes not us to ſpeak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing unto you of our ſelves, nor of our endeavours to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this Priviledge unforfeited unto you? It is ſufficient for us, which we muſt abide by, that, we have not been wanting in any means of Inſtruction, which we
<pb facs="tcp:109275:6"/> thought might conduce unto your good and advantage.</p>
            <p>You that are our own Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren immediately are moſt of you in that State, for Age and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, as wherein you muſt anſwer for your ſelves: We therefore leave it in charge with you, that there be not an <hi>Interciſion</hi> of the Adminiſtration of the priviledge and grace of Gods Covenant in, and towards our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily by your Default.</p>
            <p>Your Lot is fallen into Times of great Advantage on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Light of the Knowledge of the Goſpel, and of great Diſadvantage from the abounding of various Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in them; it requires more then ordinary Diligence ſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb facs="tcp:109275:6"/> your ſelves; that you neither ſuffer for abuſed mercies, nor fall into a Courſe of ſin upon urgent opportunities.</p>
            <p>Remember alſo in point of Honour and Intereſt that no Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies are more contemptible in the World, than thoſe, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate from pious Anceſtors; for in that caſe it is, which God himſelf hath given that expreſs Rule, <hi>They that honour me I will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and they that deſpiſe me ſhall be lightly eſteemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is but a little while, that we ſhall be preſent with you, neither have we much more to do for your advantage, than we have done: Our principal Deſign now is, to leave an abiding ſenſe with you of this our preſent Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.
<pb facs="tcp:109275:7"/> We are not altogether ignorant of what hath been ſaid by others, and of what yet may be ſaid in the way of Advice to Children by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who have a Care of their Temporal and Eternal good. The ſubſtance of all that can be ſpoken in this Caſe is comprized in the laſt words of <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Solomon</hi> his Son; <hi>And thou,</hi> Solomon, <hi>my Son, know thou the God of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſerve him with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect heart, and a willing mind, for the Lord ſearcheth all hearts, and underſtandeth all the Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the thoughts: if thou ſeek him he will be found of thee, but if thou forſake him, he will caſt thee off for ever.</hi> While <hi>Solomon</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb facs="tcp:109275:7"/> this advice, it was his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Honour, and when he forſook it, it was his Ruine: Nor will they have any better Succeſs, who under the like Admonition in their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances do follow his example in his miſcarriages.</p>
            <p>We could uſe many words with you unto the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, not without Hope, that, although in themſelves they ſhould not be more forcible than the words of others, yet with you they would be more effectual, and prevalent, becauſe they are ours. But our preſent deſign is onely to recommend unto your peruſal the enſuing ſmall Treatiſe, which in its O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal and Revival was direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:109275:8"/> by Divine Providence to the one of us, and thereby to be an Admonition, and means of Inſtruction unto the whole Family.</p>
            <p>You will not find in it thoſe Allurements of Style and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, which ſome in this Age do ſtrive to adorn their Writings with about things Divine. It is the Subject mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this Book, and upon the account of your ſpecial concernment in it, we propoſe to your Conſideration, and that as declared without Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torical Ornaments; yet with that Gravity of Speech, and Evidence of Truth, ſo as to recommend it unto the minds of thoſe, who are ſober and
<pb facs="tcp:109275:8"/> modeſt, and to vindicate it from the contempt of any.</p>
            <p>It doth not belong unto us to paſs our Judgement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or give a Recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto the particular mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters inſiſted on, it is ſufficient unto us, that we are ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that in the whole it may be exceeding uſeful unto your Souls, as to their Direction in the ordering of your ways with reſpect unto the Will of God. We could not therefore content our ſelves without the Diſcharge of our Duty, and ſhall pray for a bleſſing upon it unto your Advantage, when we ſhall be here no more.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:109275:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109275:9"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE, PHILIP LORD WHARTON, <hi>Grace and Glory.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>REmarkable is that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in the Hiſtory of <hi>Nehemiah:</hi> when the poorer ſort of the <hi>Tekoites</hi> laboured ſtoutly in repairing the Walls of <hi>Jeruſalem, their Nobles put not their Necks to the work of their Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Nehem 3.5.</note> By which
<pb facs="tcp:109275:10"/> we are plainly taught, that when God commandeth, Nobles are no leſs ſtraitly bound to obedience, than inferiour perſons. Indeed as <hi>godlineſs is profitable unto all things,</hi> ſo the power and practice of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is neceſſary for all perſons of all degrees. The great men of the earth, yea thoſe that are moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the higheſt ſtair of earthly Majeſty, muſt not think it any diſparagement to labour for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Myſteries of Religion, &amp; to exerciſe the duties of piety: their places cannot pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge them, their affairs may not excuſe them from works of this nature,
<note place="margin"> Dut. 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1.2, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.11. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. &amp; 72. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.11.</note> For <hi>first,</hi> as there is but <hi>one God,</hi> and one Kingdom of Heaven, ſo there is but one way leading to that Heaven, which is
<pb facs="tcp:109275:10"/> 
               <hi>the way of holineſs and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Whence it follows that the ſons of Nobles are no more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the neceſſity of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, reading, confeſſing, praying, faſting, holy conference, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over their own ways, and the ways of their houſes, and ſuch pious exerciſes which are main duties, means and helps of holineſs, than the pooreſt man in the world, that if they leave the care of theſe things to the poorer ſort, they ſhall leave Heaven to them alſo, and be turned into <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheth,</hi> while <hi>the poor take the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by violence.</hi> Secondly, the mightieſt are but Gods tenants, farmers, ſtewards, vaſſals, <hi>vaſſels</hi> as well as the meaneſt, they hold of him whatſoever they have, to
<pb facs="tcp:109275:11"/> their very breath, by homage they ſo depend upon him, that they cannot ſubſiſt one moment with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, their greatneſs as well as their being is from him, a gift of his providence (for promotion cometh neither from the Eaſt, nor from the VVeſt, nor from the South, but from God the Judge, who putteth down one, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth up another) therefore they owe as much love,
<note place="margin"> Pſal. 75. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 7. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 13.8. Dan. 4.17.</note> reverence, thankfulneſs, obedience to their Creator as others, that is in a word, they ought to be as religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as others.
<note place="margin"> Gal. 3.28. Col. 3.11.</note> For in the ſpiritual Kingdom of Chriſt there is not (nor ſhall there be in the day of wrath, and before the glorious Tribunal of Chriſts) any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt the Prince and the
<pb facs="tcp:109275:11"/> Peſant. Thirdly, Religion and Piety, bringing to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the ſpiritual ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the divine Nature, ennobles Nobility, ſets a Crown upon Earthly Dignity, makes greatneſs truly honourable: whereas the moſt glorious greatneſs without true godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and goodneſs, is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vanity, but baſeneſs in the ſight of God, deſpiſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by holy <hi>Moſes</hi> (for can any thing be more baſe, than to command many, and yet willingly to ſerve the Devil, the worſt Maſter, the vileſt Tyrant in the VVorld? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that in Scripture, not the great but the good, not the
<pb facs="tcp:109275:12"/> high but the holy, are ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the precious, excellent, glorious ones, Gods Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, worthy perſons, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the living God in whom he walks and dwells, Kings born of God, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of Chriſt, the King of Kings, dwelling in Heaven, &amp;c.) and will end in ſhame and miſery, as many teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and examples in Gods word prove abundantly? Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, where much is given, much is required; where God ſowes liberally, he looks to reap accordingly. Now great men are moſt indebted to Gods liberality, <hi>their heads are anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Oil, their cup runs over, they are fed with the finest of the
<pb facs="tcp:109275:12"/> wheat, and ſatisfied with honey out of the Rock,</hi> they enjoy the moſt precious and delicate portions of the world, and ſuck the ſweeteſt marrow of Gods temporal boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they have, or may have if they be not wanting to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, better means and more time of building up themſelves in godlineſs, than others. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have no cloak for their ſin yea double guilt lies upon their ſouls, if receiving moſt wages, they give the Lord leaſt glory, leaſt faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. They that having moſt allurements and helps to be good, will not be good, ſhall be deepeſt in Hell. Fifthly, feweſt great ones are called to grace, as few firſt born, named
<pb facs="tcp:109275:13"/> in Scripture were vouchſafed <hi>the adoption of ſons</hi> (God delighting <hi>to ſtain the pride of Mans glory,</hi> and to ſpoil him of all matter of boaſting, all occaſion of putting confidence in carnal priviledges) and its harder for great men to be ſaved, than others; becauſe there are moſt and ſtrongeſt bars to keep them from converſion, they are moſt hardly brought to emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty themſelves by ſelf-denial, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty of ſpirit, mortification, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the world, that they may be fit to enter in at the ſtrait gate, they are expoſed to moſt &amp; grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt temptations and ſpiritual dangers, as the tal Cedars to ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt blaſts, Satan hath many more advantages againſt them, than meaner perſons, they are moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb facs="tcp:109275:13"/> to be poiſoned with pleaſures, puffed up with pride, ſurfet of proſperity, let looſe the reigns to all injuſtice, violence, cruelty; in a word, to break the bonds of all diſcipline, promiſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves impunity, and become in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible (while they powre out themſelves to all licentiouſneſs) becauſe few dare freely reprove them: (hence, no doubt, ſprung that Dutch Proverb, which muſt be taken with a corn of ſalt, Princes in Heaven are as ſcarce as Veniſon in poor mens Kitchins) therefore they have need to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary careful of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and guarded with double diligence, watchfulneſs, zeal in all religious duties. Laſtly, their lives are very exemplary, obvious
<pb facs="tcp:109275:14"/> to publick inſpection and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, many eyes are fixed upon them, their actions are powerful to command, effectual to corrupt inferiours, who are too ready to follow and conform to their courſes, and think, if great men live wickedly, they may do the ſame by authority, Satanknoweth, that by their exorbitances they not only loſe their own ſouls, but draw much company with them to perdition, Examples e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of greateſt Princes, Kings, Emperours further confirming this point are not wanting. <hi>David,</hi> though entangled in many wars, beſides other incumbrances and employments not a few, ſpent no ſmall time in communing with God and his own heart, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb facs="tcp:109275:14"/> by this, that 140 of the Pſalms in probability are of his penning and compoſing. King <hi>Joſiah</hi> in the eigth year (not of his life, as ſome miſtake, but) of his reign, that is in the ſixteenth of his life, began <hi>to ſeek after the God of David his father,</hi> that is to give himſelf to the private ſtudy of piety; to reading, prayer, and ſuch like exerciſes. Who more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout than <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> two great Courtiers and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours? <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides reading and praying with his family, did every day at ſet times ſhut himſelf in his cloſet, and there converſe with God by ſolitary Prayer. <hi>Alfred</hi> King of <hi>England</hi> ſpent eight hours (the third part) of every natural day
<pb facs="tcp:109275:15"/> in prayer, ſtudy, and writing. Theſe things I have thus diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that your Lordſhip may ſee and others acknowledge, I do not without cauſe offer to your hands and eyes a Treatiſe, wherein the two main parts of religion, faith and good life, are explained and urged. It pleaſed your Noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, while yet he dwelt in the land of the living, to vouchſafe me, the meaneſt of Gods meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that gracious reſpect, which I could never have expected from ſo honourable a perſonage; and your Honour alſo, in thoſe times to take notice of me. The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thoſe things hath em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened me to this Dedication, which otherwiſe I ſhould never have preſumed to attempt. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:109275:15"/> the Searcher of hearts knoweth I ſeek and aim at nothing elſe, but the honouring of his memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry who now ſleepeth in the Lord, and ſtirring up your tender mind to the imitation of his vertues. What honeſt heart ever knew him and did not lament his departure as a publick loſs, or ſay, this world which now wants him, was unworthy of him? He was a profeſſed enemy of Popery and Prophaneneſs, a true friend and favourer of all godly and painful teachers, without exception or partiality, receiving their perſons and doctrine with ſuch gladneſs and ſingular reverence, as I muſt needs ſay to me was vvonderful, and in perſons of his ranck is rarely ſeen, ready at all times by
<pb facs="tcp:109275:16"/> his authority, ſpeech, letter to help and encourage them in their holy function? What ſhall I ſay of his ſupported life in the ſlippe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time of youth, his religious care of conſtant frequenting Gods houſe, not only twice on the Lords day, but ordinarily on Lecture days, and preparing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for the uſe of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, his ſincere affection to the holy ways of the Lord, and all that walk in the ſame, which to any obſervant eye appeared by many not obſcure ſigns and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies? I ſhall comprehend all if I do but ſay, by profane great ones, who openly reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him, he was ſecretly twitted for Preciſeneſs and Puritaniſm. And could the Epilogue of ſuch a
<pb facs="tcp:109275:16"/> life, be any other but a bleſſed death? Though his ſickneſs was violent, yet how ſweetly he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted himſelf in the Lord, and having foretold the day of his death rejoyced in ſpirit from aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of being with Chriſt after his diſſolution, how graciouſly, feelingly, powerfully, he powred out his heart in ſupplication be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, thoſe that were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent can witneſs, and will never forget, and amongſt the reſt I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member one (an ancient and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Miniſter) who profeſſed to me, that himſelf was exceedingly affected and refreſhed by his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and that he hath ſeldom heard any Preacher pray more excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, more divinely. Novv (my Lord) vvhy hath the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
<pb facs="tcp:109275:17"/> (which doth nothing in vain) ſent &amp; ſet before you ſuch a domeſtical precedent? Surely, for your admonition and inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that you might be warned there by to tread in the ſame ſteps, and learn the path of life by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample as well as precept. Suffer therefore (I beſeech your Honor) the word of exhortation. As God hath made you heir of your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers greatneſs, ſo labour to ſhew forth an expreſs image of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and godly converſation, and think often you hear his voice thus ſounding in your ears (for by his life, <hi>being dead, he yet ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to you) My ſon know the God of your father, and ſerve him with a perfect heart and willing mind,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:109275:17"/>
            <q>Macte nova virtute puer, ſic itur ad astra,</q>
            <p>By the grace of God I have led you the way, walk as I have wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, that we may meet and enjoy one another in Heaven. Repel with infinite loathing the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperings of thoſe witches, who go about to perſwade that (though its not amiſs for Nobles to have a form of godlineſs, yet) forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in Religion is a ſtain and blemiſh to Noble bloud. Such things are ſuggeſted by the father of lies, to rob you of true comfort in this life, and a Crown of glory after death. For I aſſure your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the word of truth, as true piety is able to accommodate Noblemen with the beſt Muſick (peace of Conſcience) the beſt
<pb facs="tcp:109275:18"/> Counſellor (the wiſdom which is from above) the faireſt and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt houſe (Gods protection) the beſt weapons, defenſive, offenſive faith and the ſpirit of prayer) the beſt attendants (Gods holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels) ſo it will wonderfully adorn and beautifie all other excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, purchaſe them more true honour than an external accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment, even <hi>the honour that cometh from God only, a place and a Name better than of</hi> Dukes, Earles, Lords, <hi>an everlaſting name, that ſhall never be cut off,</hi> and at laſt put them into the poſſeſſion of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, and eternal life. The father of mercies inrich with all bleſſings of heaven and earth, the noble and vertuous Lady <hi>Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphia</hi> your mother, keep your
<pb facs="tcp:109275:18"/> Honour from every evil now and ever, ſeaſon and govern your young years by his holy ſpirit, that as you increaſe in days and ſtature, ſo you may increaſe in all ſanctifying gifts, and in favour with God and men, flouriſhing in the Courts of our God, as thoſe that are planted in the houſe of the Lord, and bringeth forth more fruit in old age, to the glory of his bleſſed name. Amen and Amen, from his heart ſaith</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>To your Honour moſt addicted</hi> SAMUEL WALES.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Apr: 30. 1627.</hi>
               </date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:109275:19"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109275:19"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Theſſ. 1. v. 11, 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>11.</hi>
                     </bibl> Wherefore we alſo pray always for you, that our God would make you worthy of this calling, and fulfil all the good pleaſure of his goodneſs, and the work of faith with power.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>12.</hi>
                     </bibl> That the Name of our Lord Jeſus Christ may be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in you, and ye in him, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the grace of our God and the Lord Jeſus Christ.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE ſcope of the Apoſtle in this Chapter is, to refreſh with the cool water of conſolation, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> now in the fiery Tryal of Tribulation, and with Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dials of lively Comforts to confirm
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:109275:20"/> their ſpirits macerated and ſteeped in afflictions. His chief Argument is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from that righteous recompence of reward, which the juſt Judge of all the world will give in the day of his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, endleſs trouble and torment to them that have here troubled and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the godly, eternal eaſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment to them who are now hated and vexed for Chriſts ſake. And to the end this comfort might ſink more deeply and ſtick more firmly, he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth a little into a deſcription of Chriſts coming to Judgement, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (as it were) the very Heavens and repreſenting him to their eyes with all his glory. Theſe two Verſes now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the concluſion of this conſolation, the ſum whereof is, a commemoration of the Apoſtles Chriſtian care and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious practiſe of carrying the names of theſe <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord in holy petition, and making ſuit for them, that they might hold out in this noble but painful race and warfare, which was indeed the ſcope of his conſolation.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:109275:20"/>
            <p>In them we may conſider,
<list>
                  <item>1. The act or duty ſimply pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</item>
                  <item>2. The amplification of it,</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1"> 1. From the adjunct circumſtance of time, when or how often he did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe it.</p>
            <p n="2"> 2. From the moving cauſe, included in the firſt word <hi>[Wherefore.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3"> 3. From the ſubject or perſons for whom, the afflicted <hi>Theſſalonians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4"> 4. From the object or perſon to whom, <hi>[our God.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5"> 5. From the matter of the prayer, [<hi>that he would make you worthy,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
            <p>Let us begin with the firſt. The act or duty performed by <hi>Paul</hi> and two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy men of God, <hi>Sylvanus</hi> and <hi>Timotheus,</hi> is prayer: <hi>[we alſo pray]</hi> that is, we do not only give thanks to God for you, comfort and teach you the way of ſalvation, both by preaching and writing; but moreover, we make earneſt requeſts to God in yoor behalf. Our leſſon hence is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miniſters must pray for their People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Teachers of the Church muſt add
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109275:21"/> prayers for the Church, to all their other labours, prayers, I mean both private and publick. The ſons of <hi>Aaron</hi> are commanded <hi>to bleſs the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael,
<note place="margin"> Num. 6.23. Deut. 33.10. 1 Sam. 12.23. Jer. 18.20.</note> 
               <hi>to put incenſe before the Lord</hi> (a type of holy prayers.) <hi>Samuel</hi> calls the neglect of this duty <hi>a ſin againſt God.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, he had <hi>ſtood before the Lord to ſpeak good for his hearers, and to turn away his wrath from them.</hi> Nothing is more plain or frequent in all the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles almoſt of all the Apoſtles. And good reaſon: For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, They are ſpiritual Fathers of their Congregations, and therefore ſhould have paternal affections in them, which cannot but ſend forth Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for their Children. Will not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Parents earneſtly wiſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the good of their ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Their Prayers may greatly help and advantage the People, 1. By diverting threatned and imminent, or removing already inflicted and incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent Plagues. <hi>Moſes ſtanding in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109275:21"/> breach, turned away the Lords wrath from</hi> rebellious <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſaved them from deſerved deſtruction.
<note place="margin"> Pſal. 106.23.</note> The withered hand of that wicked <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> at the Prayer of the Prophet is reſtored. Two heavy Judgements ſhewed in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> prepared for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> at his interceſſion were ſtayed at leaſt for a ſeaſon. Read <hi>Amos</hi> 7.1.2, 3, &amp;c. 2. By procuring or pulling down from Heaven many bleſſings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, ſpiritual and corporal. <hi>Elias prayed</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi>) and <hi>the Heaven gave rain, and the Earth brought forth her fruit.</hi> If the prayers of private Chriſtians may prevail with God for <hi>healing thoſe that are ſick in ſoul or body,</hi> ſhall we think the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of his faithful Meſſengers; who come nearer unto him, will do nothing? But eſpecially their Prayers may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of God that bleſſed ſucceſs and fruit of their Miniſterial travels in the converſion and ſanctification of their hearers, than which nothing can be more profitable for the People, and which is the Crown of the Miniſters rejoycing.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:109275:22"/>
            <p>Firſt then, many are worthy to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved. Some are ſo full of Satan, that if any of their hearers do but croſs or diſpleaſe them, they break out into black and bitter curſing inſtead of bleſſing; wiſhing Gods Plagues and vengeance may fall upon them. Some are ſo ignorant, they cannot pray; ſome ſo profane, they care not for praying either for themſelves or others: they have more skill of ſwearing and ſwag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering, than powring out ſpiritual prayers. Many utter words of prayer in publick, who are dumb at home all the week long, and trouble not the Lord with one fervent and ſavoury re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt for the ſpiritual welfare of the ſouls of their people. I fear, when the great Shepherd, the Prince of Paſtors ſhall appear, theſe will appear and be found unfaithful Shepherds. For as that Chriſtian who never prays for himſelf but in the Church, is convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to pray only for faſhion; ſo that Preacher who never prays for his ſheep but in the Pulpit, may juſtly be thought to pray of cuſtom rather than
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109275:22"/> from conſcience and zealous deſire of their ſalvation; and he that prays of cuſtom only will (I warrant him) by cold and careleſs teaching (except the wind of praiſe drive his Mill) teſtifie to the world, that he cares not much who carry away their ſouls, ſo he have their fleeces.</p>
            <p>Secondly therefore, let all that are ſet over Congregations in the Lord, provoke themſelves to this duty, I mean, to be as well inſtant ſuiters for them to the Lord, as conſtant inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of them from the mouth of the Lord. Let every faithful Steward of Chriſt ſay with <hi>Samuel, God forbid I ſhould ceaſe praying</hi> for the people of God committed to my charge. For; 1. If we bear them in our hearts,
<note place="margin"> 2 Cor. 7.3.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> did his <hi>Corinthians</hi> &amp; <hi>Philippians,</hi> if we earneſtly long after and love them in the bowels of Chriſt Jeſus, as the ſame <hi>Paul</hi> did the ſame <hi>Philippians,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Phil. 1.7, 8.</note> (and what are we but hirelings, if we do not?) we cannot but remember and mention them to God in our daily prayers, as <hi>Paul</hi> did all the Churches.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109275:23"/> 2. Can we ſee our Auditors rotting and ſtinking in the Graves of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracious courſes, ſtumbling (or poa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting rather) in the path of perdition, ſtabbing and wounding themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, and like mad men treaſuring up wrath which ſhall burn themſelves in the bottom of hell? Can we ſee theſe things and not pity them, and pitying ſhall we not by prayer ſeek to help them? 3. Seeing all our ſpeech without the inſpiration of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, can neither call nor keep men in the ſtate of grace, have we not need with the Apoſtle night and day excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly to pray for them? The conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a ſinner (a work no leſs diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult than the quickening of one dead) is far above the activity of any means or labour we can uſe; yea, the power of the Angels of Heaven. A mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral diſpute of an heathen Philoſopher, much more a divine diſcourſe of a Chriſtian Preacher, may ſtirr up ſtrange pangs and paſſions, but cannot imprint grace in the ſoul, no more than turn a ſtone into fleſh. Should
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109275:23"/> we waſte our lungs, and weary, yea, wear our tongues with ſpeaking, if God bow not the heart, we ſpend our ſtrength in vain and for nothing. Now how can we expect or promiſe to our ſelves this great bleſſing, I mean the winning and ſaving of ſouls by our doctrine (which a good Paſtor thriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after more than any earthly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, and vvherein he rejoyceth more than if ten thouſand royal dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dems, all garniſhed vvith pretious ſtones, vvere ſet upon his head) if vve crave it not of God by fervent prayer?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Hearers muſt hence learn to crave the help and comfort of their godly Miniſters prayers. I doubt not but they fare better for them in their perſons, children, eſtate, travels, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſeed-time, harveſt. Its a good and commendable cuſtom to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the afflicted in Congregations to the prayers of the Paſtor. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf and his People in a great and dangerous ſtrait, by meſſengers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth the Prophet <hi>Eſay to lift up his prayer for the remnant that were left</hi> in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109275:24"/> the Kingdom of <hi>Judah.</hi> The Apoſtle wills the faithful, when any are ſick among them, to call for the Elders of the Church, that they may pray over them. If any be ſo godleſs, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe or make light account of the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Gods Meſſengers, not only the godly, but the wicked ſhall condemn them: For reprobate <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> when the hand of God preſſeth him, can ſay to <hi>Moſes, intreat the Lord for me;</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> to <hi>Peter, Pray to the Lord for me, that none of theſe things come upon me.</hi> But here let <hi>Jothams</hi> Counſel be remembred, <hi>Hearken to me you men of Shechem, that God may hearken unto you.</hi> If thou wouldeſt have thy Teacher to be a ſpeeding ſpokeſman to God for thee, if either thou deſireſt or thinkeſt thou ſhalt ever need the relief of his prevailing prayers in the day of thy calamity, ſee that now thou obey from the heart the doctrine he delivers, ſubmit as a good Child to his holy counſels and admonitions. If thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueſt to rebel againſt the word which he brings from God, it may be as the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109275:24"/> Lord charged <hi>Jeremy not to lift up a cry for the Jews, nor to make any interceſſion for them,</hi> becauſe he was determined not to hear; ſo he will lock the heart and cloſe the lips of thy Miniſter that though he would fain ſpeak for thee, he ſhall find neither words nor affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of prayer, God ſhutting the door of prayer againſt him, becauſe he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to ſhut up his mercy from thee, and not to be intreated to do thee good. And this is juſt, that he who would not hearken when God beſought him in his Miniſter to repent, ſhould not be heard, when by the Miniſter he ſueth to God for favour.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the duty. The firſt thing whereby it is amplified, is the adjunct circumſtance of time, when or how often they prayed <hi>[always]</hi> which is not ſo to be underſtood, as if they were continually upon their knees, or did nothing elſe but pray, without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion but the meaning is, that they continued and renewed every day the practiſe of this duty at fit times and ſeaſons. So <hi>Solomons</hi> ſervants are ſaid
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109275:25"/> to <hi>ſtand continually before him:</hi>
               <note place="margin"> King 10.</note> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoiachim,</hi> to <hi>eat bread continually before the King of Babylon;</hi> that is, he had a daily allowance or portion at meal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. And the daily Sacrifice in the Law is called the continual burnt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offering, becauſe it was conſtantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated twice a day, that is, offered con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually morning and evening, as elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where the Holy Ghoſt expoundeth himſelf. Now becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> and his fellows may and muſt be conſidered both as Miniſters, and as Chriſtians, hence we obſerve that,
<q>Chriſtians muſt daily exerciſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Prayer.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The ſervants of God muſt keep a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courſe of calling on God day by day. This leſſon is taught by the moſt holy mouth of our Saviour, both in that Parable of the Widow importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the wicked Judge, the ſcope whereof is to teach that <hi>men ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to pray,</hi> and in his pattern of prayer, wherein he directeth us to beg every day bread for the day: likewiſe by the example and practiſe of the Saints,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109275:25"/> 
               <hi>David, Daniel, Anna, Paul.</hi> The reaſons are many and evident.</p>
            <p>Firſt, What more equal than that part of every day be given and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to him, who is the Lord of the day and of all our time? Is it not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we ſhould daily do homage and ſervice to him, by whom we are main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and ſuſtained daily; <hi>in whoſe hand are all</hi> our days, <hi>all our ways?</hi> Is it not fit he have a ſheaf of his own Field, a Cake of his own Lump? They had a morning and evening ſacrifice in the time of the Law ſhall we, who have greater light than they had, come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them in honouring the Lord? ſhall we want that truth, whereof they had the ſhadow?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Prayer is a ſingular means of near and Heavenly communion with God: therein the godly not only ſeek, but enjoy the face of God, talk familiarly with him. And have we not need every day to maintain this communion, which is the root and fountain of all our comfort, to hold and continue acquaintance and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109275:26"/> with him, <hi>who is our life,</hi> ſtrength, beſt friend? Is it not a ſhame for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, living in houſe with their Father to paſs a day without ſpeaking to him, or looking him in the face?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Prayer ſanctifieth to us (that is, obtaineth of God for us a lawful and comfortable uſe of) all the things and affairs of the day. Without prayer therefore our callings and our labour in them are unclean: whatſoever we enterpriſe or do, is unclean to us; we cannot expect Gods bleſſing on any thing for our good, we cannot be aſſured that it ſhall beprofitable or wholeſome to us, vve may juſtly fear we ſhall be brought to Judgment and condemned for every thing we do, take, or uſe, becauſe vve defile it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, every day vve ſtand in need of many things, belonging both to temporal and ſpiritual life. We want much knowledge, vviſdom, faith, love, fear, &amp;c. our graces have no leſs need to be renewed, our ſouls repaired, than our decaying bodies &amp; bodily ſtrength, by daily food. Now Prayer is that which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109275:26"/> gets theſe vvants ſupplied, fetcheth from Heaven that bleſſing by vvhich ſpiritual ſtrength and ſtature is aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, yea by exerciſing and ſtirring up Gods graces in the heart, increaſeth them.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, We are commanded every day to lead holy lives, <hi>to walk as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh Saints, to have our converſation in Heaven, to paſs the time of our dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling here in fear, to ſpend that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth of our life, not according to the luſts of the fleſh, but according to the will of God.</hi> Novv Prayer is a neceſſary help and prop of a godly life, a good means of quickening, ſeaſoning, well-ordering the heart, of vvinding it up from Earth to Heaven, and of paſſing thorough all the parts and buſineſſes of the day, chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly and purely.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, vve are every day, yea, every hour ſubject to many dangers, outward in our bodies, families, eſtates, inward in our Souls, Satan inceſſantly vvatcheth all opportunities to do us a diſpleaſure, to ſtrike us to the heart vvith ſome fiery dart, to overthrovv our goings, lays
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109275:27"/> ſnares for us in the moſt lawful things: provocations to ſin abound every vvhere: hovv ſoon are vve diſtempered, diſſetled? hovv hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought into good frame again? Novv Prayer is our Hedge fencing us, an excellent Weapon by vvhich vve drive back Satan, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the evils vvithin or vvithout vvhich encounter us. Have vve not need to be daily armed vvith ſuch a notable help, that ſo vve may ſtand faſt againſt temptations, vvalk ſafely, and hold faſt peace vvith God?</p>
            <p>This Doctrine, if vve deſcend to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, vvill firſt reprove Three ſorts: 1. Thoſe that Pray not at all, except in the publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that riſe up and lie dovvn daily vvithout requeſt-making to God: urge upon them praying at home, their reply is ready, that's too much purity, they have other things to mind, and vvill leave that burden to the Miniſter. The Scripture hath
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109275:27"/> long ſince branded theſe for Atheiſts. Not Papiſts only, but even Gentiles ſhall condemn them, one of which counſelleth his Brother, every Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Evening to offer to God pure incenſe and oblation, that Gods favour may be towards him, and he may have ſucceſs in his affairs. If amongſt us after ſo long teaching any continue in this ſin, let them know, that as Gods fear is not in their hearts, ſo God is not in their houſes (for he dwels where he is worſhipped by prayers and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) the Devil rules all, and unleſs they repent, the curſe of God, as a canker, ſhall conſume them and theirs. 2. Thoſe that pray by fits only, as when Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience gnawes, fickneſs binds them to their beds, death threatens, buſineſs calls not, or ſuffer any worldly, any trivial occaſion to break off or juſtle out this duty. Shall I fear to ſay, this ſeeking Gods help only in extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtraits, argueth, that men think they can do well enough ordinarily without his help, and by their own wit, ſtrength, induſtry, compaſs their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109275:28"/> own ends and deſires: which a Papiſt will tell them is Gentiliſm? Had ſome of theſe Men a Neighbour, who would never viſit them, but when ſome urgent neceſſity did preſs him, would they not ſuſpect his affections towards them to be cold, and that he cared little for their company? I dare aſſure them, the Lord judgeth of them, as they of this Neighbour. It may juſtly be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vvhether ever they knew the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, or ſelt the ſweetneſs of true Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Let us fear, leaſt if we ſend for, and entertain Prayer but now and then as a ſtranger, God be ſtrange to us when we vvould moſt gladly be acquainted with him. 3. Thoſe that are fallen from their former Conſcience and care of practiſing private prayer, whoſeharts can tell them they are particularly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, if I do but ſay there are ſome amongſt us, vvho in former times were as forward and ſervent this way as the beſt, and are now become as careleſs of praying as the prophane. Its eaſie to ſhevv the reaſon why they are weary of Prayer; They have baniſhed the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109275:28"/> holy Ghoſt, and entertained the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean Spirit again, which carries them to ſwearing, drinking, delighting in bad company, and thoſe abominations from vvhich they were waſhed; vvhence it is that they have loſt both skill and will to call upon God: they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by their own Mouths, by their own Conſciences when they do pray, and therefore dare not call upon God, but flie from his preſence. The Lord be merciful unto you, that you <hi>ſleep not the ſleep of death, but may remember whence you are fallen, and come out of the ſnare of the Devil.</hi> I ſay unto you in the name of the Lord, take heed you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come not very <hi>Cains,</hi> ſpiritual vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, ſtraying and running further and further from God, till you arrive in the land of eternal horrour.</p>
            <p>Secondly, let all the Servants of God continue their holy care of daily offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Sacrifice of invocation. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the ſeaſons and occaſions of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as thou doſt thy Meal-times. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in Prayer, and faint not. Reſolve with thy ſelf, rather to ſtrive to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109275:29"/> this duty in a better manner and more abundantly, than to break it off and take liberty to neglect it. Brethren, why are we ſo backward to come unto him, to whom the oftner vve come, the more we are vvelcome, the more importunate, the more acceptable? Whence is it that every Year we ſee or hear of ſtrange puniſhments, heavy accidents befalling men, whereby they are brought to miſery or untimely death? Is it not hence, that true Prayer is out of requeſt with the moſt? Whence is it, that many ahve no better ſucceſs in their Earthly Callings and Affairs? They pray not. Whence that we hear Men complain their Houſes are inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with Spirits? (all ſuch things are not fables and illuſions, though many be) There is no Prayer in their Houſes. Whence is it that we find not help, or more comfort and ſtrength in our troubles? We pray not. Whence, that many of us are enſnared and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by every temptation? We Pray not. Pray, and thou canſt not want any good thing which God can give, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109275:29"/> the want be better for thee than the poſſeſſion. In few words, think ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly of thine own need, and the great gain of Prayer, the danger and hurt of careleſs and willing neglect of it, how highly it honours God, and I ſhall not need to uſe many reaſons for perſwading thee to aſſiduity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in the performance of it. Far be it from any truly fearing God, to think, a Chriſtian may be as ſtrong and well armed againſt temptations, as heavenly minded, as able to walk ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily and faithfully in his calling, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve peace and purity of heart, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Prayer as with it. They that are thus minded, ſhall I hope acknowledge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they die (if they belong to God) that <hi>this is not the perſwaſion of him that called them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much of the circumſtance of time. The ſecond point is the motive or cauſe which induced and ſtirred up the Apoſtle thus to pray, and that was his thirſt after the ſalvation of the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians,</hi> or his earneſt deſire that they might be glorified among other Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109275:30"/> in the day of Judgment. This is implied in the word <hi>[Wherefore]</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, And now to the end you may obtain without fail this rich prize of Heavenly happineſs, which I have ſet before you, and towards which you are already marching, that you may be ſharers with the reſt of the Saints in that admirable glory (menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the former verſe) I pray, &amp;c. Here let it be obſerved, that though the Apoſtle knew theſe <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> were entred into that good way which would certainly lead to life eternal, and aſſured of their full and future glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification, yet he thinks it behoveful and needful to help them forward by Prayers. Out of the which we may collect two inſtructions.</p>
            <q>Firſt, that <hi>the beſt need helps towards Heaven.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>And no marvel. For;</p>
            <p>Firſt, as Mans final happineſs, ſo the means leading to it are included in Gods predeſtination. He that hath ordained certain Men to ſalvation, hath ordained that by certain means
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109275:30"/> they ſhall be brought to the knowledge of it, ſtrengthened in the ſaith and hope of it, upholden in the way to it. For whomſoever God hath prepared glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (I ſpeak of thoſe that are of ripe age in the Church) to them he hath left and commended his ſacred. Word, Paſtors and Doctors, Sacraments, Prayer, Watchfulneſs, Faſting, and the like, with expreſs charge to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe and attend upon theſe means, while they abide in this Tabernacle. Now if we did not need theſe things, God would never have appointed them: he that is moſt wiſe, doth nothing in vain, nor cloggeth his Children with unneceſſary burdens.</p>
            <p>Secondly, not every one that begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth well, but <hi>he that continueth to the end, ſhall be ſaved.</hi> No Crown without perſeverance, <hi>back ſliding is the way to perdition.</hi> Now the beſt are prone to turn back from following the Lord, or to faint in the way: For the beſt 1. have weakneſs in them; 2. meet with many lets incumbring them. 3. The trade of godlineſs is difficult,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109275:31"/> irkſome, and grievous to the fleſh. True it is,
<note place="margin"> Iſa. 45.24.</note> 
               <hi>the strength by which they ſtand, is in and from Chriſt,</hi> but conveyed and miniſtred unto them by the pipes of holy means and ordinances, which himſelf hath ſanctified to that end. In vain do they look to be kept and ſtrengthened by Chriſt, who wittingly caſt away the means by which his ſtrength ſhould be applied to them. Theſe things being ſo, who ſeeth not how neceſſary it is that they who run well, be helped and underſhored by ſpiritual means?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Satan <hi>hath great wrath</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that are taken out of his hands and <hi>tranſlated toward the Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> he labours buſily to intangle them in the old ſervitude, and bring them back into the former bondage. In regard of <hi>this wicked one,</hi> therefore they have need to be ſupported, leſt <hi>the Dragon cast them down</hi> from their good beginnings, and <hi>ſo their latter end be worſe than their beginning,</hi> of which the Devil would be moſt glad.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, we ſee the folly of them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109275:31"/> diſcovered and checked; who cry down all means, as being of little or no uſe to them that are in Chriſt. I know the Mans Name, who compared one commed to Chriſt, unto a Man that having finiſhed his Houſe, lays aſide his Tools. How I pray you (judge in your ſelves) can thoſe Men, who deny that Scriptures are either guide or rule to a true Chriſtian, who maintains that Miniſters ought not to urge &amp; call for repentance, mortification, holy walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; who diſlike repetition of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, judge Family-prayer a thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, dare travel on the Lords day without ſcruple, reſt contented with a reading Miniſter, caſt away all Books but the Bible, and ſay plainly. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries do but miſlead Men, that Treatiſes directing to lead a godly life will mar Chriſtians: How, I ſay, can theſe think, that means and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are needful? And doth any Man now expect, that by Arguments drawn out of the Word, I ſhould oppoſe this new Divinity? ſhall I ſpend time in ſhewing how this Opinion fights with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109275:32"/> the experience and practice of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> both of them (though Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets) moſt preciſe obſervers of holy duties and exerciſes, and one of them bitterly lamenting the want of publick means? How it voideth and breaketh many Scriptures, as, <hi>Quench not the Spirit, Deſpiſe not Prophecying, Stir up the gift of God in thee, Attend at the poſts of wiſdom, Keep thy Heart above all keeping, Ponder the path of thy feet, Build your ſelves on your moſt holy faith, Search the Scriptures, Whet theſe things ou thy Children, Hold faſt what you have heard, Watch and Pray, Examine your ways,</hi> and almoſt ſix hundaed ſuch like pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? (unleſs they will give us new ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of theſe plain Texts, never before heard of) or laſtly, that it carrieth a too too rank favour of Anabaptiſm and Familiſm? No, no, the bitter fruits of ſuch looſe conceits in the lives of theſe new Evangeliſts, cry aloud that the good Spirit is not the Father of them. Behold here a marvellous poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and ſtratagem of that many-headed Serpent. The greateſt part of the world
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109275:32"/> he holds in a ſecure and dead conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein they came neither for Chriſt nor means. When he cannot keep Men from means, he perſwades and cunningly prevails with many to reſt contented in the naked and powerleſs uſe of them, abſtracted from Chriſt, and his quickening Spirit, the Life of means. When this plot ſucceeds not, he will puſh Men into the contrary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream, perſwading ſo to hang upon Chriſt, as they neglect all means; wherein it ſeems ſome of the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> faulted. Oh that theſe Men would conſider that which the Devil knows full well, that they who dare abandon and relinquiſh the means of maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Godlineſs and a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, will in time caſt off all care of godlineſs and keeping a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and he who dare bid farewell to the means of executing Gods prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtination, is in danger to fulfil his own reprobation.</p>
            <p>Secondly therefore, let us take heed of ſetting at naught the gracious helps which God offers and affords for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109275:33"/> us on in our ſpiritual Journey. Let us lay hold upon them, and apply them with diligence, publick, private ordinary, extraordinary. God could ſave us without them, but will not. We ſhall never be ſo ſtrong as not to need theſe ſtaves, <hi>till we appear perfect before him in his holy Mountain.</hi> Its as vile preſumption and madneſs to think our Souls can be in good plight, and our ſpiritual life continued without them, as to hope for a crop vvhere vve never ſowed, or ſtrength and life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out meat and drink. Do vve not ſee that ſuch Chriſtians as uſe them moſt, have moſt grace? Take heed, ſay not in thy heart, <hi>I</hi> am ſure <hi>I</hi> ſhall never fall, <hi>I</hi> cannot be taken out of the hands of Chriſt, therefore theſe outvvard duties are not needful for me, the Spirit of grace vvill make no ſuch concluſions. Its the Devils Logick, not Gods, vvhich teacheth to reaſon from the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Gods grace to the neglect of our ovvn duty. Thus of the former inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Our ſecond Leſſon from the ſame ground is, that</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:109275:33"/>
            <q>Godly Mens Prayers promote the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of others.</q>
            <p>The hearty ſupplications of the faithful put up unto God, for their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, are good means furthering and helping forvvard the ſalvation of their brethren. if this were not ſo, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour would not have taught us to pray, that <hi>Gods Kingdom of grace and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, may come to others, as well as our ſelves that others as well as our ſelves may know and obey the will of God ſincerely, chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, constantly:</hi> The Apoſtle would not have ſaid, <hi>I know this ſhall turn to my ſalvation through your prayers; my prayer to God for</hi> Iſrael <hi>is, that they may be ſaved, the Lord grant that he may find mercy in that day; If a man ſee his brother ſin a ſin which is not unto death, he ſhall ask and he ſhall give him life for them that ſin not unto death.</hi> For ſometimes the prayers of the godly obtain for others the beginning of actual ſalvation, that is, converſion (as our Saviours prayer for the Jews who crucified him, took effect when ſo many of them were brought to repentance by <hi>Peters</hi> firſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109275:34"/> Sermon, and <hi>Stevens,</hi> when <hi>Paul</hi> was converted; therefore the Apoſtle wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Chriſtians to pray, that <hi>Heatheniſh Magiſtrates</hi> may be turned to the Lord, <hi>and come to the knowledge of the truth</hi>) ſometimes the progreſs of it, that is, the continuance and increaſe of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent bleſſings and gifts which are preparatives, forerunners, certain prognoſticks of perfect ſalvation, as fuller aſſurance, comfort in afflictions, ſpiritual eſtabliſhment, and the like. Yet here we muſt know (that we may rightly and ſoundly underſtand the point) that Prayer is not a cauſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God to ſave thoſe whom before he did not intend to ſave, or making him more willing to ſave ſuch, whoſe ſalvation he formerly willed, for Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity teacheth, that the will of God ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth not intenſion or remiſſion) but a condition commanded and required in us, which being fulfilled by us, the Lord hath promiſed to ſhew and ſhed abroad upon others that grace, which he had purpoſed before all time, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon them.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:109275:34"/>
            <p>The which doctrine ſerveth firſt to teach us, what is the beſt office and greateſt good turn we can do to any whom we love, or whoſe kindneſs we deſire to recompence, as faithful friends, bountiful benefactors, kind parents, dutiful children, loving yoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellows. Lend them many hearty prayers, intreat the Lord ſer them, that <hi>they may be delivered from this preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil world, their eyes enlightned, their ſins pardoned, their hearts parged, their feet guided in the way of peace:</hi> beg theſe things for them. If thou prevaileſt in thy ſuit, thou haſt done more for them, than if thou hadſt made them Lords of all that the Iberian <hi>Nimrod</hi> doth either poſſeſs or deſire, all the Kingdoms of the earth. Oh the dignity, utility, riches of prayer! a good man by prayer may do that for his friend, which all the wealth and power of the world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do. The pooreſt Chriſtian, on whom God hath powred the ſpirit of ſupplications, may be very profitable to the rich, helping him to that which all his ſtore cannot purchaſe. For by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109275:35"/> the Heaven-piercing prayers, which aſcend daily from the Altar of a pure heart in the Temple of his ſoul, he may be a means of <hi>receiving him into everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting habitations,</hi> that is, of ſaving his ſoul.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hence we muſt be ſtirred up, 1. In our daily petitions, not only to ſpeak for our ſelves, but to remember alſo the whole community of them that belong to God whereſoever ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. Its a great fault in Chriſtians, not only to omit this duty altogether, but to make it (as too many do) a meer matter of form. Indeed our wicked hearts out of ſloth or unbelief, will be too ready to ſay, Alas wherein can our prayers be profitable to them, whoſe faces and caſes are unknown to us. But anſwer them from this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, our prayers may advance the buſineſs of their ſalvation, and like a proſperous wind facilitate their courſe (or ſet them forward with happy ſpeed) towards the Celeſtial Paradiſe. How are we friends of Gods people, if we deny our helping hand to procure
<gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:109275:35"/> in ſpecial ſort we ſhould be mindful of them that travel under tribulation, and ſuffer with Chriſt or for Chriſt. This duty is included in that general pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, <hi>remember them that are in bonds.</hi> The practice of it occurs often in Scripture. The ſweet Pſalmiſt ſingeth, <hi>redeem Iſrael O God out of all his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, that thy beloved may be delivered, ſave with thy right hand and hear me.</hi> How often do the Faithful in the Pſalms complain to God of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches diſtreſs and petition for redreſs?
<note place="margin"> Pſal. 74.79, 80.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> Courtiers both in great favour with the greateſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs in the world at that time, how mournfully and earneſtly do they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat for the church then in miſery?</p>
            <p>For, Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> they are our fellow-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, parts of the ſame body: if one member ſuffer or be diſeaſed, will not the reſt ſympathize, and ſeek the beſt relief for it they can? if the head ake, the ſtomack want meat, the heart be pained, the arme wounded, the foot gouty? will not the tongue (the ſouls orator) by ſpeaking, the hand by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109275:36"/> crave ſupply, or remedy? ſure, elſe they were unworthy to have any place in the body, or receive life or motion from the head and heart.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> they greatly need our prayers; for their condition is both pityful and dangerous. They ſtand as Gods ſouldiers, in the very heat and heart of the moſt dangerous battle: have not theſe need to be well backed by our prayers? they ſigh and groan under oppreſſion and wrong: have not theſe need to be eaſed and helped by our prayers? they are in the furnace of fiery tryal. Have not theſe need of the cooling comfort of our prayers? if they ſhould quail and ſtart back whom the Lord hath now brought into the open field, for the maintenance of his truth, the enemies would inſult, Satan be proud of his victory, Gods cauſe in danger to fall to the ground, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny weak ones be diſcouraged.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> we may do them much good by our prayers. We may knock their perſecutors in the head (it hath been obſerved, that the faithful fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:109275:36"/> againſt proud and cruel Tyrants with no other weapons, but prayers and tears have given them blows, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which they could never riſe or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover) we may move the Lord to give them compaſſion, before thoſe that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted them, or to raiſe them up friends and fautors; we may obtain for them deliverance (as the Church did for <hi>Peter)</hi> or ſtrength to ſtand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible under the croſs.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, our own hearts will tell us,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> that were we in their caſe, we would deſire and expect this kindneſs from others. We would think them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be called or accounted our brethren in Chriſt, who hearing of our afflictions, would not afford us the help of their prayers, Now this is a rule in the royal Law, urged alſo by Chriſt himſelf, <hi>whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them,</hi> and that which is now their lot may be ours e're long: we are ſubject to the ſame things they ſuffer. Suppoſe we were out of all reach of gun-ſhot, yet we are commanded to put our
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:109275:37"/> ſelves in their room, and to be affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards them, as if their caſe were ours, as if their afflictions were our own proper burden.</p>
            <p>Firſt then,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> what manner of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are thoſe, who if they pray at all, pray only for themſelves? many (alas too many) are of this mind: may but they ſit and walk in the warm Sun of proſperity, ſleep in a whole skin, line themſelves well with wordly wealth, ſuck in the commodities of a fruitful and peaceable land, let who will take thought for diſtreſſed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, diſtreſſed Chriſtians, they will leave that to them, who have little elſe to do. To apply this ſomewhat more particularly. We cannot be ignorant how diverſe as dear to God, as the beſt of us, are at this day afflicted, ſome pinched and preſſed with penury, ſome impriſoned, ſome baniſhed: <hi>We have heard with our ears, our neighbours have told us,</hi> how ſome are ſpoiled of their goods, houſes, children, ſynagogues, liberty of worſhipping God purely, <hi>their temple-ſongs turned into howlings,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:109275:37"/> ſome kept in ſore bondage, by hard &amp; cruel Lords, mourning continually, and <hi>drinking their own tears in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, by reaſon of the oppreſſion of the enemy and the avenger: ſome given to be meat to the ſword of the furious, and ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phurous ſons of Babylon; who now is grieved for theſe breaches of Ioſeph?</hi> who lays them to heart? the telling or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of theſe things may prove a pang of pity in us, for the preſent, but who cries earneſtly to God for them? who can ſay, his ſoul bleeds in ſecret for Zions wounds, and thirſts after the peace of her children, as if they were his own natural parents and brethren? that their miſeries lie heavy upon his ſpirit, that he bears them in his heart, when he comes to God in prayer? give me the man, give me the man (that I may pronounce him <hi>the bleſſed of the Lord,</hi> yea one of 10000) who cannot take, and find that contentment, which otherwiſe he might, and could in his own good fare, quiet habitation, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious lodging, ſweet children, to whom the beſt outward comforts are
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:109275:38"/> leſs pleaſant, and often ſawced with ſorrowful ſighs, becauſe it goes not well with the people, <hi>and Saints of the Moſt high.</hi> Well, we may here learn to judge of our ſelves, if our houſes, our hearts afford no prayers for poor affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Chriſtians,
<note place="margin"> Zeph. 3.18.</note> if we be not <hi>ſorrowful for the ſolemn aſſembly, if the reproach of it be not a burden to us,</hi> we are as far from a truly Chriſtian diſpoſition, as they that are furtheſt, dead lumps in the womb of the Church, void of the ſpirit of Chriſt unworthy to be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the myſtical body of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> let us therefore make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of this duty: let us never ceaſe to commend unto the Lord his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted flock, his peeled and perſecuted people. We ought to lay down our lives for them, if God ſhould call us thereunto; and ſhall we be backward to lend them our prayers? Is it likely we would ſpend our blood to do them good, for whom we will not ſpend a few tears, a little breath? a few hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deſires and affectionate ſuits, which we may do without hurt? If the <hi>Jews</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:109275:38"/> in captivity muſt pray for the <hi>peace of</hi> heatheniſh <hi>Babylon;</hi> how much more ſhould the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God for <hi>Jeruſalem the City of God?</hi> Is not the Chriſtian Church the Spouſe of Chriſt? If we can ſee Chriſts own Spouſe deſpight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully uſed, trampled upon, wounded and not be troubled, not ſpeak a good word for her, how dare we ſay the love of Chriſt dwelleth in us? The Lord (no dobut) hath juſt reaſons within himſelf, why as yet he ſendeth not inlargement and deliverance to his Church; but this freeth not them from blame, who ſeeming, and calling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Churches chidren, pray not at all, or very coldly for the proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their mother. Nay, I will ſay bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this denying to help the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the enemy, though they never conſpired with the enemy, makes them guilty in Gods ſight of the Churches deſolation, as ſure as he that looks on, while a true man is rob'd and murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and calls not for aid, is acceſſary to the murther. Wherefore let us now begin (if hitherto we have been ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:109275:39"/> and careleſs) and continue to be importunate petitioners for the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in miſery; oh let us double our importunity (if it be poſſible) giving the Lord no reſt till he ariſe, <hi>have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on Zion, and ſtabliſh Jeruſalem, till he tread down her enemies as ſtraw is trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for the dunghil, and raiſe up Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which may fray, and caſt down the horns that have ſcattered Judah,
<note place="margin"> Zech. 1.21</note> that there may be no more a pricking briar to the houſe of Iſrael, nor any grieving thorn of all that are round about them, that they may be no more a prey to the heathen, but dwell ſafely, and none may make them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid.</hi> Let us often ſet before our eyes their rueful condition, think how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good things they want, which we enjoy; and how little worthy we are to enjoy what they want; labour to be affected with a tender ſenſe of their miſeries, that our hearts melting in compaſſion, may ſend forth many zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous prayers, the fruit and benefit whereof, they, whom we never knew, never ſaw, ſhall undoubtedly feel and reap in one kind or other.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:109275:39"/>
            <p>The fourth point in order,
<note place="margin"> Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> is the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect of <hi>Paul</hi>'s invocation, the Author of the bleſſings which are afterwards begged, thus diſcribed, [our God] that is, the true God, who generally is the God of the whole world, <hi>The Lord of all the earth,
<note place="margin"> Zeck. 6.5.</note> the God of the Spirits of all fleſh,</hi> peculiarly of his own people. Whence let us obſerve (omitting all others) only this Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <q>The Lord is in ſpecial ſort the God of the faithful,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> 
            </q>
            <p>The godly and true believers, have God to be theirs in a ſpecial manner. <hi>He is my God, my Fathers God,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Exod. 15.2.</note> ſaith <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, this God is our God for ever and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt. <hi>O Lord, thou art my God,</hi> ſaith the Prophet in the name of the Church. <hi>The Lord my God ſhall come ſaith Zachary, My God ſhall ſupply all your needs,</hi> ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. And many ſuch places there are through out the Scriptures. For,</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> he hath ſelected them out of the world, <hi>and ſeparated them from other people to be his peculiar people,</hi> and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:109275:40"/> embraceth them with ſuch a love, as he extendeth not to all.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>he hath confirmed them to himſelf,</hi> by making with them a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of life and peace, wherein he promiſed to be a Father and Husband to them, removing evils, conferring all good things, in this and the future life. So much is compriſed in theſe few words. <hi>I will be their God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> they chuſe and <hi>avouch him to be their God,</hi> to whom they give themſelves, and yeild all hearty and willing ſervice, duty and obedience, as becomes good children and ſubjects.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> this ſerves to controll the ſawcineſs and preſumption of wicked men, who being the ſeed of the old ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and children of the wicked one, will needs uſurp and intrude into the proper right of the righteous, that is, challenge God to be their God, their Father. It can hardly be told, how diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable intollerable a wrong theſe men offer to the Lord: they moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignly debaſe his excellent Majeſty, making him a favourer, Patron, father
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:109275:40"/> of naughtineſs the companion of Satan, which is moſt vile impiety, yea blaſphemy, ſhould a known ſtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſtill in all places be calling the King her Husband; would it not be counted impudency worthy to be ſeverely puniſhed by the judges? Let ſuch hear the Lord himſelf (if yet they will believe him) forbidding him to be ſo bold with his Name; <hi>What haſt thou to do to take my Covenant in thy mouth?</hi> Yea, plainly telling tthem to their faces, <hi>they are not his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, not under mercy, that he is not their God.</hi> It's true, even the vileſt men in the world have relation to him, and dependence on him, as a Creator and Conſerver: but no man can truly call God his by Covenant, till he find in himſelf, 1. A ſweet mourning in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, for that he hath done him ſo much wrong, and ſtill can ſerve him no better. 2. A ſenſibleneſs of his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour. 3. An earneſt ſtriving to give God his heart in all worſhip.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> this Doctrine nay com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the Godly. Fear not, nor be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:109275:41"/> diſmayed thou faithful Chriſtian: if he be thy God, who is the God of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and juſtifier of repentant ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, thou canſt not be condemned; if he be thine, who is greater than all, ſin ſhall not hurt thee, nor Satan <hi>pluck thee out of his hands.</hi> If God be thine, he will keep and care for thee, thou art ſure of conſolation in cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,
<note place="margin"> Eſa. 43.2, 3.</note> preſervation in perils, ſupply of all wants, his wiſdome ſhall be thy watch, his providence thy portion, his power thy pillar ſuſtaining thee in heavieſt afflictions: If God be thine his promiſes are thine, all thoſe Texts which declare what God is, or will be to his, are as ſurely thine as if thy name were expreſſed in them, his Chriſt is thine, his kingdome is thine, all are thine. If friends fail as the brooks in ſummer, kinsfolks grow unkind, and old acquaintance ſtand afar off like ſtrangers, if parents or dear yoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellows take their leave and drop down into the duſt of death, if earthly ſtays and comforts, like riches in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> take themſelves to their wings
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:109275:41"/> and fly away, grieve not thou as others that have no hope, but ſing and exult in ſpirit; ſeeing God, who is inſtead of all things, remaineth thy God for ever and ever. <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord, ye righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</hi> and be thankful for your happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; <hi>for bleſſed are the people whoſe God is Jehovah.</hi> This is indeed true felicity to him that hath God for his God, no good ſhall be wanting, no evil mortal, nothing can make him miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> the faithful are here inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, 1. To reſt on the Lord with full confidence of heart, to appropriate him particularly to themſelves, boldly to challenge an intereſt in him. When God hath pleaſed of his rich grace to become mine, giving himſelf to me, how can it be preſumption to make claim to him as mine, and ſay as holy ones have ever ſaid, <hi>The Lord is my God;</hi> from this hold (which indeed is the foundation of all our comfort) the Devil and the Pope would drive us; but we muſt maintain our title, and never ſuffer our ſelves to be beaten
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:109275:42"/> from it, eſpecialy in the evil day in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes and agonies of conſcience, imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating our Lord and Maſter, who when his Fathers hand ſo preſſed him; that to his own feeling he had forſaken him, yet cryed, <hi>My God my God, why haſt thou ſorſaken me?</hi> 2. To go boldly to him in praier, ſeeking and asking of him all things needful: ſpeak to him with confidence of acceptance and audience: if he be our God, he will deny us nothing. Should we fear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing welcome to our own? <hi>I am the Lord their God, and will hear them,</hi> ſaith God in the Prophet <hi>Zachary.</hi> 3. With erect and undiſmayed ſpirits to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs and confeſs his name before the ſons of men. If we call him ours, and here the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>he is not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be ſo called,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Heb. 11 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſhall we be aſhamed of him, deny him in the world? if we do, are we not well worthy to have our liveries taken from us, and to be turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of his ſervice, or diſcarded in the day of his glorious appearing? 4. To be careful of honouring, pleaſing, obeying him, <hi>Ye ſhall do my judgements</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:109275:42"/> (ſaith the Lord to the people in <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus) and keep mine ordinances to walk therein. Why? I am the Lord your God.
<note place="margin"> Levit. 18.4.</note> We will ſerve the Lord, for he is our God,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Joſh. 24.18.</note> ſay the people in <hi>Joſhua.</hi> For ſhame ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver profeſs thy ſelf to be Gods, never call God thine, while thou makeſt no conſcience of obeying him. Art thou a willing ſervant of ſin, more ready to do what thy luſts lead unto, than what God commands? Sin is thy God. Doſt thou beſtow upon the world, the profits and pleaſures of it, that love, fear, joy, delight, ſtrength, time, which God challengeth, and the godly conſecrate to him? The world is thy God. Are thy waies ſuch as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree far better with the will of the Devil, than with the holy will of God? Doſt thou not take far more care and pains for fulfilling the mind of the fleſh, and Satan, than doing what God requireth and accepteth? The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is thy God. See now thou haſt choſen and made ſtrange gods to thy ſelf, <hi>other Lords have dominion over thee, the God that formeth thee, haſt thou
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:109275:43"/> rejected; for no man can ſerve two ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> hence the Sons of men are admoniſhed, to take heed of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting (that is wronging) the godly, by word or work; for they belong to <hi>one that is higher than the higheſt,</hi> the mighty maker of all things is their maſter, and hath undertaken to be their Protector; he that toucheth them toucheth the Lord, who hath linked himſelf to them in an eternal league of amity. If God be theirs, he will certainly take their parts, declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an enemy of their enemies, ſmite the proudeſt that afflict them. Make God thy Foe, draw him into the Field againſt thee, and ſee how thou ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt.</p>
            <p>The laſt and largeſt branch of our general diviſion now followeth,
<note place="margin"> Reſolution.</note> which is the matter of the Apoſtles prayer. Wherein two things are to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; 1. The things craved in the reſt of the 11 <hi>ver.</hi> 2. The end for which he deſired and would have God to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow them, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. The things craved
<pb facs="tcp:109275:43"/> for the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> the bleſſings for which <hi>Paul</hi> prayeth unto God in their behalf, are two: for he intreateth the Lord, 1. <hi>That he would make them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of their calling.</hi> 2 That he would fulfil all the good pleaſure of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereof the firſt is principal the other ſubordinate, a means con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing and ſubſervient to the former. Let us begin with the former; and firſt ſeek out the ſenſe of the words,
<note place="margin"> Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iton.</note> By <hi>calling,</hi> many underſtand the glory of Gods kingdome, to which the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful are called. I ſee no need of flying to ſo far-fetcht a <hi>Metorymya,</hi> we may well enough take it in the uſual ſenſe; either for that gracious and ſaving be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of God beſtowed on the Elect, which commonly we call <hi>effectual call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or for the ſtate and profeſſion of Chriſtianity, to which they are brought by Gods calling them out of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural condition; and then the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the other words will be this. We pray, that the Lord will enable you to walk, as becometh thoſe that are the called of God, to direct, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109275:44"/> ſtrengthen you, that in nothing you may diſcredit, but in all things to the very end, honour your Chriſtian-call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Hence we may deduce three con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions.</p>
            <p>The firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>True Chriſtians of themſelves would ſhame their calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The faithful, if God do not guide and uphold them, are in danger to ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh their profeſſion. For prayer to God for any thing, importeth and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſeth our indigency, and want of the thing prayed for, or elſe impotency to retain what we have obtained, to perform what is required. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles petition implies as much, as if he had ſaid, though you have received a good portion of Gods grace, unleſs he continue to be your ſtrength, and ſtay, you will fall to ſuch courſes, as are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy your holy calling.
<note place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, endued with a large meaſure of the ſpirit of ſanctification, how did he diſcredit his religion, by his adultery, murther, counterfeit madneſs? <hi>Peter</hi> an Apoſtle, by lying, ſwearing, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing, before the enemies of Chriſt,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:109275:44"/> and by diſſembling at <hi>Antioch?</hi> The like may be ſaid of <hi>Noah, Jonah, Sampſon, Solomon;</hi> for that <hi>Solomon</hi> was an elect veſſel; and is a glorious Saint in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, I no more doubt, than that he was the Author of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes;</hi> for this Book could not be written in the time of his primitive integrity (becauſe he ſpeaks preciſely of that as a thing paſt) nor of his Apoſtacie,
<note place="margin"> Eccleſ. 2.8.</note> becauſe a ſoul turned from God would never have taken pains to draw men from all earthly vanities, which is the ſcope of that Book) nor breathed out ſuch heavenly precepts, as are here found; and therefore was written by a true pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, who found God gracious, and was received into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome.</p>
            <p>Reaſons of this Doctrine,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> may be drawn, Firſt, from the reliques of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal ſin, the root and ſource of ſins, which ſtill hath reſidency, though not regency in the beſt; the old leaven is not perfectly purged out, <hi>that fleſh in which dwells no goodneſs</hi> dwells in thoſe that have moſt goodneſs. The holieſt ſouls do neceſſarily, though unwillingly
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:109275:45"/> carry about in their boſoms an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary diſeaſe, which inclines them to drowſineſs,
<note place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.11.</note> and neglect of their holy watch. a dangerous deceiver, an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my like to Satan, luſting againſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, rebelling againſt the Law of their mind, ſometimes craftily enticing, ſometimes violently haling to thoſe things that are contrary to their calling</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> from Satans oppoſition, who thruſts ſore at them, that he may caſt them down from their excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, out of the hatred he bears both to their Souls which will be wounded? and to Gods Name, which will be ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed by their falſe. Therefore he blows the fire of natural corruption, preſents objects, and by them worketh upon the heart, offers wicked company, watcheth where they are weakeſt, when moſt unprovided, and accordingly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults them; a thouſand wiles he uſeth all the power and policie of his ſeven heads and ten horns he applieth to the ſubverting of them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, from the weakneſs of the new man. True holineſs indeed is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:109275:45"/> in them; but imperfect: their ſtrength is like the ſtrength of a child, now beginning to go, or a man reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering of a great ſickneſs; they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know, believe, nor love perfectly, and therefore can neither avoid evil, nor do good perfectly. Look then, as he whoſe ſight is dim, or joynts and knees feeble, may eaſily ſlip and fall into the mire; ſo the beſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans being attended with infirmity, whil'ſt they are ſtrangers on earth, are in danger by falling to ſhame their calling, further than they are ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God.</p>
            <p>The point thus confirmed, ſerveth further to admoniſh the godly of three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> to take notice of our great frailty. Alas, ſilly weaklings are we, <hi>unſtable as water,</hi> reeds ſhaken with the wind, if the rock of <hi>Iſrael be not our arme every morning;</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Eſa. 33.2.</note> unable to ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the left blaſt of Satans mouth, the ſmalleſt puff of wordly troubles, ready enough, if left to our ſelves, to fall as foully, as fearfully, as ever did
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:109275:46"/> any, and ſo cauſe the Church of God, the religion of God, the calling of Chr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity to be reproached; the beſt of us, the ſtrongeſt amongſt us, had we no better keepers than our ſelves, would ſin like <hi>Peter, David, Solomon, Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> yea become <hi>Judaſſes, Demaſſes, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexanders,</hi> terreſtial Devils; he that believes not this of himſelf, is blind and knows not himſelf. See what ſmall cauſe we have to be conceited, and confident of our own ſtrength.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> to fear continually, to be jealous and ſuſpicious of our felves in regard of our great weakneſs, and with all careful and curious circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to watch over our ſelves, that we be not ſupplanted by ſin. <hi>Bleſſed is he that in this ſort feareth allwaies;</hi> had <hi>Peter</hi> feared his own infirmity, he had not ſtrayed ſo grievouſly. No man is nearer downfall, than he that is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt from doubting himſelf. Had we a child, or ſervant whom we knew deſperately bent to hurt himſelf, or ſome other, or elſe in danger, either by reaſon of ſome diſeaſe to fall into
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:109275:46"/> fire and water, or of a bad diſpoſition, to play ſome lewd, ſhameful pranck, whereby our houſe might be diſcredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, would we not ſtill have an eye to him, and command our folks to watch him at every end? the caſe is our own; our own traiterous hearts conſpire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us night and day to work us woe, to lay us naked before the world, like <hi>Noah</hi> uncovered in his tent, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us into the dirty-paths of ſin, that when we have ſtained our gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, we may be the laughing ſtock of Devils and wicked men. Oh look we to our ſelves that we be not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by ſuch a cozening companion: no vigilancie can be too great, in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving and taking heed of this thief, this murtherer.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, not to inſult over,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> nor to be cenſorious in judging Chriſtians for their falls. Seeſt thou one <hi>that calls on the name of Chriſt,</hi> do this or that unbeſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his profeſſion? do not preſently condemn him for an hypocrite, nor ceaſe to acknowledge him for a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but rather <hi>ſupport him in love, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:109275:47"/> the ſpirit of meekneſs, conſidering thy ſelf, leſt thou alſo be tempted;</hi> remembring that thy ſelf, though as famous for faith and ſanctitie, as any of theſe <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians,</hi> art in danger to do as much, yea more, if the Lord do not lead thee in his truth and righteouſneſs. But let no man miſtake me, or deceive him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; I ſpeak of one, who failing in ſome particular act, is for the main, undefiled in his way; not of a man that follows ſin as a trade, and after illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and admonition, purpoſeth to go on ſtill in his treſpaſſes. We may as lawfully and certainly judge ſuch an one to be <hi>de preſenti,</hi> a ſlave of the Devil, one far off the kingdom of God, as call that a crab-tree, which beareth crabs or a thorn; which bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the fruits of a thorn.</p>
            <p>The ſecond inſtruction is,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>The godly muſt by all means grace their calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſtians muſt ſo demean them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves both in peace and trouble, as they may honour and credit the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian-name and profeſſion. For <hi>Paul's</hi> prayer includes the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:109275:47"/> as if he ſhould ſay, we knowing and conſidering, that this is a main thing chiefly to be looked unto, by you that are believers, worthy the labour of your lives, do conſtantly beg for you at the hands of God this grace, that he would make you worthy of this calling. The <hi>Epheſians</hi> are exhorted, <hi>to walk worthy of the vocation wherewith they are called. Timothy muſt teach women to carry themſelves, as becommeth thoſe that profeſs godlineſs.</hi> And good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For,</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>41</label> in ſo doing they honour the holy name of God, by cauſing the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and religion of God to be well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought and well-ſpoken of. Whereas by ſtaining their profeſſion, they ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh the glorious name of God. For they open the mouths of the prophane, to blame and blaſpheme religion, to rail againſt and curſe the Goſpel; which things muſt needs redound to his diſhonour: Hence the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth of the Jews, that by their ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous mariages, <hi>they had prophaned his holineſs,</hi> and again, for that they had
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:109275:48"/> 
               <hi>made his name to be prophaned among the Gentiles</hi> by their wicked lives. Indeed the doctrine is holy and good, and no way to be charged with the faults of the perſons, yet the men of the world judge of the doctrine, the worth and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs whereof they know not, by the works and fruits which they ſee and know; and conclude there is no ſuch holineſs, goodneſs, power in Gods School, becauſe no more appears in their lives. Therefore the Apoſtle would have <hi>young women obedient to their own husbands, that the word of God be not blaſphemed, and ſervants faithful to their maſters, that they may adorn the doctrine of God our Saviour.</hi> See Tit. 2.5, 10. 1 Tim. 6.1.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> hereby they may further the converſion of the uncalled. How is that, may ſome ſay? I anſwer, when they ſhall evidently ſee, what a broad difference there is betwixt their own lives, and the lives of the godly, they may by Gods bleſſing be convinced, that they are out of the way of life. When their experience ſhall teach
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:109275:48"/> them, that in thoſe whom they have oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en reviled and condemned, nothing is found worthy to be blamed, they may be brought to feel ſhame and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condemning accuſation in their own conſciences: when they behold ſuch worthy fruits of religion in the lives of others, as even they that will not be good, cannot but commend and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire; they be drawn to ſome liking of religion, allured to look into it, to enquire and hearken after it, to be acquainted with thoſe that teach and profeſs it, till at length they be taken in Gods net. Whereas by blemiſhing their profeſſion, they hinder the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of others, hearten and harden the wicked in rebellious courſes, in hatred or diſlike of Gods truth (who think they have good cauſe to hate it, ſeeing it produceth no better effects in thoſe that follow it) and ſo drives them fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from grace and Gods kingdome.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſon </seg>3</label> juſtice and gratitude re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it. For this calling is honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and honoureth us: it makes us of Gods houſhold, children of God and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:109275:49"/> the Church, members of the Son of God, ſetteth before us a kingdome, a crown of erernal glory as the prize for which, the goal to which we muſt runne. Is not this a great dignity? Is not this ſo worthy a calling, worthy honouring? are we not guilty of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible unthankfulneſs, unrighteouſneſs, if we do not honour it all we are able?</p>
            <p>Before we come to application,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> it ſhall not be amiſs, for further explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the point, to anſwer one queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how do Chriſtians honour or diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour their calling?</p>
            <p>Sundry waies;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> but theſe are the principal.</p>
            <p n="1"> 1. They honour it by growing up to an holy dexterity and skilfulneſs in the trade of Chriſtianity: when they ſo receine the word, as they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in knowledge and holineſs, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſtill more and more to abound and excell in ſpiritual underſtanding, maturity of judgement, power and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to ſubdue evil and do good. Contrariwiſe, they diſgrace Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity by non-proficiency, when after
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:109275:49"/> much teaching they continue ſilly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, babiſh, ignorant, ſticking and ſtumbling in the very grounds and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieſt points of religion, ever learning, and never attaining to any ſolid, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, orderly knowledge of Diuinity.</p>
            <p n="2"> 2. They honour it by ſtedfaſt perſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the holy doctrine they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived againſt all contrary blaſts of vain mouths, when they are ſo rooted and grounded in the truth, that they are able to ſtand firme and unmoveable againſt the enticing words of corrupt Teachers, yea to trie their ſpirits, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover and avoid them. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, they diſhonour it by being reeds and weathercocks in religion, when they hearken unto, and ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be ſeduced by the ſubtilties of impoſtors, and glorious ſhews of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Angels of light, vomit up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the wholeſom doctrine they have taken down, and drink in the lying words of deceitful workmen.</p>
            <p n="3"> 3. They honour it by an unſpotted converſation; when like <hi>Zachary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> They <hi>walk in all the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:109275:50"/> of the Lord, blameleſs, and are</hi> (as the <hi>Philippians</hi> are exhorted to be) <hi>unblameable, ſincere, harmleſs, without rebuke, ſhining as lights in the world,</hi> that is, ſo frame their lives, as they cannot juſtly be accuſed of any open and groſs ſin after their calling. They diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour it, by falling into reproachful and ſcandalous evils.</p>
            <p n="4"> 4. They honour it by abounding in fruits of righteouſnefs, when they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to be full of good works, holy, juſt, profitable actions, ever to be ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and doing that which is agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the word of grace, and may ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God, edefie the inward, or help the outward man in themſelves or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ever to be exerciſed in one good work or other; in a word, when they endeavour ſeriouſly, that their practiſe may anſwer their teaching and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. They diſhonour it by barrenneſs, fruitleſneſs, careleſs neglect of good works, when they place religion only or principally in knowing or talking, profeſs piety, but expreſs it not in their practiſe, or do not conſtantly
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:109275:50"/> ſhew forth mercy and equity in all their actions, ſo that the very wicked can tax them for the want of theſe things.</p>
            <p n="5"> 5. They honour it by bridling and moderating affections, manifeſting Chriſtian meekneſs (when occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of being provoked are offered) equanimity, confidence and joy in God, when he takes away good things; or brings evil upon them. They diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour it, by ſuffering paſſions, now ſtirred by ſome adverſe and ingrateful occurrences, to overflow the banks and break out into unſeemly exceſs, when they can keep no mean or mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in their anger, are fearful above meaſure, altogether heartleſs at the approaching of danger, grieve immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately for loſſes and croſſes. For worldlings, ſeeing the children of God ſo impotent, impatient, timorous, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, think within themſelves, ſurely there is no ſuch joy in theſe mens reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, no ſuch power in faith as Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers would perſwade us.</p>
            <p n="6"> 6. They honour it by union and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of hearts and tongues, when
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:109275:51"/> they ſweetly conſpire and are knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in judgement and affection, as the boards and curtains of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by rings and tenons, minding ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame thing, walking by the ſame rule. They blemiſh it by mutual jars, vvars, diſſentions, eſpecially in matters of Religion.</p>
            <p n="7"> 7. Laſtly, they honour it by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in religion, vvhen they are called to ſuffer great things for it: holding on in the way of life, when ſhowres of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution falling, threaten to drown them: willing and chearful forgoing the deareſt things for the Goſpel. They diſhonour it by ſpiritual cowardife and apoſtaſie, ſtarting back from the truth becauſe of the Croſs, ſhrinking away from the love, profeſſion, practice of godlineſs, leſt they ſhould be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and perſecuted. This makes men think Religion is worth nothing, for which they that know and have profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, will loſe nothing: this makes men ſay, theſe love the world and the things of the world, as well as others, for they will yield to any thing, rather
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:109275:51"/> than part with living, liberty, life.</p>
            <p>This inſtruction thus confirmed and opened, ferveth <hi>firſt</hi> to reprove many that deſire to be counted and called Chriſtians, but anſwer not their ſtile. Some, notwithſtanding all our preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are unexpert in the word of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, in the art of godlineſs, grow not in knowledge, but ſtand at a ſtay like dwarfes, and dwel perpetual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iy upon that <hi>a. b. c.</hi> of Religion; which they learned long ago. Some of good age and long ſtanding, have begun to totter and turn after ſeducing ſpirits, which promiſe to open unto them a new way, that they may find reſt and peace to their ſouls, wherein they may walk without a Conſcience. Some, for fear of worldly troubles, let good cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes fall to the ground. But above all others this point thunders againſt thoſe, who by their diſordered lives, bring ſhame not only upon themſelves, but upon Chriſtianity in general. Its to be lamented, that ſome by idleneſs in their callings, pride, unthriftineſs, undutifulneſs to Governours, unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:109275:52"/> in dealings, ſlipperineſs in promiſes, rigor in ſtanding upon and proſecuting their own right to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, diſcords and ſuch like groſs faults, appearing in their lives, give the wicked occaſion of condemning our whole <hi>brotherhood,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> 1 Pet. 2.17.</note> and make Religion aſhamed that ever ſhe knew them, yea bluſh and hide her face, if they do but look at her, or challenge any acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with her. And do we ſerve our Religion thus, (Beloved) in which we hope to be ſaved? Do we look ſhe ſhould comfort us, plead for us, lead us to heavenly glory, and yet we deal with her, as <hi>Judas</hi> did with <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that is, daily deliver her up to be mocked, ſcourged, crucified, pierced by the ſpears and arrows of ungodly mens venomous tongues? Do we not fear, leſt if we continue to be a ſhame to our fathers houſe, expoſing it to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy and obloquie in the world, we be caſt out at length as baſtards and bond ſlaves, leſt if we be a ſhame to the Goſpel, the Author of the Goſpel be aſhamed of us in that great day.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:109275:52"/>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> all that call upon the Name of Chriſt, and are called after his Name, muſt hence be ſpurred and ſtirred up to anſwer their calling, eſpecially by an holy and unblameable life. Brethren, let us ſtudy every man in his place to be an ornament and credit to Religion. Whatſoever things tend to the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of our holy profeſſion, let us <hi>think on them and do them,</hi> embrace and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after them: whatſoever things we know, or juſtly ſuſpect will diſparage and bring an aſperſion upon our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, avoid, abhor them. Away with the works of darkneſs, let them not be ſeen among us, they are moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly, unſeaſonable in Chriſtians. What a ſhame is it that thoſe who are called to ſo great and glorious things, ſhould live like the baſe ſcullions of the Devil? <hi>ought we not to walk in the fear of our God, becauſe of the reproach of our enemies? that we may give no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the adverſary to ſpeak reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully?</hi> Let us, oh let us ſtrive to be ſuch manner of perſons for holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation and godlineſs, that our very
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:109275:53"/> lives may proclaim to all men, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our hearts, hopes, countrey, portion is above, not in this world, that in our words and works wicked Men may ſmell the fragranſie, and behold the majeſty and glory of Religion to their aſtoniſhment, and be compelled to ſay, theſe are kindly Chriſtians indeed, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the Name they bear, <hi>the ſeed which the Lord hath bleſſed.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Eſa. 61.9.</note> Conſider I pray you (for I would gladly ſtrike this nail a little further) 1. That profeſſion ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from ſutable practice, is a great Enemy of Chriſts Kingdom Unreform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Proteſtants muſt be content to be ranked among adverſaries, as well as Turks and Pagans, and its hard to tell which is moſt dangerous. For 1. theſe fight only from without the City of God, and who can look for any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from them, who profeſs hatred and enmity againſt the Church? Thoſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving within the bounds and bowels of the Church, put weapons into the hand both of forrain and domeſtick loes, ſecretly encourage, ſtrengthen, arm them againſt Religion, while they
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:109275:53"/> ſeem to be Friends. 2. Neither ſhould external enemies have any power to hurt the Church, if the ſins of thoſe that are in the Church, did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord to become her Enemy, to pull down her wall, and give her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the uncircumciſed. 3. The bad lives of Chriſtians are a great hindrance of the Churches increaſe. For when the Men of the world ſee them as earthly midded, as covetous, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious, and (in a word) in many things as blame worthy as themſelves, they applaud and ſettle themſelves with more confidence on the dregs or dunghil of their own curſed condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as giving ſufficient hope of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they think our doctrine, touching the neceſſity of holineſs and univerſal obedience in them that ſhall be ſaved, to be vanity and falſhood, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve they need no more repentance than they have (which indeed is none at all) and <hi>ſo come not to Chriſt that they might have life:</hi> vvhereas a good liſe is a good oratour, perſwading and calling others to goodneſs, wooing and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:109275:54"/> the minds even of rude aliens to an approbation of it, and ſo prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them to be further wrought upon by the word of grace. Whence the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth Wives to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection from this reaſon, that <hi>ſuch Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands as obey not the word, may be won by the converſation of the Wives.</hi> Were we ſuch Chriſtians as we ought to be (ſaith an Ancient) ſuch as bleſſed <hi>Paul,</hi> there would be no Gentiles (no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane men) left among us. We might draw many worlds to the faith.</p>
            <p n="2"> 2. A bad life in Chriſtians makes way for corruption in judgement, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of Chriſt, and the height of wickedneſs. For 1. God being provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by mens impounding or impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his truth in unrighteouſneſs, and partial walking in his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in judgement gives them over to deluſions, leaves them to fall into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and damnable opinions. 2. When men are not what they profeſs and know they ought to be, it cannot be but they feel themſelves often ſtung, laſhed, judged by the word of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:109275:54"/> God and their own Conſciences. Wherefore to be rid of this trouble and torment, and get liberty from Gods yoke (the ſtrictneſs whereof they cannot endure) Firſt, they begin to deſire (and then labour to perſwade themſelves) that ſome things which they have learned may be falſe, or at leaſt doubtful, not very certain, they invent (or fetch from the Devils forge) colours, excuſed defences of that they mean not to amend, wicked and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtical concluſions encouraging to continue in their courſe, till at length the ſpirit being wearied and departing, they fall to open prophaneneſs, grow extremely impudent and obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in ſin, and ſo their latter end be worſe than their beginning. Wouldſt thou have me ſpeak more plainly? Art thou a Chriſtian in name, but li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt not like a Chriſtian? Take heed, thou art in danger to be given over to hereſie, to believe Doctrines of Devils, or wholly to forſake the way of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, to return to thy vomit and wallowing in the mire, to become a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:109275:55"/> ſtinking ſnuff or vapour in the noſtrils of all men, yea ſeven-fold more the child of hell than when thou didſt firſt begin to profeſs Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3"> 3. As God expects more duty from his own than others, ſo their unholy lives diſagreeing from their holy cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, kindle his anger, more than the ſins of others. <hi>He will be ſanctified in them that draw near him. You only have I known of all the families of the earth, therefore I will viſit you for all your ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</hi> He takes it moſt unkindly to be diſhonoured by his own people. He will wink at the wickedneſs of ſtrangers, when thoſe of his family ſhall be ſure to ſmart for their diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and worthily. For (as one ſaith) if Gentiles live filthily, its not a thing to be wondred at, nor worthy of ſo deep cenſure: but for Chriſtians, who enjoy ſo many glorious favours of God, to live wickedly, is a thing intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p n="4"> 4. Chriſtians, not Miniſters only, ſhould be lights or candles ſhining and ſhewing to others the way to ſalvation.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:109275:55"/> If then by the dark and foggy cloud of carnal converſation, we lead them into the pit, how ſhall we anſwer our Judge? Dread we not that ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>Curſed is he that cauſeth the blind to err in the way?</hi> Indeed the wicked who take occaſion from our unworthy walking to ſpeak evil of the way of God, or to wander in the way of death, ſhall periſh in their iniquity; but we who give the occaſion ſhall not eſcape. Truly, when I hear a man thus taxed, Oh ſuch an one is one of theſe forward fellows, who love Scripture, Prayer, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, and yet he will ſwagger in ſome company as well as others, or, he hath ſo deceived me, that I will take heed how henceforth I truſt or entertain under my roof any of that feather, I cannot but ſay within my ſelf, <hi>It were better a milſtone were hanged about his neck and be caſt into the depth of the Sea,</hi> than he ſhould by ſuch un-Goſpel-like carriage, and diſcoloured manners, lay ſuch a ſtumbling block in the world.</p>
            <p n="5"> 5. Think with your ſelves, what comfort can any man have in that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:109275:56"/> life which fighteth with his profeſſion, in that profeſſion which is controlled by his life, to which his life daily gives the lie, which will certainly be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement and witneſs againſt him in the great day? If it be a ſhame for one pretending himſelf a Grammarian, to ſpeak incongruouſly, a Muſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to play or ſing unskilfully, howgreat a ſhame is it in the ſight of God and his holy Angels, for one to profeſs and make ſhew of Chriſtianity, and yet ſo groſly to fail in obſerving and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the rules of it, that his own works condemn him in the gate? What a ſhame is it laſtly, that thoſe who by their lives ought to condemn the unclean world (as <hi>Noah</hi> did by his obedience, and all ought, who hope to <hi>be aſſeſſors or benchers with Chriſt</hi> in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the world) ſhould give the world juſt cauſe to condemn their lives? I would gladly take off mine hand and make an end, but the point holdeth me, as if it were loth to leave you, till you were perſwaded. I beſeech you <hi>ſet your hearts to all theſe words which I teſtifie unto you
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:109275:56"/> this day, and let them ſink down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ears,</hi> yea into your ſouls. <hi>Let your converſation be ſuch as becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt, walk worthy of God who hath called you to his Kingdom and glory,</hi> that you may by a real demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the power of Religion, ſtop the mouths of fooliſh and ignorant men, who would be barking againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by practiſe and expreſſions of holineſs, muzzle or make aſhamed the ſlanderous brood of Antichriſt, who charge us to deny or contemn inherent holineſs. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid once, <hi>Goe to the Piſmire;</hi> ſo ſay I, Go the little Bees, conſider their ways and be aſhamed of irregular lives, of ill compoſed man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, when you ſee their little cels or hony-combs ſo artificially and accurat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly framed. Conſider &amp; remember often, that your Chriſtian calling calls for &amp; requires great circumſpection &amp; watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, great purity and uprightneſs. See you not how careful ſome Men are when they walk or ride in a fair new fuit, to keep it from ſpotting? So muſt you your heavenly vocation. Speak,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:109275:57"/> do nothing but that which beſeems your calling, and you ſhall not eaſily offend in word or work. What ſhall I ſay? no more but this, let's either be ſuch indeed as our names import and report to others, or elſe caſt away the names and call our ſelves from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters we ſerve; and the Lord grant that whoſoever heareth or readeth may be perſwaded (or this doctriue may put a ſting into his conſcience, never giving him reſt, till he reſolve) to lead the life of a Chriſtian. And ſo I paſs on to</p>
            <p>The third inſtruction, <hi>A Chriſtians walking worthy of his calling, is from God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All ability in believers to grace and adorn their profeſſion, is Gods gift. Therefore doth the Apoſtle beg this grace at the hands of God for the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians.</hi> And there is good reaſon for it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, no man is of <hi>himſelf ſufficient to think,</hi> much Ieſs to accompliſh <hi>that which is good.</hi> This, that great Apoſtle, who <hi>was taken up into the third heaven,</hi> confeſſeth and confirmeth in himſelf;
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:109275:57"/> therefore all the ſufficiency of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful muſt needs be from that <hi>Father of lights, from whom deſcendeth every good and perfect gift.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, God gives the firſt grace, whereby they begin both <hi>to deny ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> to renounce all that ſpiritual uncleanneſs of ſin, which is contrary to their calling, and to do thoſe good works, to which they are called, to bring forth new fruits of holineſs and righteouſneſs, a greeable to their new calling.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he continues and confirms this grace or gracious work by a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent. <hi>upholds them in their integrity, stabliſheth their hearts in holineſs,</hi> gives wiſdom to eſpie and ſhun the ſnares of the tempter, <hi>Delivers from every evil work</hi> (and conſequently preſerves from ſhameful fals diſgracing their cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) waters them as a garden, that they may be fruitful in good works, which are a comely ornament to their profeſſion.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, he limiteth or reſtraineth their adverſaries, ſpiritual, corporal, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:109275:58"/> ſolliciting to defection from the faith, or tempting to ſin in conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation (ſuffers them not to affault his children, when, where, with what wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, with what force and fury they would) or elſe miniſtreth ſtrength to withſtand and overcome them. Now he that curbs or puts to flight the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies which would draw us to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable acts, muſt needs be the cauſe of our honourable ſtanding in the day of battel, and conſequently of our winning credit to our calling.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, haſt thou eſcaped many dangerous pit-falls, and quick-ſands in which others have been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, many foul ſins of youth, of age, which have foiled others, and defiled both them and their profeſſion, Haſt thou as a brave Souldier of Jeſus Chriſt, warded or repelled thoſe blows of temptation, which have brought o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers on their on knees, or driven them from their ſtation? Haſt thou purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the name and repute of a worthy Chriſtian, by a godly, harmleſs, meek, ſober, peaceable converſation, gained
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:109275:58"/> honour not only to thy ſelf, but to the general calling of Chriſtianity, and ſo ſent abroad the ſmell of the ointment of thy graces, that others have been thereby induced to ſpeak honourably of Religion for thy ſake? Be not proud of it, its Gods work in thee, aſcribe the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it wholly to him who <hi>keeps back his children from evil, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms them in good,</hi> without whom we have no ſtedfaſtneſs, no power to live well, or hold out in good cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but ſhould certainly after we have <hi>begun in the ſpirit, end in the fleſh.</hi> Its truly ſaid of an Enemy, the leaſt temptation, if God forſake us, and ſuffer the Devil to work as pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully as he can, will be intolerable; invincible.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Doſt thou deſire to honour thy Chriſtian calling by walking as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeems the Goſpel? Do for thy ſelf, what <hi>Paul</hi> did for his <hi>Theſſalonians;</hi> ſend every day poſt to the Court of heaven, none other but thine own heart, on the winged horſe of Prayer.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:109275:59"/> Spread thy petition, as <hi>Hezek.</hi> his letter, before the Lord; ſay unto him Lord, as thou haſt made me <hi>partaker,</hi> make me alſo worthy of the <hi>heavenly calling,</hi> give grace that whiles I live, I may ſhew ſuch behaviour, as is fitting the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable condition to which thou haſt brought me. Let me die, rather than I ſhould admit or commit any thing which might impair the reputation of Religion and cauſe Chriſtianity to find worſe entertainment in the world: <hi>Guide me therefore by thy counſel, till thou receive me to glory; hold me by thy right hand, ſtrengthen me with thine own might, turn from me ſhame and contempt, order my ſteps in thy word, and let no iniquity have dominion over thy ſervant, keep my ſpirit ever waking and watchful againſt ſin, ſtabliſh my heart in thy fear, my feet in the way of thy precepts, enable me to continue holy and faithful unto death, and lead me in the way everlaſting to the land of righteouſneſs.</hi> This is the way to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this excellent grace, and he that perſeveres earneſtly begging it, adding thereunto holy endeavours, making the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:109275:59"/> matter of his prayer; the matter of his practiſe, ſhall be preſerved from op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious evils.</p>
            <p>The ſecond petition of <hi>Paul</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, wherein ſuch things are begged as mainly and neceſſarily conduce to the honouring of a Chriſtians calling, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by undaunted conſtancy and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance in the time of tribulation. The means are two, 1. General. 2 Special.</p>
            <p>The general is, fulfilling all the good pleaſure of his goodneſs. By good pleaſure, I underſtand Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree and promiſe of beſtowing on his children all ſpiritual bleſſings needful for the attainment of eternal glory, or his love and favour now begun to be executed and manifeſted to the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians,</hi> by effects and real gifts ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying ſalvation; this is ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the cauſe. What is the root, fountain, and foundation of this good pleaſure? the goodneſs of God, that is, the kind and gracious nature of God, whereby he is ready to deal bountifully with his creature. The meaning then is, we pray, that the Lord
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:109275:60"/> would accompliſh and finiſh all thoſe good things, he hath intended to work in you and for you, that he would give the fulneſs and perfection of all thoſe graces, wherewith of his meer grace and goodneſs he hath purpoſed, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and already begun to enrich you. The words may admit two other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings and interpretations, for they may be turned [all the well-pleaſing of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs] that is, all that goodneſs and holineſs which is acceptable and well-pleaſing to God. And again [All the deſire of goodneſs] that is, all the good and godly deſires of your hearts. But this latter ſenſe is barren and not ſo ſuitable to the Apoſtles words and ſcope, &amp; the former is included in that which we gave in the firſt place, which I judge to be fulleſt, moſt proper, and therefore moſt worthy to be preferred and followed.</p>
            <p>The inſtructions to be drawn out of this clauſe are three.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That all good in man is from the meer goodneſs of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatſoever grace God willeth to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:109275:60"/> and worketh in his children, it flows only from his free grace. <hi>God</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>God worketh in us both to will and to do, of his good pleaſure.</hi> You ſhall find the Scripture exemplifying this point in particulars, aſcribing all the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving benefits of God beſtowed on his people, to his grace and good will, ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or predeſtination to life, redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, remiſſion of ſins, juſtification, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, vocation, revelation of the myſtery of the Goſpel, and giving of knowledge and wiſdom, ſpiritual vivification, and conſequently ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, regeneration, comfort and hope after their calling, ability for the faithful diſcharge of the duties of their callings, deliverance from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, confirmation and perſevetance, glorification. Reaſon proveth the ſame.</p>
            <p>Firſt, its a ſure principle in Divinity,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> the moſt free will of God (which is all one with his goodneſs) is the firſt and ſupreme cauſe of all things. If God be not every way the firſt cauſe, he hath either an equal, or a ſuperior, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:109275:61"/> ſequently is not God. Nothing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth induce and more him to do good to his creature, but his own goodneſs. If ſomething with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him ſhould move his will, that thing muſt needs be in nature before him, and more worthy than he, he muſt depend upon it, and ſuffer from it, but theſe things cannot agree to the nature of the firſt cauſe. Wherefore ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we muſt confeſs there is no grace and holineſs in man which ſpringeth not from the ſole goodneſs of God, or elſe deny a moſt certain Canon of Religion, and ſpoil God of his nature, and prerogative royal.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> man cannot by any deſert provoke God to be good and bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to him. For 1. while he is unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, there is no goodneſs in him, nothing truly good can come from him: he is dead in ſins, wholly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and abominable; his reaſon is blind, his heart rebellious, his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom enmity to God. 2. The good gifts which are in man juſtified and renewed, and the exerciſe of them, cannot (if
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:109275:61"/> we will ſpeak properly) be an impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive provoking cauſe of Gods augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting theſe gifts. Becauſe 1. God pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in his eternal Councel before the world, to beſtow or work that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and therefore it being an effect of Gods will, cannot be a cauſe of the ſame. 2. Nothing temporary in man, can be a cauſe of that which is eternal in God: therefore God was not moved by any thing fore ſeen in time, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree this increaſe. If nothing beſides his own goodneſs, moved him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree to work it, nothing elſe moves him actually to work it, elſe the decree and the execution of it do not agree.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God is not bound to man,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> owes him nothing, being an abſolute Monarch, who hath moſt full and free power to do with his own what he liſt. If he give, his bounty is thereby manifeſted; if he withhold, he wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth none. Now if we cannot poſſibly by any means make God our debtor, it followeth, that whatſoever good we have or receive, it proceeds from his only kindneſs.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:109275:62"/>
            <p>Firſt then here are confuted,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> firſt ſome falſe Doctrines of the Papiſts; As 1. That a ſinner not reconciled to God, may by preparatory works of repentance, deſerve in ſome ſort juſtification, which they call the merit of congruity. I am not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant how one of the Maſter-daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Myſtical <hi>Babylon</hi> goes about to ſalve this point by a favourable interpretation; but if there were no ſnake in this graſs, <hi>I</hi> marvel why ſome of great name and note a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them (who doubtleſs under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood well enough the tenets of their own times) vviſhed the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing and abandoning of it. 2. That Man is able by a power na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally inherent in his will, if it be but helped and vvakened by grace, to believe and convert. Indeed they diſavovv this Opinion (as whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters are ſometimes aſhamed of their baſtards, but they muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, will they nill they, to father it. For the vvritings of the Jeſuits (who in this point are hotly oppoſed by their
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:109275:62"/> own pue-fellows the Dominicans) witneſs that beſides the outward means, they acknowledge nothing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to converſion, but inſpiration, illumination, excitation, they require not any ſuper-natural habit or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple infuſed into the will by which it may be diſpoſed and elevated to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the act of faith: they make effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual grace to be nothing elſe, but Gods perſwading and calling Men in ſuch a time, place, manner, as he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees moſt agreeable to their diſpoſition, inſpiring ſuch motions, as he ſeeth by their free-will they will embrace: yea, ſome of them ingenuouſly confeſs, that the firſt radical cauſe of the effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of grace is the co-operation of mans will. 3. That men may merit (yea o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for them) increaſe of grace, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance and reſtauration by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, when they have fallen. How theſe Romiſh Opinions are repugnant to the doctrine in hand, grounded upon the plain words of the Apoſtle, he is blind that ſeeth not. Secondly, the doctrine of the <hi>Arminians.</hi> who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:109275:63"/> that the ground and cauſe of Gods election; is foreſight of ſaith, and perſeverance in perſons to be elected, that God ſends the means of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and offers his grace to this or that people, becauſe he did ſee and know they would with humble readineſs embrace and rightly uſe that grace and come when he called. 1. Theſe are right builders of <hi>Babel:</hi> Is not this moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible &amp; moſt wicked coufuſion, to thruſt the firſt cauſe out of his rank, and ſeat the ſecond in his room? to ſubject the Creator (or make him inferiour) to his creature? to fetch the firſt riſe or ſpring of mans ſalvation from man? It is no leſs abſurd and blaſphemous (for ought I can ſee) to ſay, Gods will had or needed an external moving cauſe in ordaining things, than to ſay his power had or needed an outward help in creating things. The Papiſts ſhall riſe up in judgement and condemn them, ſome of whom do affirm roundly (and confirm as ſoundly) that there is no cauſe in us of Gods predeſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that election is altogether free,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:109275:63"/> without previſion of good works. 2. What faith could God fore-ſee in man not half, but wholly dead in treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes and ſins? what power of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their own converſion in Men of ſtony hearts, altogether impotent to ſpiritual good, mancipated to Satan? 3. Laſtly, where they ſay, God beſtows means of ſalvation upon ſome rather than others, becauſe he ſeeth they will profit better by them, a pur-blind Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt will tell them its manifeſtly falſe. For if that were the reaſon, then the Lord ſhould always ſend his Goſpel and Miniſters to thoſe that are moſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and capable, deny them to thoſe who are moſt hard-hearted and rebellious: but we ſee in Scripture and experience, he often ſends them to thoſe that are worſe than others, as to <hi>Iſrael</hi> a gain-ſaying people, a people of ſtiff and ſteely necks, adamantine hearts, brazen fore-heads,
<note place="margin"> Ezek. 3.6.7. Matt. 11.21.</note> more ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born and inflexible than the Gentils, than the Tirians and Sidonians.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This muſt teach us humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> We have no cauſe to be lifted up
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:109275:64"/> in pride for any good thing we have or can do. For its neither from our ſelves, nor procured and purchaſed from God by any worthineſs or work of ours. Nothing is our own but evil, let us take nothing to our ſelves but ſhame and confuſion. Haſt thou ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, riches, children, bodily ſtrength and activity, friends, gifts of nature, graces of the ſpirit? ſay with <hi>Jacob,</hi> theſe are the riches, the children, the gifts which God hath graciouſly given me. If thou feeleſt at any time ſuch thoughts as theſe ariſing in thy heart; Becauſe of my ſincerity, obedience, hearty and conſtant praying, I have better children, better ſucceſs in the world than others, I am preſerved and delivered out of dangers wherein o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers periſh, judge them to be the iſſue of Satan, that father of pride, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded our firſt parents, and ſtill would all his poſterity, to affectate the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and therefore ſerve theſe cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice eggs, as they deſerve, trample upon them, cruſh them, eaſt them in the Devils face, &amp; know that our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:109275:64"/> is not a cauſe of Gods kindneſs and benignity, but a way or path lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the taſte and feeling of it (God who is faithful having promiſed that whoſoever walk in that way ſhall find him gracious and bountiful) or a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition pre-required in thoſe that ſhall taſte the fruits of his goodneſs, which condition (not man by his own power performeth, but) the grace of God worketh and produceth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> This ſhould ſtir us up to magnifie and extol this goodneſs of God, which giveth us all good things, not onely abundantly, but freely. If all the rivelets of bleſſings, wherewith we are watered, flow from the Sea of his mercy, its meet they ſhould reflow thither by thankſgiving. We ſhould imitate the Marigold, vvhich continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally turneth it ſelf to the Sun, from whom it receiveth juyce. If we have received great kindneſs from one, at whoſe hands vve could never have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected or deſerved any ſuch thing, how are vve affected with it? vve cannot ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily make an end of commending him,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:109275:65"/> nor ſatisfie our ſelves in thanking him. Oh (ſay we) ſuch a man is a mirrour of good nature. When I was a meer ſtranger to him, had none to mediate for me, could give him nothing, nor any way pleaſure him, of his own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, out of his own free diſpoſition, he thus and thus befriended me: Oh how am I bound to him, I ſhall never forget it while I live. How much more (brethren) ſhould the praiſes of the goodneſs of our God be ever in our hearts, in our mouths, who loved us when we were enemies, ſought us when we ſtrayed like loſt ſheep, ſound us when we ſought him not, called us when we reſiſted him, remembreth us when we forget him, keepeth promiſe with us moſt faithfully, when we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful to him, followeth and <hi>ladeth us with his benefits,</hi> when we have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited all by unthankfulneſs, undutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? how ſhould we awaken our dead hearts to admire and glorifie this ſo free mercy of the Lord,
<note place="margin"> 2 Sam. 7.21.</note> and ſay, <hi>for thine own ſake, and according to thine own heart</hi> (O God) haſt thou ſhewed me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:109275:65"/> wretch,
<note place="margin"> Neh. 9.5</note> 
               <hi>leſs than the leaſt of all thy mercies,</hi> all this grace and truth: <hi>bleſſed be thou for ever and ever, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be thy glorious name which is exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above all bleſſing and praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let this ſuffice to have been ſpoken of the firſt leſſon: Now ſecondly, vvhen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Apoſtle prays in this manner for a people excelling many in grace and goodneſs, in the next place we ſet down this concluſion.</p>
            <q> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> Fulneſs of grace is not given at once, but by degrees.</q>
            <p>God is able enough to repleniſh his children with all holineſs, and lift them from the hell of miſery, wherein he finds them, to a ſtate of perfect happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in a moment: yet he pleaeth to proceed ſtep by ſtep in opening and diſplaying to them the treaſures of his goodneſs, and not in an inſtant to powre out upon them all his ſpiritual riches. Therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> compares a <hi>just mans path to the ſhining light that ſhines more and more unto the perfect day.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Pro. 4.18.</note> Hence are theſe Exhortations, <hi>as ye have received of us,
<note place="margin"> 1 Theſ. 4.1</note> how ye ought to walk and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:109275:66"/> pleaſe God, ſo abound more and more, grow in grace, put on the new man, cleanſe your ſelves from all filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit,</hi> and theſe promiſes, <hi>the righteous ſhall grow like a Caedar in</hi> Lebanon, <hi>ye ſhall grow up as the calves of the ſtall,</hi> and the like. For,</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> the Lord ſtoopeth to our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. We are dull in conceiving, ſlow of heart to belieue, like infants, or nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-mouthed veſſels, which receive li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor but by drops. As therefore the loving nurſe or mother in feeding, the wiſe father or ſchool-maſter in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, accommodate themſelves to chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens vveakneſs, rather conſidering vvhat and how they are able to take, than ſtriving to powre in all themſelves are able to give, whereby life or memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry may be over-whelmed: ſo the Lord in diſpenſing of his graces, attempers himſelf and his dealing to the infirm capacity of his ſervants, imparting them by degrees, becauſe they are not fit to receive them otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> as God in the firſt creation made and adorned this ſpacious and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:109275:66"/> ſpecious world, not in a moment, (which to him had been as eaſie) but ſucceſſively in ſix days ſpace, partly that man might learn by his example, to take more time, leiſurely and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly to meditate of his works, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to help man the better to conceive of his workmanſhip, and in what order the parts of the building were joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; (whence many profitable conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations ariſe, whereof this is not the leaſt, the admirable power of the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er appears, in cauſing light and day, before there was any Sun, graſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rain and the like, which we ſhould not have ſeen, if all had been diſpatcht in an inſtant:) ſo in the reparation of the world he perfects ſanctification in his children gradually, by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, that he may lead them to a more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and punctual notice-taking of all his graces in themſelves, and the foot-ſteps of the worker, that is, the ſundry wonderful waies and paſſages of his providence and adminiſtration in the perfecting of them. (Whence they gather much ſweet experimental
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:109275:67"/> knowledge) that he may give occaſion more fully to obſerve, deeply ponder, and highly praiſe his wiſdom and power, which ſhine forth more conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous and illuſtrious, in his making a ſmall grain of grace to prevail againſt a world of corruption, and bringing them thorow ſo many weakneſſes, bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, ſeas of troubles and temptations, falls and foiles, (every of them threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning death) to compleat holineſs and happineſs, than if he had made them perfect at their converſion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> the Lord will have his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren wreſtle for a time in a ſtate of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, that he may train them up in humility, Let them ſee their own impotency, and that all their ſtrength is in him and from him, quicken them to pray, and earneſtly deſire the coming of the kingdom of glory, teach them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe their ſalvation wholly to him, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to value and eſteem his graces, the want whereof hath ſo pinched them, the keeping and increaſe whereof coſts them no ſmall care, ſtrugling, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. Our firſt father received all
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:109275:67"/> his portion at once, (an exceeding great ſtock of grace:) but he quickly forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting both God and himſelf, ſpent it and proved a bankrupt. Wherefore our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father thinks fit to give us ours by little and little, that we may know, and all the days of our life acknowledg our ſelves to be beggers, depend upon him for a continual ſubminiſtration of new grace, learn better to husband and improve that little which he hath put into our hands.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> this Doctrine confutes all thoſe that dream of perfection, attainable in a ſhort moment: As 1. Papiſts, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that in Baptiſm the ſoul is made inherently as pure, ſpotleſs, glorious as the Sun, and grace infuſed by which a man is made able to fulfil the Law. Alas, no marvel men roave ſtrangely, ſpeak abſurdly and ignorantly of the ſtate of grace, and the ſaving workings of the holy Ghoſt, when they have no experience of theſe things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. 2. Familiſts, and ſuch like fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, who boaſt of ſuch a fulneſs of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, that they need no further pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:109275:68"/> who (if their confident affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be believed) have ſo much joy, that they need or deſire no more in heaven, brag that they are paſt the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the hearts deceitfulneſs, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver crave pardon of ſin, and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly tell them that do, they have their pardon on their back, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no uſe of the Law after juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, feel no need of preaching, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Sabbaths, uſe theſe things ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leaſt they ſhould give offence, than for any neceſſity, profeſſing to the ſame purpoſe this to be their opinion, that the new man may be ſo ſtrong as it ſhall not need any means: and to this height they are mounted in a few months, I might truly ſay, days, even by hearing one or two Sermons. Well, we need no other argument (if we be wiſe) to perſwade us to ſtop our ears againſt ſuch erroneous ſpirits, but this, that they boaſt of and arrogate to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the poſſeſſion of ſuch things, as <hi>Paul</hi> the greateſt of the Apoſtles had not attained many years after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, not many before his death, as
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:109275:68"/> appears by his complaint to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> his confeſſion to the <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, this muſt comfort and ſtay thoſe righteous ſouls, who are much dejected becauſe they find much cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and great want of grace in themſelves. I forbid them not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore and grieve for their ſpiritual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, not to ſeek to the fountain for ſupply and perfecting his work in them, only I exhort them not to be diſmaied, nor to conclude they have no grace, becauſe they have not the meaſure they deſire. Thy caſe is the common caſe of all the godly, not one of them but hath his wants to complain of, not one of them but feeleth in himſelf much emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs, great weakneſs of holineſs, much ignorance, vanity, unbeliefe, hardneſs, deadneſs, inordinacy of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, nay evil motions and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations: yea, the better any man is, the more he diſcerneth and groaneth under theſe things, and confeſſeth himſelf far ſhort of perfect fulneſs. Look not the Lord ſhould deal
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:109275:69"/> otherwiſe with thee, than with all <hi>the ſons he brings to glory.</hi> Be content there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore firſt to be a babe in Chriſt, for ſo thou muſt, before thou canſt be a tall man: be content that the ſeeds of grace do firſt poorly peep up and ſprout in the mould of thy heart, which in time will grow to be great herbs, and fill the whole garden. If thou wert recovering of a great ſickneſs, though health ſhould return very ſlowly, wouldſt thou not be glad and praiſe the Author of life? Do here in like manner, rejoyce and bleſs God, that thou art begotten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and come into the new World of new Creatures, though thou wanteſt much of that ſtrength which ſome have attained.</p>
            <p>The third inſtruction is,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Chriſtians ſhould deſire a full meaſure of all graces or ſpiritual gifts.</hi> That which <hi>Paul</hi> beggeth for his <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> every believer ought to deſire for himſelf; but <hi>Paul</hi> deſireth that God would accompliſh in them, all good things needful for their ſalvation. This is further confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in thoſe places, in which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:109275:69"/> prays (or teſtifies that he prayed) for them to whom he writes,
<note place="margin"> Epheſ. 3.19. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>That they might be filled with all knowledge of Gods will, abound more and more in knowledge and in all judgment, be filled with the fruits of righteouſneſs, yea with all the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, made perfect in every good work, to do his will:</hi> thoſe places alſo which exhort to ſuch things, as, <hi>Be ye perfect even as your Father which is in heaven is perfect, be ye filled with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſuch like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And good reaſon. For firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> there is a certain fulneſs attainable in this life, which appeares, becauſe 1. God hath promiſed <hi>to repleniſh and ſatiate the hungry ſoul, to poure his Spirit abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on his people, to fill the earth with the knowledge of himſelf, as the waters cover the ſea, to make the parched ground a pool, the thirſty land ſprings of water, the feeble in the Charch like</hi> David <hi>in ſtrength, ſo that they ſhall mount up with wings like Eagles, run and not be weary, walk and not faint.</hi> Now he that promiſeth, wanteth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will nor power to perform his word, being the All-ſufficient, a moſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:109275:70"/> bountiful Father and Maſter, <hi>Rich to all that call upon him,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> giving liberally and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding no man, delighting in the poſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his ſervants.</hi> 2. The Scripture af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth examples of ſuch as have attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. I ſpeak not of extraordinary per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, (ſuch as the Apoſtles, of whom joyntly it is ſaid, <hi>They were filled with the holy Ghoſt,</hi> as the ſame is affirmed particularly of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> ſuch alſo as were ſundry miniſters &amp; believers in that firſt Church; for example, <hi>Steph'n</hi> &amp; others with him in <hi>Jeruſalem, Barnabas, &amp;c.</hi>) but of ordinary Chriſtians. Doth not the Apoſtle give this honourable teſtimony of the ancient <hi>Romanes,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.14.</note> that he <hi>was perſwaded they were full of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, filled with all knowledge?</hi> Of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> and <hi>Epheſians,</hi> that <hi>they were enriched with all knowledge, utterance, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, prudemce?</hi> Now that which God hath promiſed, and the Saints have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from him, why ſhould not the godly ſtill deſire and hope to obtain? If in any thing this point contradicteth other Scriptures, and the places men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the former Doctrine; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:109275:70"/> fulneſs is either abſolute, ſuch a perfection as admits no defect, this is reſerved for the life to come; or compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, ſuch a meaſure or degree of grace, as ſitteth &amp; falleth into a grown Chriſtian, is anſwerable to the age of a Father in Chriſt, which in reſpect of the weak beginning of young Chriſtians, may be termed fulneſs: this is that we affirm may be found &amp; enjoyed here on earth: wch thing the Apoſtle alſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teacheth; for in the very ſame place where he denies himſelf to be perfect, he calleth himſelf &amp; thoſe believers in <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippi,</hi> that were of good ſtanding and growth in Chriſtianity, perfect, wch ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences ſeemingly contrary, are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled by the fore-named diſtinction.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> this fulneſs is exceeding comfortable, for it gives ſtrong aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the ſpecial and everlaſting love of God. The richer a man grows in grace, the more is his election evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced and ſealed unto him, (becauſe this is the fountain whence all ſaving and gracious gifts, as ſtreams do flow) the more he is conformed to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:109275:71"/> Chriſt, and ſo aſcertained of Chriſts dwelling in him, the nearer he draws to heaven, and the life of Angels, hath more certain teſtimonies and pledges of his ſalvation, and laſtly, the leſs power ſhall any evil, which can befal him, have, to diſquiet his courſe, damp his joy, diſturb his inward peace, or remove him from his ſtedfaſtneſs.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> the more a man abounds with grace, the more able he will be to glorifie God; Firſt, in word, he will be often breaking out into <hi>Pauls</hi> doxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies.
<note place="margin"> Pſal. 63.5. Eph. 5.18, 19.</note> 
               <hi>When the ſoul is ſatisfied as with marrow and fatneſs, the mouth will praiſe God with joyful lips: if the heart be filled with the Spirit, the mouth will be filled with Pſalms and ſpiritual ſongs of hearty thankfulneſs.</hi> Secondly, in works of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience: 1. Active; As abundance of ſpirits in the body, makes one more light and lively: ſo abundance of grace in the heart makes a Chriſtian go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Gods buſineſs more nimbly, ſtrongly, with more chearfulneſs and largeneſs of heart, more ready to do
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:109275:71"/> the good will of God, more fruitful and abundant in all good actions. 2. Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive: As he that is well lined with meat and drink, will beſt endure winter blaſts, and as the body, or any part of it, the fatter it is, the leſs it is pierced with pinching cold, (whence it is, that in greateſt froſts, our eyes never feel cold, becauſe the fatneſs of the white keeps them warm:) ſo the richer any one is in grace, he will bear afflictions the more equally, rejoyce in tribulations more ſweetly, and like the Elephant, walk moſt ſteadily under the greateſt load.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> the beſt have ſome vacuity or emptineſs in them, and therefore ſtand in need of repletion, (for neither doth ſpiritual light ſo perfectly poſſeſs their minds, nor holineſs their wills, that there is not place for increaſe) and theſe heavenly graces are of all things in the world incomparably far the beſt, and worthieſt, as being the very image of God, coming from heaven, and fitting for heaven, excelling fineſt gold, and coſtlieſt pearl a thouſand
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:109275:72"/> times further than theſe excel the mire in the ſtreets. Is not a large portion of ſuch riches worthy to be deſired?</p>
            <p>This reproveth three ſorts;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> 1. Our muddy and baſe minded wordlings, who thirſt indeed after fulneſs, but of Mammon, of earthly and outward bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; they deſire, but what? To ſee <hi>their corn and wine encreaſed, and God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly bringing into their hands, even more than heart can wiſh, to have their bellies filled with his hid treaſure, their garners full, affording all manner of ſtore,</hi> their bags full of gold and ſilver, their <hi>hearts of food and gladneſs,</hi> that they may be able to ſay to their ſouls, with the rich man in the Goſpel, <hi>Soul, thou haſt much good laid up for many years, take thine eaſe, eat, drink, and be merry;</hi> theſe are the things which the men of this generation admire, this is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happineſs their Souls long to find. As for the gifts of the Spirit, the riches and ornaments of the Soul, which make man an Angel among men, abide with him in death, and goe with him into heaven, they are ſo far
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:109275:72"/> from deſiring to be filled with them, that they care not for taſting or being acquainted with them; yea, ſcarcely once think of them, except when they are forced in hearing a Sermon. Alas ſilly-wood-cocks, whoſe whole life is in ſucking the ground! when you ſee a company of little children, buſie as Bees in making houſes, and banquets, and yet, if a ſhower fall, or hunger pinch, take themſelves to their heeles, and ſeek refuge, or relief elſewhere, do you not laugh at their folly? Should you ſend your ſervant to buy in a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-town, ſpices, drugs, wines, and ſuch things of ſpecial price and uſe, and he come again laden with clay, or peble-ſtones; or ſhould you ſee a Merchant undertake a long, painful, perillous, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtly voyage into the remoteſt parts of the world, and return at length fraught with ſand, vile earth, or ſuch baggage, as either he could not carry out of the ſhip with him, or if he did, would not profit him; would ye not ſtand amazed at the mans madneſs? I tell you before hand the terrours of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:109275:73"/> death ſhall open your eyes to ſee, and confeſs the caſe to be your own: that is, that all the ſtudy, thought, care of your whole life, hath been conſumed in heaping up goods, which can do you no good in the day of wrath: or elſe, if your hearts in death be turned into a ſtone, like <hi>Nabals,</hi> (which is much to be feared) you ſhall curſe your ſelves in the dark dungeon of hell, and ſay, Fie upon us idiots, more brutiſh than the beaſts of the field, we never lived the life of men, or reaſonable creatures before God, becauſe in ſo many years we never began to mind, or do, what we were born to mind and do above all things. In the mean time, I wiſh you to conſider, that he cannot be Gods child, who contents himſelf with Gods baſeſt bleſſings. Did you ſee one in a Gentlemans kitchin, ſeeding upon ſcraps, or the courſeſt food in the houſe, you would not doubt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, this is none of the children, but ſome ſcullion, or one that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to the family: apply this to your ſelves, and you ſhall find juſt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:109275:73"/> cauſe to fear, that you are but veſſels of diſhonour, ſlaves, that muſt not abide in the houſe for ever.</p>
            <p n="2"> 2. Prophane Proteſtants are here to be taxed,
<note place="margin"> Ezek. 9.9.</note> who are (or ſtrive to be) <hi>full of wickedneſs, and perverſeneſs,</hi> like <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem; of miſchief, and ſubtilty,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Act. 13.10. Matth. 23.28. Rom. 1.29. Act. 13.45, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> like <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limas; of hypocriſie, and iniquity,</hi> as the Phariſees, <hi>af all unrighteouſneſs,</hi> as the Gentiles; <hi>of envy and wrath,</hi> as the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing <hi>Jews; have mouths full of curſing and deceit, eyes of adultery, tongues of deadly poyſon,</hi> who (in a word) take the high way to be filled with the ſpirit of Satan. As <hi>Abner</hi> ſaid to <hi>Joab,</hi> ſo I to theſe, <hi>Know you not, that it will be bitterneſs in the latter end?</hi> When for every ſugred morſel of ſin, which now goes down ſo pleaſantly, you ſhall receive a double portion of the ſowre ſauce of vengeance? The more you fill your ſelves with the liquor of hell, the more will the Lord fill you with the <hi>dregs of the wine of his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and daſh you like bottles one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another: the more pains you take <hi>to fulfil the luſts of the fleſh,</hi> the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:109275:74"/> more you fill up the meaſure of your ſins; and take heed, <hi>leſt God accompliſh his fury, and fulfil the good pleaſure of his juſtice in your condemnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3"> 3. Many of better proficiency are to be cenſured, who finding in themſelves ſome ſeeds and elementary rudiments of godlineſs, let fall the fails of their deſires, and ſit down well contented. I wiſh this <hi>Corinthian</hi> and <hi>Laodicean</hi>-like fulneſs, be not a ſickneſs too common among Chriſtians; but I fear too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, not of the worſt ſort of our hearers, if once they have but thus far profited, in Chriſtianity, that they can thank God they are much reformed in mind and life, or perſwaded of the truth of their converſion, think themſelves rich enough, they have gotten grace ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſave their ſouls, and now they are well-ſatisfied, they will not trouble themſelves to labour for any more. This is to manifeſt our own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences being witneſſes; we have no queſtions, we feel no poverty of ſpirit, we complain of no wants, our ſecret ſighs, and fervent longings for grace,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:109275:74"/> are dried up and withered, the temper of our ſpirits is cold and dead, as the winter ſeaſon, our affections are grown flat, and frozen, we pleaſe our ſelves in a conceit or ſelf-ſufficiency, and that more holineſs, than we have already attained, is ſuperfluous. But brethren, if we be ſo eaſily, ſo quickly ſatisfied, and glutted with Gods dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (which make true believers more hungry) I teſtifie unto you, we may juſtly fear, that we never rightly taſted, at leaſt never kindly digeſted them, but have all this while dreamed, and been deluded by Satan, and conſequently, doubt of our converſion. Aſſure your ſelves, when God ſhall call us to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count (ſuch a time will come, and how ſoon we know not) we ſhall have ſmall comfort in looking back, and recounting, what a long rich ſpiritual ſeed-time, and harveſt, we have enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, wherein manifold means, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of getting a fair ſtock of grace, have been plentifully afforded, and we in the mean time, like loitering ſons of ſhame, dallying with Gods
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:109275:75"/> bounty, and neglecting to redeem the ſeaſon, have gathered little.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> if the godly muſt deſire, it followeth, that in the uſe of all ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied means, they muſt labour for the accompliſhment of all Gods gracious pleaſure in themſelves, all gifts accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying ſalvation. We muſt not reſt in any meaſure of holineſs, but preſs after perfection of every grace, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſt till we ſee, yea feel powred upon our heads, all the goodneſs that God hath promiſed to ſhew his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in this life. Truly, as the heathen King is reported to have wept, when he heard a Philoſopher ſpeak of more worlds than one, becauſe himſelf had not yet conquered one: ſo its a thing much to be lamented, that whereas God hath provided for his children, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in this world, ſuch a liberal por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of grace, as might make their lives an heaven upon earth; the moſt of us enjoy and receive ſo little: the reaſon whereof is, becauſe we are not cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous enough, we beg not in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, or elſe ſecond not our prayers
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:109275:75"/> with ſuitable endeauours, we aim not at a great meaſure. Alas, that we ſhould be ſo poor, and have a father ſo able, ſo willing to enrich us. I beſeech you therefore, <hi>if there he any conſolation in Chriſt;</hi> if ever you have taſted how <hi>good the Lord is,</hi> ſtick not in beginnings, call upon your ſelves to ſtrive and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour after the higheſt degree of mortification, and power to reſiſt, and conquer remnants of corruptions, the higheſt degree of all poſitive graces, knowledge, faith, love, joy, fear, &amp;c. the higheſt degree of chearful and conſtant obedience, of lively and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful walking before the Lord, the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree of peace and comfort, of ſtrength, ſtedfaſtneſs, boldneſs. The means in which we muſt ſtrive, are 1. A conſtant attending upon publick ordinances (eſpecially the Word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and the Lords Supper) which God hath ſanctified for perfecting the Saints, and by which he is wont more and more to convey his graces into the ſouls of thoſe, who uſe them with pure and prepared hearts. 2. Feeding much
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:109275:76"/> upon Chriſt by application of: he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, drawing and keeping near him in our ſpirits, taking all occaſions of looking up, and ſpeaking to him, often bringing, and baring your hearts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, as husbandmen do the roots of their trees before the Sun: the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe he is not onely <hi>the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of goodneſs,</hi> who makes the ſpirits of thoſe that delight in approaching to him, and walking with him, watered gardens: but alſo, <hi>that Sun of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> whoſe ſweet and quickening heat, doth enliven, regenerate, renew, impregnate with ſpiritual graces and fruits, the inviſible world of believing ſouls, and advance the ſame to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſpiritually, as this viſible Sun doth creatures in this viſible world na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally: the more communion any one hath with this fountain, this Sun, the more grace he ſhall be ſure to have. 3. Plying God with fervent prayers, ſpringing from ſpiritual hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and deep ſenſe of our own beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, intreating him by the wind of his Spirit, <hi>To blow upon the garden of our
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:109275:76"/> hearts, that the ſpices thereof may flow forth.</hi> 4. Improving,
<note place="margin"> Song 4.16.</note> and blowing up grace by ſpiritual exerciſes of reading, finging, meditation, conference, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate communication of gifts. 5. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuation, purging out by renewed repentance, ſuch matter as might cauſe an oppilation of thoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, in which grace ſhould flow unto us; for Chriſt, to whom we are joyned as members (if we be believers) is an head <hi>full of the holy Ghoſt, full of grace &amp; truth;</hi> if we defire to receive abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his fulneſs, we muſt take heed, the nerve of faith, and pipes of Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances be not ſtopped, or made ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual in us by our worldlineſs, dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſpirit, luſts, or ſome known corruption too indulgently handled. 6. Laying our hearts low before the Lord, in humiliation and humility. For the low valleys, becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive moſt dew and rain into their boſoms, are moſt fruitful: ſo the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble heart, the broken ſpirit, is of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers a ſubject moſt capable of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſhall be moſt plentifully watered
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:109275:77"/> with the ſhowres of grace, becauſe the God of all grace and goodneſs hath promiſed to dwell in ſuch a ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Do you now ſee the way? Walk in it, that you may find reſt to your ſouls. Do you know theſe things? <hi>Bleſſed are you if you do them.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſtill ſuffer the word of exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the uſe of theſe means, propound this mark to your ſelves, <hi>To be filled with the holy Ghoſt, with wiſdom and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, with all riches of full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, with all might, patience, and long ſufferance, with joy, and peace in believing, to be full of good works, of mercy, and good fruits, of thankfulneſs, and Gods praiſes all the day.</hi> Oh ſpare no pains for ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up abundance of grace, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid of his children <hi>the fruit of the womb, happy is the man that hath his quiver full of them:</hi> ſo may I much more truly ſay of the fruits of the ſpirit, happy is the man that hath his heart full of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: here only covetouſneſs, yea vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is lawful, and holy. Say not within your ſelves, this is an hard, doctrine, and impoſſioſe. What? we cannot be
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:109275:77"/> perfect here; ſuch thoughts are promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Satan, to make you lazie, and rob you of your crown. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was not ignorant of this, yet <hi>He forgat the things that were behind, and ſtretched himſelf unto the things before, yea laboured, if it were poſſible, to attain to the reſurrection of the dead.</hi> So that, though we cannot reach an entire and compleat perfection, yet we may, and muſt grow ſtill more and more perfect; and though our attainments ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in this life overtake, and equal our deſires; yet as he that ſhoots at the noon-Sun, though he be ſure he ſhall never hit the mark, is ſure to ſhoot higher than he that aims at a buſh: ſo if we deſire, and aim at the higheſt pitch of grace, vve ſhall be ſure to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip our fellows, and attain ſuch a meaſure, as ſhall make our profeſſion, both comfortable to our own ſouls, exemplary to our brethren, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the eyes of ſtrangers.</p>
            <p>And thus much touching this branch of <hi>Pauls</hi> prayer: for though I perceive there is one point more couched in it,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:109275:78"/> which have not been handled; yet for brevity, I will refer, and reſerve it, to be wrapt up (as well it may) in the concluſion of the next member, which now remaineth to be opened; wherein a ſecond thing is craved by the Apoſtle, as a neceſſary, and more ſpecial means of making them worthy their calling.</p>
            <p>The words are <hi>[and the work of faith with power]</hi> where confider 1. The bleſſing asked, which is, fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the work of faith. By work of faith, may either be meant the exerciſe, operations, fruits of faith; faith, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, acting, labouring, producing ſuch works as are proper to her: or faith, as it is Gods work in man, the grace, or habit of faith, wrought by God in our hearts. I take this latter ſenſe; the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference is not great, and this includes the other.</p>
            <p n="2"> 2. The efficient cauſe of it, Gods power: For ſo I underſtand thoſe laſt words <hi>[with power]</hi> that is, by his own Almighty power, joyning them to the word <hi>[fulfil]</hi> rather than to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:109275:78"/> 
               <hi>[faith]</hi> which worketh powerfully in believers. The meaning then is, as if the Apoſtle had ſaid; But above all other graces, we make ſuit unto God for the perfecting of that bleſſed and ſingular work of faith, which his grace hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in you, and that by the ſtrength of his own right hand, who is omnipotent, and all-ſufficient.</p>
            <p>The inſtructions to be gathered from theſe words follow, whereof the firſt is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The beſt faith hath wants.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> Underſtand it of faith in the ſons of men in this world. Its plain in our text. The Apoſtle witneſſeth in his former Epiſtle, that this people <hi>received the word with much aſſurance,</hi> that <hi>their faith to Godward was ſpread abroad in other places.</hi> In this very Chapter, he hath <hi>given thanks to God; that their faith grew exceedingly:</hi> yet here he tels us, they have need to be prayed for, that God would perfect their faith. A cloud of witneſſes doth further confirm it. <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith did limp, and halt a little, when he hearkned to the counſel of <hi>Sarah,</hi> in going in to
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:109275:79"/> 
               <hi>Hagar,</hi> for he conſented to the uſe of unlawful means, for bringing about Gods purpoſe: likewiſe when through fear, he ſained <hi>Sarah</hi> to be his fiſter: weakneſs appeared in <hi>Sarahs</hi> ſaith, when ſhe laughed at the promiſe of a ſon: in <hi>Jacobs,</hi> vvhen tidings of <hi>Eſaus</hi> coming did ſo affright, and diſtreſs him, though he had a promiſe of Gods preſence and protection in that journey: in <hi>Davids,</hi> when in his haſte and fear he ſaid, <hi>I am caſt out of thy ſight, all men are liars,</hi> when he fained himſelf mad: in <hi>Peters,</hi> when being afraid of his skin, in the high Prieſts hall, he denied his Maſter.</p>
            <p>And no marvel, for firſt, if know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge be imperfect in all Chriſtians, confidence cannot be perfect in any: How can the heart deſire, or cleave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this, or that, further than the mind apprehends it as true and good? I can. not reſt upon a man, believing he will do this or that for me, further than I know him. The meaſure of faith in the will, depends upon, and ſollows the meaſure of light in the underſtanding, (I mean in reſpect of latitude, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:109275:79"/> or in intrinſecal vigour; for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe I know, there may be great faith, where there is but ſmall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as in many Martyrs,) A man may know more than he believes (ſo do many wicked men in the Church) but he cannot believe more than he knows. Now its certain, that we know but in part; for neither do we appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the whole object of knowledge, that is, the whole body of divine truth, (my meaning is, vve know not all things to be known, vve are ſtill ignorant of many things) neither do we ſee thoſe things which now we know, ſo fully, clearly, diſtinctly, as vve ſhould, and ſhall in the life to come. If therefore we know but imperfectly, we muſt needs truſt imperfectly. Experience in our ſelves, and other Chriſtians, may partly teach us the neceſſity of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence. Do we not perceive this to be (or have been) one ſpecial cauſe of the failing of our faith, that either vve know not this, or that promiſe, or were not ſufficiently acquainted with the ſaithfulneſs, and goodneſs of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſer,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:109275:80"/> or did not ſo evidently behold the good things, God had begun in us, as from them we could conclude our ſelves to be heirs of the promiſe?</p>
            <p>Secondly, there are many enemies, which oppugn a Chriſtians faith: from without, Satan by his temptations, ſometimes more ſubtil, ſometimes more violent: in his own boſom, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal vviſdom, and reaſon, natural ſlowneſs, or untowardneſs of heart, to that which is good, inordinate affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and paſſions (for grace doth not wholly expel, and root out theſe <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anites,</hi> though it brings, and keeps them under the yoke of the ſpirit.) Novv theſe ſometimes dim the light, of faith, by raiſing miſts, and fogs of objections, and doubts, ſometimes caſt her into a ſlumber, ſometimes, as it vvere, by a ſudden vehement blow aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh her, and in a vvord, by many means hinder the efficacy, and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of faith. No marvel therefore, if ſometimes the beſt faith ſtagger and waver.</p>
            <p>This doctrine confuteth, 1. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:109275:80"/> vvho to the end they may vvith more probability maintain, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the poſſibility of fulfilling the Law in this life, teach, that faith and charity are perfect in this life. 2. Some in our Church at home, vvho hold, that a man never doubts, after he is a true believer. It ſeems theſe men think faith to be like certain little bones in mans head, of vvhich the Doctors of nature vvrite, that they are of the ſame bigneſs in an old man, and in a child. 3. Our common people, and ſilly ignorants, vvho brag their belief is ſo ſtrong, as nothing can ſhake it, no company can hurt, no Devil prevail againſt them, they never ſound in themſelves any want or vveakneſs of faith, they never diſtruſted God in all their lives, they can believe as ſted faſtly as they lift. From their own vvords, their faith is evinced, to be nothing but an idle ſancy; for the child of God ſeels ſuch crazineſs in his faith, as vvrings from him many deep ſighs, bitter cries, dolorous complaints, <hi>before his heavenly father who ſeeth in ſecret.</hi>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:109275:81"/> He, who never groaned under ſence and conſcience of great infidelity, is yet in the ſtate of infidelity, and death, and hath no more true faith than the Devil.</p>
            <p>But is it poſſible (may ſome ſay) that any man ſhould be ſo deceived and miſtaken,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> as to perſwade himſelf, he is rich in faith, vvhen he hath none at all?</p>
            <p>I anſwer,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Yes very eaſily: For 1. the heart is naturally very full of ſtrong preſumption, vvhich theſe men, becauſe of the ignorance that is in them, not being able to diſtinguiſh from ſaith, do therefore take, and reſt in the one, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the other. 2. Being full of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, deſtitute of ſpiritual light, they ſee not that mighty maſs, that ſink, that ſea of unbelief vvhich is in them; they knovv not what infidelity is, nor what are the proper ſymptomes and effects of it; and therefore, though it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſtirring, yea ruling in them, and breaking out ſo, as others may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern it, yet they ſee it not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, becauſe they know not them.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:109275:81"/> ſelves, nor what is in them, as one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily blind, or going into a dark night without a candle into a room, cannot diſcern what filth and baggage is in it. 3. All unconverted are in a deep and deadly ſleep, (for repentance is called awaking;) therefore we need not think it ſtrange or impoſſible, they ſhould dream of great riches, when they have nothing; of eating and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, while their ſouls are empty. 4. The Devil will do his beſt to keep ſuch from doubting, for fear of loſing them: for well he knows, that, to doubt one hath gone wrong, is a ſtep to returning, and to fear ones heart is faithleſs and graceleſs, a ſtep to belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let the child of God take heed of numbring himſelf among un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers, and concluding that he is void of faith, becauſe ſometimes he finds his heart trembling, and ſhaken with doubtings and fears. Indeed Satan will encounter a Chriſtian with this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry; Thou haſt experience o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much wavering, thou art not ſtedfaſt and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:109275:82"/> rooted in faith therefore thou art not found in the faith: but vve muſt anſvver the tempter boldly, If this reaſon be good, <hi>all the generation of the juſt muſt be condemned,</hi> none of vvhich vvere exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and priviledged from knovving vveakneſſes, and failings of faith.</p>
            <p>If it be objected,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Chriſt prayed for every believer, as vvell as for <hi>Peter,</hi> that his faith ſhould not fail:</p>
            <p>I anſvver;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> faith may be ſaid to fail, either in regard of habit, vvhen its ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſt and extinguiſhed, and this fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling doth not, ſhall not befall a true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, according to our Saviours prayer, and the true meaning of it: or in regard of act and operation, vvhen in time of danger, ſome grievous fall, or temptation, it fainteth, ſvvouneth, vvorketh not, or but very vveakly; and in this ſenſe and manner, the beſt mans faith may fail, as <hi>Peters</hi> did (for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial proceeded from ſuch a cauſe, as ſtrength or lively povverful vvorking of faith expelleth, <hi>viz.</hi> predominancy of carnal fear) neither did our Lord Jeſus pray that his elect might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from it.</p>
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:109275:82"/>
            <p>If it be objected again,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved without ſtaggering,</p>
            <p>I anſwer; 1. True,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> when God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but it doth not hence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that he never at any time ſtagger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. 2. This example teacheth what a ſtrong faith ordinarily can do, and what every Chriſtian ſhould labour to do, but not, that every one, who reacheth not <hi>Abrahams</hi> meaſure, is an hypocrite. I ſpeak this for the comfort of true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, not to nuzzle up any in their doubts; if any man ſhall hence take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to pleaſe himſelf in a floating uncertainty, hanging between hope and fear, and neglecting to try (or labour for more ſtrength of) faith, becauſe he hears the beſt faith hath weakneſſes, he perverts and wreſts the word of God to his own deſtruction.</p>
            <p>But (may ſome man ſay) ſeeing a good Chriſtian may be troubled,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> and toſſed with doubts, ſhall not I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, I am the child of God, and in an happy caſe, if I feel doubtings?</p>
            <p>Take heed of this deceit.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> A right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever may doubt, and he may doubt
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:109275:83"/> that never was believer. The difference between them is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The doubts of a wicked man (touching his ſalvation) are cauſed, or confirmed by the light and power of Gods word rightly divided, and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, diſcovering his unfoundneſs, and ſo convincing his conſcience, that its forced to give ſentence againſt him, and roundly to tell him, he is not quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied like one that ſhall inherit the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and enjoy the ſalvation of God: they come not from Satan ordinarily; for his cuſtom is (and he knows its for his profit) to apply falſe comfort to hypocrites, when God hath terrified and wounded them, not to tempt them to unbelief (I mean, ſtill about the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their ſalvation) (except when he gets them at a dead lift, as in the hour of death, or in ſome great extremity, wherein he hopes to puſh them head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into deſperation,) becauſe then he ſhould miniſter occaſion of ſeeking that precious faith, of which himſelf is as much afraid, as the Lion of fire, and conſequently ſhould be divided againſt
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:109275:83"/> himſelf, his own enemy. But the doubts of a ſound Chriſtian come principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from Satan, (yet not without the help of natural ignorance and infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, by means whereof he hath great advantage to work) whoſe policy is, when he cannot keep the child of God from grace, then by aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his ſin and unworthineſs, by exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating, or hiding from his eyes the good things God hath given him, to hold, and deter him from beleiving, to make him (if it were poſſible) wholly to caſt away his hope, or elſe to languiſh in an heavy uncomfortableneſs, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpleaſing, and diſhonourable to God. But how may one know that his doubts are from Satan? 1. If after a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, privy ſearch in the cloſet of his ſoul, he finds ſuch ſigns of faith, as certainly declare its there preſent, though the comfort of it be not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently felt and diſcerned; as namely, a turning of the ſtreame, and bent of the thoughts and affections after heavenly things, an ingenuous and lovely melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the heart into ſorrow, for offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:109275:84"/> to the Lord, ſtrong deſires of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring and pleaſing God, with reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of cleaving to (and following) him, though he ſhould never receive comfort from him, an hearty hatred of (joyned with a ſerious ſtrife againſt) ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret hypocriſie, and carnal ends in well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, and the like. 2. If he feel, that the ſpirit in the miniſtry of the Word fights againſt his doubts, ſweetly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades and draws him to believe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth and rejoyceth his heart, not beatting and battering down his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, (as ordinarily it doth the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites) but bettering and ſtrengthening it: for hereby it appears, that his doubts are the enemies of Gods Word and Spirit, and therefore not the eccho of the word, nor the juſt verdict of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſpeaking from the word, but the voice of Satan.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> a believer finding doubts in himſelf, is exceedingly grieved for them, bewails want of Faith, as his greateſt miſery, willingly accuſeth and condemneth himſelf for theſe pangs, and qualms of unbelief: as for great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:109275:84"/> ſins, they are very burthenſome to him, chiefly becauſe they rob God of his glory, and make him leſs cheerful in rendring unto the Lord praiſes, and other obedience. But the hypocrites doubts trouble him, and he wiſheth to be rid of them, only becauſe they are attended with inward diſquietneſs, terrours, fears of the Lords judgments, not becauſe they are ſins againſt God: whereof this is a ſufficient proof, that if he enjoy a kind of peace, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion that he is the Child of God, though his evil heart, full of infidelity, ſecretly deny or call into queſtion an hundred things in divinity, one after another, he relents not, he is not troubled; tuſh, theſe are but flitting motions, nor worthy check or controle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> doubts drive a true belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, firſt, to God by earneſt requeſts, for the diſcovering and diminiſhing of his unbelief, ſtrengthening of his faith; then into himſelf, by a more exact and impartial ſcrutiny of his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and eſtate: they quicken him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weariedly,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:109275:85"/> and conſtantly to go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in reſiſting and ſubduing them, in ſeeking and lamenting after Chriſt, and never to ſit down, till God have brought his heart into the harbour of a ſtabliſhed aſſurance, till he ſee, feel, and (as it were) handle eternal life in himſelf, till he know Chriſt and all the treaſures of grace and glory in Chriſt, as undoubtedly to be his own as his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, money, houſe, lands, till the Holy Ghoſt have ſigned, ſealed and delivered the heavenly inheritance in the Court of conſcience: in a word, till he have gotten ſuch a faith, as can glory in God, inſult over Hell, Death, Devil, Sin, the Curſe of the Law, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wreſtle all difficulties: but the unſound Chriſtian, either builds himſelf a Caſtle of imaginary aſſurance upon the ſand of falſe grounds, or lies under his doubts irrecoverably, giving over ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before he receive a ſound, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and ſatisfactory anſwer from the Lord, either out of ſloth or deſpair of obtaining, or becauſe he hath lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſtrongeſt faith is ſubject to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:109275:85"/> ſome faintings, and therefore judgeth it needleſs to ſtrive any longer, or labour for more faith, ſeeing that which he hath will ſerve his turn, and its no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with him than it is with a true Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We muſt hence be admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, not to diſdain or condemn ſuch Chriſtians as ſometimes bewray ſome feebleneſs of faith, in word or work. Thou ſeeſt or heareſt thy brother is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient in affliction, fears poverty, ſhrinks at the approach of perſecution or death, is diſcouraged by reproaches and ſlanders, not ſo zealous and valiant in maintaining Gods glory and cauſe, as it were to be wiſhed, for fear of the wrath of Man, omits ſome neceſſary good, defiles himſelf with the doing of ſome evil: do not now think or ſay, ſuch a one is a faithleſs temporizer; take heed of ſuch judgment, leſt thou be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: ſeeing the truly faithful have done as much, thou ſhalt do well to be ſparing in thy cenſures, till thou canſt ſhew a perfect faith.</p>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:109275:86"/>
            <p>Fourthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> ſee the reaſon why ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the lives of very godly men are blemiſhed with ſome faults. Alas, the tree is imperfect, therefore the fruits muſt needs be ſo; for nothing can give that it hath not. Though the godly by the grace of God, may be free from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious ſins, yet they cannot obey per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, becauſe they believe but in part. Why then do carnal men, if they ſpie but a ſpot in a godly mans face, a frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his converſation, (though it be but a moat in compariſon of their beams) Why do they preſently cry out, Theſe that make ſo much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion are naught, they are naught all of them, they are diſſemblers, they are not what they ſeem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Abſurd, unreaſonable men, do you expect they ſhould be perfectly holy, when they are but imperfectly faithful? If one of your children have a ſlow, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly pace, by reaſon of lameneſs, or debility in ſome member, you think he is rather to be pitied than upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If you will not learn to judge mercifully of the godly when they fall,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:109275:86"/> and to impute their ſlips, rather to the imperfection of their condition, than the hypocriſie of their hearts, and naughtineſs of their diſpoſition, you ſhall but prove your ſelves to be haters of your brethren, and he that <hi>hates his brother is a murtherer,
<note place="margin"> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.15.</note> and no murtherer hath eternal life abiding in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, hence we are taught,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>5</label> that believers muſt not truſt to the ſtrength of their faith, as is by the power of it alone, they were able to ſtand againſt all blaſts, reſiſt all temptations: for though it's an excellent grace, yet it's but a creature, and imperfect too; and therefore in ſenſe, and diſtruſt of our own weakneſs, we have need to cry to God, that he would ſhield us with his grace, and ſupport both us and our faith by his power.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it follows hence,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>6</label> that faith doth not juſtifie by any valour, vertue, dignity of its own: neither as an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit or quality, nor as a work, but as it is a means or inſtrument of obtaining that for which we are juſtified: its not
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:109275:87"/> the gift of Faith dwelling in the Heart, nor the act of believing, (as the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers teach) but the thing holden and poſſeſſed by believing, which is our Righteouſneſs. For that thing, by which we are in proper ſenſe, abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and (as I may ſay) formally juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and preſented ſpotleſs before God, muſt be perfect, yea expiate infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite guiltineſs, anſwer the Juſtice of God: but this faith cannot do, becauſe it is imperfect, as we ſee.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Inſtruction or Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be drawn out of theſe words, is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtians muſt deſire the accompliſhment and perfection of Faith above all other Graces.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> The reaſon is, becauſe Faith, of all Graces which exiſt in us, is the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt for excellency, and of neceſſity it hath the preeminence, whether we conſider the Glory it brings to God, or Profit to Man.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> no grace exalteth and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God, as faith doth. For 1. In the cauſe of Juſtification and Salvation, Faith utterly annihilates man, tramples under foot all the glory of nature, all
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:109275:87"/> goodneſs, all privileges, all works of man, ſeeks righteouſneſs and life onely from Gods grace in Chriſt: when a poor ſinner ſeeth himſelf a condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed rebel and traitour, feels nothing in himſelf but darkneſs; unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, wrath, and death, hath nothing to bring to God but ſhame and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; Faith leads him to the Throne of Grace, and makes him bold to beg, and expect pardon in Chriſts blood, for no other cauſe, but becauſe God is graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; yea, when his many, mighty, ugly ſins diſcourage and terrifie him, to cleave ſtill to the free and everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing goodneſs of God, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bords mercies infinitely to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs his iniquities. Thus Faith gives the whole praiſe of mans ſalvation to the grace of God. 2. Faith believes God upon his bare word; if God have revealed or promiſed this or that, though all the world ſay it cannot be, though reaſon cannot comprehend how, or why it ſhould be, though many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons appear why it ſhould not be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, none at all why it ſhould, but this,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:109275:88"/> that God hath ſpoken, faith will ſtill all contrary ſurmiſes, and ſubſcribe to Gods teſtimony, as more ſtable, and ſtedfaſt, than the foundation of the earth. Thus faith highly honours Gods truth. 3. Faith proclaims God to be able to effect whatſoever he hath promiſed, and believeth, that though a thouſand difficulties ſtand in the way, the overcoming of which, fleſh and blood judgeth, not only a thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable, but impoſſible, it's as ſure as if it were done already.
<note place="margin"> 
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20, 21.</note> Thus <hi>it gives glory to the power of God.</hi> 4. Faith cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a man denying and renouncing his own judgment, wiſdom, will, as fooliſhneſs, to bleſs God, as well when he denies, or takes away, as when he gives; as well for the worſt as the beſt; and to reſt perſwaded, that the worſt eſtate is the beſt for him; when God is the Author of it, that poverty is better than abundance; when God will have him poor, reſtraint than liberty; when God will have him reſtrained, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that it's greateſt gain; to loſe all things for Chriſt, that God loves in ſmiting,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:109275:88"/> heals by wounding, exalts by hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, thorow the gates of death brings unto life. Thus faith extols the wiſdom of God. 5. Faith makes man juſtifie God in all his decrees, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, dealings, ſubſcribe to the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of them all, even when he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives not of them, adore the unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of them, reverently ſubmit unto them, yea, when they thwart his deſires, pronouncing, approving all his ways to be pure, and righteous, when he neither ſeeth, nor asketh any reaſon thereof, but Gods will. Is not this a great honour, which faith gives to Gods righteouſneſs? 6. It beholds him that is inviſible, every where pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, perſwaded that he ſeeth and knoweth all things, and ſo glorifieth him in reſpect of his omnipreſence. In a word, (that I be not too long in mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying particulars) Faith (if I may ſo ſpeak) gives unto God his whole Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and of all graces moſt ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies his Name, by acknowledging and confirming, as it were, by ſeal, all thoſe excellent properties, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:109275:89"/> which the Scripture aſcribeth to him. Indeed other graces alſo, as love, fear, joy, and the reſt, do ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God, (nor do I mean to rob them of their due praiſes) but neither primarily, (for the cauſe and foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all that honour is in faith) nor yet in ſuch ample and full manner as faith. Seeing then, nothing is ſo glorious to God as Faith, and conſequently, the more faith any man hath, the more he glorifies God; doth it not ſtand every Chriſtian in hand, above all graces to labour for perfection of Faith?</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> No Grace is more uſeful, more profitable to man than Faith, whether we conſider life ſpiritual, or natural. For ſpiritual life; 1. Faith eſpouſeth and conjoyneth man to the Son of God, in whom he findeth and obtaineth the dignity or preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of Son-ſhip, and juſtification of life, which things the better they are known, the more they are felt, and ſealed up in the Soul by believing, the more is the heart refreſhed with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable comforts. 2. Faith purifieth,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:109275:89"/> and ſanctifieth; becauſe 1. Being a gift of an holy and heavenly nature, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending from above, it will oppoſe and fight againſt corruption, as light expels darkneſs, heat cold, and antidote poiſon. 2. Laying hold on Chriſt, it draweth, and deriveth from him the Fountain, Vertue, and Power, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by corruption is maſtered, and morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as a leaden pipe brings water from the ſpring, wherein veſſels are waſhed and cleanſed. 3. Faith is the mother and root of all other holy graces in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and therefore as faith increaſeth, the reſt will increaſe; the more perfect that Faith grows, the nearer the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is the whole cluſter of heavenly gifts in the children of God; the more a man knows and believes the love of God to him, the more fervently he will love God, the more reverently he will fear him, burn with zeal of his glory, patiently hope, earneſtly deſire to be with him in heaven, and ſo of the reſt. 3. Faith ſtrengthens, 1. To obey God in leading an holy life, in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming all duties, and doing all the good
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:109275:90"/> works he requireth of his people, ſo as they may pleaſe him in all things. 2. To fight againſt, and foil all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual enmity: faith makes a poor ſoul able to reſiſt the Devil, a ſpirit of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great power, to ſtand faſt, when he is buffeted by Satans ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, which <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency could not do, and to overcome whatſoever is evil in the world: faith either wards off the blows, or ſo heals the wounds received in this battel, that the ſoul becomes more ſound and healthful than before; the Apoſtle therefore to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> arming, and training the ſpiritual ſouldier, bids him, <hi>Above all, take the ſhield of faith:</hi> Hence it is, that this grace is of all others moſt aſſaulted by the Prince of darkneſs. 3. To per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere and continue in the way of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to the end, becauſe it doth ſeat, and keep believers in the impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fort of Gods faithfulneſs, and tower of his Almighty power, wherein the gates of hell cannot prevail againſt them. In a word, what is ſaid of <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> locks, may be ſaid of faith, a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:109275:90"/> ſtrength lies in it, yet not ſimply, and for it ſelf, but becauſe it lays hold upon Chriſt, the rock of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who ſtrengthens his Members to do all things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> for natural life. 1. Faith procureth temporal good things. For God, who is faithful, hath promiſed to them that fear him, and will ſubject themſelves to his government, <hi>follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him wholly,</hi> like <hi>Caleb,</hi> even outward and temporal benefits, ſo far as they may be good for them, and not preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to their ſpiritual proſperity, or ſoul-thriving: now a Chriſtian by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving and ſuing to God in prayer of faith, obtaineth them, and ſo findeth relief and ſupply of temporal wants. 2. Faith makes evils tolerable, ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth croſſes, enables to endure affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, by aſſuring the believer, that in them God offers himſelf as a Father, will moderate the ſtroke, miniſter ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſtrength, give an happy iſſue, turn them to his good, by ſetting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes ſuch a Crown, ſuch a weight of Glory, with which <hi>the light
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:109275:91"/> and momentany ſufferings of this life, are not worthy to be compared.</hi> Now (to knit up this reaſon) if there be ſuch neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and uſe of Faith for Juſtification, Sanctification, corroboration in holy obedience, and in the ſpiritual warfare; ſuſtentation and conſolation in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and conſequently, the greater faith, the more peace, holineſs, ſtrength, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in afflictions; who ſeeth not, how needful it is, that every Chriſtian do chiefly, and above all things, deſire the accompliſhment of ſaith.</p>
            <p>This diſcovers,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> and reproves a great fault in ſome Chriſtians, who travel and take pains to increaſe knowledge, ſorrow for ſin, zeal to ſubdue and root out hypocriſie, evil thoughts, and luſts, while the care of growing in Faith lies neglected, or is ſuperficially proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, fecondarily attended. Alas! do you not ſee (my brethren, I ſpeak to ſuch, (whom this point concerns) that this is to begin at a wrong end, as if a man ſhould take Phyſick, or apply Medicines for Stomach, Eyes, Legs, Armes, and be careleſs of the Vital
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:109275:91"/> Parts, as the Heart and Liver, or look well to the branches of a Plant, and neglect the root. Aſſure your ſelves. the hand of Satan is in this matter, who like a moſt ſubtil enemy, when he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not keep you, now quickned with the life of God, from ſeeking grace, and working that which is good, labors that you may ſeek and work prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly (and ſo without ſucceſs or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort) doing any thing rather than that which chiefly, and above all things ſhould be done.</p>
            <p>Wherefore <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> let my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel be acceptable to you, as you labor to excel in every gvace, ſo bend, and apply your principal endeavours hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that you may flouriſh and a bound in this Cardinal Grace, this Queen-Mother of graces, which gives life to all other vertues and duties: if ever you have taſted the ſweetneſs, and known the worth of Faith, ſtir up your ſelves with an holy contention, to aſpire after a plenitude of Faith. Why are we ſo ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and diſquieted when troubles, yea, rumors of troubles come, ſo faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:109275:92"/> or dead in afflictions, ſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, ſometimes with fears, or fruitleſs penſiveneſs, ſo burthned, or diſtracted with want of this or that earthly bleſſing, ſo weak in love to God, in reſiſting our luſts, in holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? Why is there not (as indeed there ſhould) ſuch a light of heavenly joy and ſanctity in our lives, as might make the men of the world ſtand wondring at the glory of Chriſtianity? is it not want of this great faith, this ſtrong faith the Scripture commends? Let us trace our own hearts, and ſearch the matter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially, and we ſhall find it to be ſo. We all deſire ſtrong bodies, ſtrong houſes, firm evidences, and Writings for money or land, and ſhall we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelues with a weak and wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring faith, which will be daſht out of countenance with every doubt; not labour for that ſtedfaſt and grounded aſſurance, which will miniſter ſtrong conſolation? Its a ſhame for us to be babes in faith, who have ſo long enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the means of faith. We are now nearer our ſalvation, than when we
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:109275:92"/> firſt believed, and therefore ſhould lay faſter hold upon eternal life. Little do we know what need we ſhall have of the ſtrongeſt ſaith before we die. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we ſhould be freed from outward trials, the Devil will ſift and winnow us, and when that time comes, the beſt of us ſhall find all the faith we have gotten, little enough. Beſides, oh the benefit of a manly and grown faith! Its the crown and glory of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity before Men and Angels, it brings a man to know and enjoy a Heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, works for him wonderful things, and incredible to reaſon; fills the heart with ſuch triumphant and glorious joy in tribulations, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane men in all their wealth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity never feel, nor can poſſibly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, makes him conquer by ſuffering. Wouldſt thou gladly be broken-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, humble, patient, heavenly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? Let faith have her perfect work, and thou ſhalt be all theſe and more. Gods yoke ſhall be ſweet and eaſie to thee, thy corruptions, like <hi>Davids</hi> ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſhall fall under thy feet, thou ſhalt
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:109275:93"/> chaſe and put to flight armies of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and lead about the roaring Lion in Triumph, thou ſhalt behold God more neer, and ſee him more clearly than many others; when thou art weak thou ſhalt be ſtrong; when thou art poor, thou ſhalt abound; <hi>in darkneſs thou ſhalt ſee light; and in the ſhadow of death, find life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi> What could we want, if we wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not Faith? how happy might we be, if we were rich in Faith? My exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation therefore, and earneſt ſuit unto all Gods people is, and ſhall be, that they would not only ſtrive to ferret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidelity out of their hearts, and confirm Faith, but ſeek and reach after the moſt excellent and eminent degree of Faith, a powerful and victorious Faith, carrying them far above the World in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and labour by often chewing particular promiſes, and meditation of their glorious hopes, by praying ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly with the Apoſtles, <hi>Lord increaſe our faith,</hi> by conſtant hanging upon the breaſts of the Miniſtry, coming to the word of faith with an eager appetite,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:109275:93"/> receiving it with application, by kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in memory, and revolving the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience they have had of Gods Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Mercy, by fellowſhip with ſtrong and experienced Chriſtians, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing Faith in all occurrents, and ſuch like holy meanes; labor I ſy, that the ſmall grain of Faith, which God hath ſown in the ſoil of their Souls, may grow up to a tall Tree, whoſe height reacheth unto Heaven, full of fair leaves nnd ſavoury Fruits, yielding ſhade and ſhelter to many. <hi>Bleſſed is he that heareth and keepeth;</hi> for he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videth well for his Soul, he ſhall ſing, when others ſorrow; ſtand, when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſtagger or fall; the Lord ſhall reveal to him the abundance of peace and truth. <hi>The Lord give us underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in all things, and perſwade our hearts to the things which belong to our peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I gather hence,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> that Gods word doth warrant Chriſtians to prize, prefer, reſpect Faith before all other Gifts: which I note, to let you ſee a difference betwixt Apoſtolical and
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:109275:94"/> Apoſtatical doctrine, the ſpirit of <hi>Paul,</hi> and the ſpirit of <hi>Papiſts:</hi> for they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the dignity of ſaith, and extol charity and the works of charity far above it. They teach, that the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, when it hath to deal with men faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and regenerate, calls not for faith any longer, but urgeth good workes:</hi> they teach, that <hi>true righteouſneſs conſiſteth principally in charity;</hi> that charity <hi>onely is the forme and Queen of vertues,</hi> (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of faith, as if one ſhould ſay, the form of juſtice is temperance, an habit diſtinct from it; or motion the form of the ſpirits in our bodies; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound learning indeed, by ſome of their own men diſliked:) they teach, that faith doth out <hi>only diſpoſe us unto juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, make us meet to receive grace, and obtain Chriſts merits,</hi> but charity <hi>alone ſufficeth it to juſtification,</hi> charity <hi>will purge away ſin, and deliver from the guilt of death eternal.</hi> Who can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to ſee the Daughter lift up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Mother, to hear the hand ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured above the heart? But that ſuch Divinity ſhould come from <hi>Papists,</hi> we
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:109275:94"/> ſhall think it leſs ſtrange, if we do but remember two things.</p>
            <p n="1"> 1. That the <hi>Roman</hi> Synagogue is juſt ſuch a Church, as a Carcaſe is a Man, and therefore it was meet ſhe ſhould neglect that grace which is the ſpring, and ſoul of all piety, juſtice, charity; What's fitter for a dead Church, maintaining a dead Chriſt, a dead Croſs a dead Word, dead Sacraments, dead Prayer, a dead Miniſtery, than a dead juſtice?</p>
            <p n="2"> 2. That the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Faith is nothing elſe, <hi>but an aſſent to all ſuch things, as the Church propoundeth out of the word, written or unwritten;</hi> which (themſelves being witneſſes) many <hi>Catholicks</hi> have, who are notorious Sinners, Murtherers, Fornicators, Thieves, Drunkards,; ſuch a faith I am ſure may be in the Devil: and therefore good reaſon they ſhould commend any thing before it.</p>
            <p>If it be objected,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>that our Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly affirmeth love to be greater than faith or hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:109275:95"/>
            <p>I anſwer,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> his meaning is, that love is more excellent, not ſimply and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolurely, but in ſome reſpectonly, that is, in regard of the manner of working, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and uſe towards others; for the work of Faith is ſecret in the heart, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible; the work of love manifeſts to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſenſible; Faith reſpects God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Love ſtretcheth her Armes both to God and Man: Faith is profitable only to him that hath it, but Loue ſtudys the Edification of the Church, and ſpurs forward to labor the good of the Members thereof, both in Soul and Body, which ſeems by the Context to be the very thing the Apoſtle intends: unleſs you will expound it thus, as ſome have done, that in the life to come there ſhall be far more frequent, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and illuſtrious uſe and exerciſe of Love, becauſe the glorified Saints ſhall not be troubled in Heaven about hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faith and Hope as they are in this World but wholly taken up with loving God hauing no other work and imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment during all eternity, but to ſolace and delight themſelves in the fruition of
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:109275:95"/> his glorious Preſence, and the ſociety of the bleſſed Angels.</p>
            <p>We come now to the laſt inſtruction, which is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The perfecting of faith and all other Gifts in the Elect,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> is a work of Gods Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Power of God accompliſheth the Belief, as every other grace of the Godly. I join together the general and ſpecial from both the clauſes which might be handled diſtinctly. Hence is that of the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin"> Ro. 15.13.</note> 
               <hi>The God of hope fill you with all peace in believing, that ye may abound in hope through the power of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> 2 Pet. 1.3.</note> So elſewhere <hi>His divine power giveth us all things pertaining to godlineſs.</hi> The truth is, God himſelf muſt either do it by his own ſtrong hand and mighty arm, or it will never be done.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Firſt,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> There is no other cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to produce this effect: the means without. Gods bleſſing and ſpirit brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in them, are but a dead ſound and can do nothing, both the Miniſters la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and the ſucceſs of them are
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:109275:96"/> from Gods efficacy; Man himſelf, though indued with faith, cannot believe when and ſo much as he pleaſeth, its not in his own power to reſt ſo firmly and ſtedfaſtly upon Gods promiſes as he deſireth; and therefore cannot perfect his own faith. Alas, how ſhould he? when <hi>he cannot make one hair white or black,</hi> command one ounce of bodily health at his pleaſure, or add one cubit to his ſtature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> The enemies which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the growth of faith and holineſs, are ſuch as cannot be vanquiſhed, but by the power of the Omnipotent Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; natural ignorance and infidelity, (degrees of ſpiritual death) cannot be expelled, but by the Author of life; thoſe potent and ſubtil ſpiritual Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes cannot be maſtered, but by <hi>him that is ſtrongeſt, able to tread down Satan under our feet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Then it follows hence, <hi>that much more the beginning, and firſt working of Faith, is from Gods power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful efficacy or effectual power.</hi> For its a greater work to give, than to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:109275:96"/> life; to kindle or produce fire where none was, than to keep it bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when it is kindled. If that which is leſs, <hi>viz.</hi> the conſummating of faith, much more that which is greater, the begetting or infuſing of faith muſt be attributed to the power of God; which meets with the <hi>Arminians,</hi> teaching, <hi>that God doth not by his Almighty Power bring men to believe, but only allure, perſwade, excite, leaving it ſtill in their power, whether they will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve or no.</hi> But the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> makes the revelation of Gods Arm, to be the efficient cauſe of the belief of the Goſpel, and our Apoſtle aſcribes the believing of the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> to the ſame mighty power of God, by which he raiſed Chriſt Jeſus from the dead. It were well therefore, they would change their minds, or correct their Bibles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> This may comfort belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, againſt fear of loſing (or ſalling from) faith. The great God, <hi>who is ſtrong in power, who created all theſe things, bringeth out their hoſt by number, and calleth all by their names, by the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:109275:97"/> of his might,</hi> who can do what he will, and hinder what he pleaſeth, who <hi>never fainteth nor is weary,</hi> hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to finiſh their faith by that <hi>effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual working whereby he is able to ſubdue all things to himſelf.</hi> As ſoon ſhall God fail, as the Faith of the Elect utterly fail: till the Almighty be overcome, they can never periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Believers who complain of weakneſs of faith, are here taught to follow the Lord with importunate and earneſt requeſts, that he would by his out-ſtretched Arm uphold them in believing to the end, and accompliſh their faith by the ſame power whereby he firſt brought them to Faith. Do we ſometimes feel our ſelves ſo near ſwouning, that we are ready with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> to cry out, <hi>My fleſh and my heart faileth me?</hi> let us cry unto <hi>Jeſus, the Author and Finiſher of Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Heb. 12.2.</note> that he would ſtrengthen us, and <hi>perfect that which he hath wrought in us;</hi> Let us look up unto him,
<note place="margin"> Joel. 3.16. Pſ. 68.35.</note> 
               <hi>who is the ſtrength of the children of Iſrael, who gives ſtrength to his people, power to them that are
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:109275:97"/> faint, and to them that have no might increaſeth ſtrength, let us lay hold upon his ſtrength, who is the God of all Power, the rock of our hearts, and of our faith, the worker of all our works in us, and for us, who is able to do exceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly above all that we ask or think, according to the power that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in us, to him be glory for ever and ever, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It ſeemes to me,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> we may rightly conclude from this point, that Faith ſhall not ceaſe in the life to come. For that which God will accompliſh, ſhall not be aboliſhed: elſe God ſhould perfect and accompliſh a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Habit in vain and to no purpoſe, which ſtandeth not with his Wiſdom. Becauſe the aſſertion may ſeem ſtrange and new (though indeed it hath worthy Authors) theſe reaſons may further confirm it.</p>
            <p n="1"> 1. Were it not harſh and abſurd to ſay the glorified Saints have no confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God?</p>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:109275:98"/>
            <p n="2"> 2. No man can doubt that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of juſt and perfect Men now in Heaven, do believe and wait for the redemption of their bodies; therefore faith and ſight are not ſo oppoſed, as they cannot ſtand together</p>
            <p n="3"> 3. If there ſhall be a word in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, then faith; but there ſhall be a word, not this written or printed Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but the ſubſtance of that Doctrine which is contained in the Bible, and conſequently, all thoſe Promiſes which ſpeak of the Eternity of that glorious Eſtate reſerved for Believers in He a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſhall be written in their hearts, So that if any ask, what uſe ſhall there be o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Faith, when now they enjoy the Lords promiſed Salvation. I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> they ſhall believe, that God will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuat and continue thoſe joys and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that bleſſed condition to them for ever and ever.</p>
            <p n="4"> 4. I ſuppoſe this is ſound Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, (which hath hitherto gone for currant among our Divines, unleſs in that late Controverſie, whether faith or repentance hath precedency, it
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:109275:98"/> have received ſome affront.) Faith is the root, foundation, original of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs. Doth the root wither when the tree and branches flouriſh more than ever? 5. In the day of Judgment the Lord ſhall pronounce all the ſins of the righteous eternally forgiven, &amp; the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of abſolution &amp; remiſſion ſhall be openly and fully declared and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as Divines teach. Shall they nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what Chriſt ſpeaketh? 6. Why may we not ſay, that as the godly in this world believe things paſt, as the creation, the incarnation, death, reſurection of Chriſt, ſo ſhall they in the life to come. Theſe arguments ſway me to this opinion, as moſt probable, that Faith in God is an eternal gift, abiding in the Heavens, the ſome Operations of it ſhall ceaſe in Heaven, whereof there ſhall be no num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. The matter is not of ſuch weight, that I would contend with any man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it. Let the Prophet judge, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct him better (if he orr) who in points of this nature ſuſpecteth his own judgment; as much as any other, and is more deſirous to learn than to teach.
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:109275:99"/> Laſtly, from this inſtruction its eaſie to gather, that we muſt ſeek unto, and reſt upon God, as well for the finiſhing as beginning of our ſalvation. Should the beginning be Gods work, the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment ours, ſo wiſe an Apoſtle would not have ſpent, nor by his own example taught us to ſpend ſo many prayers for it. This is to be marked as meeting with the <hi>Papiſts:</hi> they will have God lay the foundation of mans ſalvation by Predeſtination, redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, free remiſſion of ſins: but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they will not be much beholden to him: they can now perfect the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelves, for they can merit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of juſtice and eternal life, ſo that in effect they ſay to God, as a man ſometimes to his neighbour, when he would have this or that work done, do but ſet me in, and I ſhall do well enough. But that doctrine which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth us not with the Apoſtle to pray while we live, Lord accompliſh in us, weak and worthleſs Veſſels, by thine own power, the work of faith, and all the good pleaſure of thy goodneſs, is
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:109275:99"/> not from heaven but from men and the Devil. Hitherto we have unſolded the ſpecial requeſts which the Apoſtle made unto God for the <hi>Theſſalonians:</hi> There now remaineth only the end why or for which he thus intercedeth with God, and moveth him for the forenamed bleſſings, and its double; 1. Principal, reſpecting Chriſt. 2. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate, reſpecting the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <p>The former is ſet down in theſe words, <hi>[that the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt may be glorified in you]</hi> that is, that Chriſt himſelf by this means may be honoured in you; and by you in this preſent world. As if he ſhould ſay, I do the rather beg theſe things for you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they mainly tend to the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the glory of Chriſt among the ſons of men, which thing I am ſure your ſouls earneſtly wiſh and deſire.</p>
            <p>Obſerve from theſe words to inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>that the ſcope of Chriſtians muſt be the glorifying of Chriſt.</hi> The Apoſtle teſtifieth of himſelf in another place,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:109275:100"/> that <hi>he deſired nothing more than that Chriſt might be magnified in his frail body,
<note place="margin"> Phil. 1.20.</note> whether by life or death;</hi> and profeſſeth, that he made this the only end of his life, the mark at which he aimed in his whole Miniſtry, all his actions and paſſions, to bring glory to Chriſt. For ſo I expound thoſe words, <hi>for to me to live is Chriſt,</hi> and generally, of all true believers he ſaith elſewhere, <hi>Whether we live, we live unto the Lord, or whether we die, we die unto the Lord.</hi> And good reaſon, For</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Chriſt is the Author both of their being and conſervation. From him they have life and ſuſtentation, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and ſpiritual For <hi>by him all things were created:</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Col. 1.16.</note> do ſubſiſt, <hi>and are uphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the word of his power,</hi> he gives unto every Mun that comes into the World <hi>a reaſonable ſoul,</hi> he quickens ſanctifies the elect, <hi>Feeds them with his own fleſh and bloud,
<note place="margin"> 1 Cor. 1.2. 2 Co. 5.17.</note> preſenteth, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſheth, enableth to every good word and work,</hi> holds them in his hand, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports them by his grace, as the High Prieſt the ruines of <hi>Iſrael</hi> on his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders:
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:109275:100"/> without him we have nothing, <hi>can do nothing,</hi> would return to nothing. Therefore nothing is more meet than that Chriſtians ſhould wholly addict themſelves to his glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> conſider the ſeveral rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Chriſt unto Chriſtians. Is he not their Husband? <hi>Muſt not all Wives give honour to their Husbands?</hi> Is he not their King, yea the King of glory? are not ſubjects bound <hi>to honour their King?</hi> Is he not their Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? ought nor <hi>ſervants to count their maſters worthy all honour?</hi> Laſtly, he is their dear Redeemer, who willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſrobed and emptied himſelf of his regal glory, and put on the homely mantle of humane fleſh, that he might ranſom them with the price of his own bloud? Therefore they owe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wholly to him, and ſtand obliged <hi>to glorifie him in ſoul and body, whoſe they are both in ſoul and body.</hi> For <hi>to this end</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Chriſt died for them,
<note place="margin"> 1 Co. 6.20.</note> that they ſhould not henceforth live to themſelves- but to him that died for them:</hi> Hence the living Creatures are
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:109275:101"/> brought in, ſaying with a loud voice, <hi>worthy is the Lamb that was ſlain, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive honour, glory and bleſſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> its no ſmall honour which through Chriſt is already put upon them, and from Chriſt they expect far greater in the next life. They are now partakers of a glorious adoption, a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſhining righteouſneſs, glorious graces, glorious joys, they are called to glory, and wait for a richly glorious inheritance, an eternal weight of glory to be conferred upon them by Chriſt. Now ſhall not thoſe that have and look to receive ſo great glory from Chriſt, endeavour ſo to live as Chriſt may have glory from them?</p>
            <p>But alas,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> how few will be able to ſtand, if they be judged by this doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine? How many who call themſelves Chriſtians, will be found lighter than vanity, liars againſt the truth? Firſt, many propound to themſelves no other end of living here but hoording up rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, building their neſts on high, ſerving their bellies, wallowing in pleaſures, enjoying honours. The glory of Chriſt
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:109275:101"/> (their conſciences being witneſſes) is no more thought on or remembred, than if Chriſt had never bin, of all other things this hath never troubled their heads. Wel, if Chriſt had ever viſited theſe men with the light of life, and by his ſpirit ſent joyful tidings of ſalvation to their ſpirits, it would be otherwiſe with them. Never did man truly know Chriſt, and what Chriſt hath done for his ſoul, but was much taken up and tranſported in muſing, deviſing, defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to glorifie him. Be not deceived, if the Lords honour be a ſtranger in your minds, memories, intentions, endeavours, you are in darkneſs till this preſent, and cannot be aſſured to your comfort, that you have part in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption which is in Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> do not many live as if they had been made or born to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Chriſt? As 1. our idolaters, who more ſtupid than the old <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> give the glory of Chriſt to crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to their own works, to the works of the Painter, Carver, Baker. I fear theſe grand thieves are long
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:109275:102"/> ſince paſt ſhame and grace too. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord Jeſus requires at their hands the reſtitution of that honour which moſt ſacrilegiouſly, contrary to his crown and dignity, they have robb'd him of. 2. Our prophane ſwearers, who tear the glorious name of Chriſt, or toſs his Titles unreverently in their Mouths; theſe honour him, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did when they ſpitted on him. 3. All contemners of Chriſts ordinances and ſervants, who ſhall one day find that whatſoever is done to things or perſons bearing his Name, Jeſus Chriſt will take it and revenge it as done to himſelf. 4. All wicked livers, whoſe ungodly works cauſe <hi>that worthy Name by which we are called,
<note place="margin"> Jam. 2.7.</note> to be blaſphemed in the world.</hi> We ſhall ſometimes hear them deteſt and curſe both <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> for perſecuting it with the ſword, when themſelves (like arrant hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, in whom the love of Chriſt dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not) tread it under foot by their curſed and moſt abominable licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Let all the Lords people
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:109275:102"/> ſtudy in all things and by all means to glorifie Chriſt Jeſus. Let his honour be dearer to us than all things. For this cauſe were we redeemed
<note n="†" place="margin"> Iſ. 43.21.</note>, called, quickened, <hi>that we ſhould ſhew forth his praiſe, live to his glory.</hi> Do not maſters look their ſervants ſhould be a credit to them? The Angels of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven have no more noble imployment than to ſerve and honour the Son of God. <hi>The Father hath committed to the Son the government of all things, That all men might honour the Son,
<note place="margin"> Joh. 5.23.</note> as they honour the Father.</hi> If any deſire di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for the practice of this moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary leſſon, know that we muſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the Name of Chriſt, both inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and outwarly. Inwardly in ſpirit and affection. 1. By ſtirring up and cheriſhing in our minds honourable thoughts of Chriſt, an high eſteem of him and his excellency, of that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable goodneſs and power which he ſheweth in leading us to ſalvation. 2. By believing againſt hope and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, truſting on his grace, and caſting our ſelves wholly upon him, in want
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:109275:103"/> of feeling, and when all things ſeem to be againſt us. 3. By intending his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in every thing, making it the mark at which we ſhoot, and if we cannot be ſo happy, as at all times to find, that this is the end which before every action firſt comes to our minds, and ſenſibly moves our wills, yet muſt we ſtrive to find in our ſelves after the action, an high prizing, and earneſt thirſting after his glory, far above all our own good, temporal and eternal. 4, By grieving heartily to ſee, or hear him diſhonoured by falſe worſhippers, falſe teachers, carnal Chriſtians. 5. By often calling upon our hearts to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire and rejoyce in him, more than all other things. Outwardly, both in word and work. In word; 1. By aſcribing the whole glory of our ſalvation to him only. 2. Speaking of him, and uſing all his Names and Titles with ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, as beſeems ſo great a Lord. 3. Continual praiſing him for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and truth towards us, for the things be hath wrought, daily worketh, and will hereafter work for us, ſpeaking
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:109275:103"/> much good of him before others, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them what a wiſe, powerful, bountiful Lord we ſerve. 4. Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him boldly before the ſons of Men, vindicating and maintaining by our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologies his cauſe and truth when they are oppoſed and ſpoken againſt. In work and converſation; 1. By ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſelves to the direction of his word in all things, enterprizing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without leave or warrant from him. 2. By a godly life and fruitfulneſs in a Chriſtian courſe. 3. By upholding and ſetting forward his Goſpel to the utmoſt of his power. For the Goſpel is Chriſts chariot, wherein he rideth through the world, to conquer his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and gather his Church; if the Goſpel run and prevail, his glory is inlarged: if the Goſpel be ſtopped, his glory is hindred. 4. By willing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoing any thing for his ſake. Theſe are the things which we muſt remember and do, <hi>that Chriſt may be glorified in us;</hi> in the doing of which we ſhall not be a little helped, by accuſtoming our ſelves every day, yea often in the day
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:109275:104"/> to call our own hearts to account, and enquire, what glory hath redounded to Chriſt this day, this hour, from my thoughts, my ſpeeches, my actions, that ſo far as we find our ſelves bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and defective this way, we may take ſhame to our ſelves, and turning our feet into the way of Gods teſtimonies, with renewed care, and redoubled re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, ſet upon this greateſt and moſt honourable Work of honouring the Lord.</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> obſerve, that <hi>a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian deſires the Lord may be glorified by others.</hi> A good man is not content to honour God in his own perſon, but he heartily wiſheth, and prayeth that others may do it as well as himſelf. So did <hi>David, Pſa.</hi> 67.3, 4. and <hi>Paul, Eph,</hi> 3.21. For,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> The zeal of God burns in his breaſt, the love of Chriſt conſtraines him, he knows that God moſt highly eſteemes and loves his own glory, that this being the laſt end of all his counſels and works, muſt needs be more worthy and excellent than all
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:109275:104"/> creatures; in regeneration he puts on the image of God, by which he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined and enabled to will what God willeth, to love what the Lord loveth, and in the ſame manner, (according to his meaſure) therefore he cannot but deſire the inlargement of his glory in the world, and the communication of that grace to many, by which they may be effectually taught and moved to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He loves the ſouls of men,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> and heartily deſires their welfare, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, eternal, now he knows that this task of glorifying God, is both at, tended with much preſent ſweetneſs and comfort, and will certainly bring a moſt glorious reward, life everlaſting, Wherefore that Chriſtian love of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which the Holy Ghoſt hath kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his heart, makes him ſeriouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that they may be ſharers in ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and matchleſs a gain; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently join with him in the means leading to it namely, the ſtudy and care of honouring the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:109275:105"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> then this reproves two ſorts; 1. Thoſe that hinder and deter men from glorifying God, ſuch I mean, who diſcerning in others holy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs in religion, love of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and godly perſons, tenderneſs of conſcience, care to depart from evil, and ſhun the ſociety of ſinners, ſnub ad diſcourage them by threatnings, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, commandments, puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. This is a fearful thing, though men ſee it not; its manifeſt fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and playing the part of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lymas,</hi> who is therefore called <hi>the child of the Devil, and an enemy to all righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> Judge in your ſelves, can he be the child of God, who neither gives him his due honour, nor ſuffers them that would? As we ſtand affected to the glouy of God, and the means of it, ſo are we affected towards God himſelf. He that cannot endure the light of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the life of his child, ſervant, kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, neighbour, by which God is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, would baniſh God out of the world, if it were in his power. <hi>He that
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:109275:105"/> deſtroys the Temple of God,
<note place="margin"> 1 Co. 3.17.</note> him ſhall God deſtroy:</hi> he that quencheth the fire of Gods grace in others, ſhall burn in the fire nevar to be quenched. 2. Thoſe that draw or thruſt others forward to ſuch courſes, as diſhonour God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke and perſwade them to ſwearing, riot, drunkenneſs, wantonneſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for ſhame let not ſuch men any longer call themſelves ſons and ſervants of the living God. Should I hear a man in ſecret conference with another, command or councel him to ſet a fire on his neighbours Corn Barn or Dwelling houſe, might I not ſafely conclude, this is no friend, but a very dangerous and bitter enemy of his neighbour? Is it not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that by thy perſonal ſins thou <hi>fretteſt, yea breakeſt the very heart</hi> of God every hour, except alſo thou hire and procure helpers, as if thou couldſt not eaſily ſatisfie thy ſelf in heaping injuries upon him, and loading him with contumelies? Tell me vile hell-hound, do men thus to
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:109275:106"/> their friends? Go now, and if thou haſt loſt all forehead, deny thy ſelf to be the Lords enemy. I tell thee thou art a flat hater of the holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or the Devil is none.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> by this doctrine we may examine our ſelves, and judge what manner of Chriſtians we are. Doth it ſting, yea cut thee to the heart, to ſee Chriſt ſo ſlenderly known and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the world, ſo many profeſſing him, who in their works deny him, calling him, Lord, Lord, when by their lives he is blaſphemed? Doth it grieve thee to ſee, that in every place where thou commeſt, the moſt are no better than walking tombs, moving ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, unmeet for the Lords uſe and ſervice? Do theſe things lye nearer thy heart than thy perſonal croſſes and injuries? Canſt thou pour out prayers, even as for thine own foul, for thoſe who belonging to God, run forward in wickedneſs, that they may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed to glorifie him in the day of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation, and for the called, that they
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:109275:106"/> may be made more zealous of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>ſhew forth the vertues of him, who hath brought them out of darkneſs into his marvellous light?</hi> Anſwer me, is it thus with thee? no doubt a portion of <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit reſts upon thee. But if the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual condition of others affect thee not, if <hi>thy ſpirit be not ſtirred,</hi> when the Lord Jeſus is crucified afreſh by Oaths and blaſphemies, his Sabbaths pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, his word deſpiſed, if thy heart tells thee thou careſt but little what become of Gods glory, how often or by whom he be wronged, ſo thy ſelf be not tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, what become of other mens ſouls, whether they ſink or ſwim, if theſe things wring no ſighs, no prayers from thee in ſecret, <hi>though thou haſt a name to live, thou art dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> here is matter of inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. We ſee here whats the reaſon why the godly deſire and ſeek the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſinners. You ſhall ſometimes hear a wicked fellow, if a ſervant of God, but reach him the helping hand of Chriſtian admonition, to pull him
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:109275:107"/> out of his ſin, fall a fuming and exclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, <hi>what hath he to do with use, let him look to himſelf, he is more buſie than needs, he ſhall not anſwer for me,</hi> &amp;c. But ſtay a little, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid to <hi>Eliab, Is there not a cauſe?</hi> Thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath received mercy from the Lord, and therefore cannot but ſhew mercy to thy ſoul: grace hath kindled in his boſom a deſire of thy good, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid him not to ſpeak, when the Lord hath bidden him. He knows that as God is by thy ſin diſhonoured, ſo by thy repentance he would be greatly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, and that if Chriſt have not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry now by thy converſion and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he will get himſelf glory in thy confuſion. Hence it is that he calleth upon thee to renounce the works of the fleſh. Canſt thou blame him? Is it not a bruitiſh part to be angry with him that would gladly have thy company to heaven? if thou ſtormeſt againſt thoſe, who wiſh thee in as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py a caſe as their own ſouls; what wilt thou do to thine enemies?</p>
            <pb n="179" facs="tcp:109275:107"/>
            <p>This ſerveth laſtly for exhortation,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> to ſtir us all up, as we would prove our ſelves right Chriſtians, by all good means within our power to endeavour, that others may ſet forth the Lords glory. Let us begin with thoſe that are under our charge, or neareſt unto us, and then extend our care to ſuch as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally we converſe and meet with, teaching them who and what a one God is, and what he requireth of us, that we may honour him, warning them of ſuch things by which he is or might be diſhonoured in them, labouring their converſion and tranſlation into Chriſts Kingdom (becauſe till they be truly turned, they can never rightly glorifie him, and <hi>multitude of ſubjects is a Kings glory</hi>) at leaſt reſtraining them from open profanation of his name. How do the followers of noble Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages beſtir themſelves that their Lords may have honourable reſpect in every place where they come? What child deſires not to ſee his father very wealthy? The Lord give us ſuch minds
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:109275:108"/> and hearts toward our heavenly father</p>
            <p>The ſecond end, reſpecting the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians</hi> followeth, which is 1 propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, 2 amplified from the cauſe of it, propounded thus <hi>[and ye in him]</hi> that is, and ye thus living to his glory, may be glorified in and through the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>Obſerve hence only one inſtruction, that,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They which glory in Chriſt,
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> ſhall he glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified by and with Chriſt, Rom.</hi> 8, 17, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. For firſt, God is a bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful rewarder of all diligent and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervants of his moſt beloved Son. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the members muſt follow and be conformed to the head. Now Chriſt the head of believers firſt <hi>glorified his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon earth,</hi> and was afterward <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with that glory which he had with the father before the world.</hi> Therefore the faithful ſhall go the ſame way, that is, after they have finiſhed their courſe of obedience, in doing and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering to the glory of Chriſt, they ſhall be received into the glory of Chriſt and the Father, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> in
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:109275:108"/> glorifying the godly, Chriſt glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf. Relatives mutually give and receive honour. The nobility, beauty, bravery, diſcretion of a wife is an honour to the husband, and the glory of the ſpouſe of Chriſt, ſhall fet forth and illuſtrate the glory of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>If any ask,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>what is this glory which the Lord beſtows upon his Saints that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer:
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Its either preſent or fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Preſent in this world, a preamble to that which ſhall follow in the next, is either more open and manifeſt, or more hidden and ſecret. More manifeſt, is when God gives them ſome great and famous deliverance, or lifts them from a baſe and mean condition, to places of dignity, or makes them to be highly reverenced and had in precious eſteem, even amongſt thoſe who are of a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent religion, and contrary diſpoſition. <hi>Joſeph</hi> had great glory in the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Court,
<note place="margin"> Ge. 45.13.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes was very great in the ſight of Pharoahs ſervants, and the people of Egypt,</hi> David <hi>honourable in</hi> Sauls <hi>houſe,
<note place="margin"> 1 Sa. 22.14</note>
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:109275:109"/> Mordecai in the Court of Ahaſuerus.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Eſt. 8.15.</note> More ſecret is when the wicked who openly deſpiſe, vilifie, condemn the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, are forced inwardly to juſtify them, and to feel their own conſciences tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, that they, or no people in the world are in an happy eſtate, and in the way of life. Whence it is that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we have known Mockers and profeſſed Enemies of Gods Servants (<hi>Puritans</hi> Men call them now adays) in cold bloud, or in the evil day deſire their prayer, wiſh to dy their death, and commit to their truſt moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant buſineſſes. For <hi>the ſpirit of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reſts upon them,</hi> which cauſeth the face to ſhine, and imprints that Majeſty in the countenance or converſation, which makes their perſons no leſs ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable and terrible to thoſe that hate them, than amiable to thoſe that love them. Future is that wherewith they ſhall be crowned in the life to come when every faithful perſon ſhall be cloathed in ſoul and body from top to toe, with ſuch glory as ſhall cauſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:109275:109"/> in men and Angels, and dwell for ever with moſt glorious company, in a moſt glorious Manſion, of which particulars I think it not fit to treat largely in this place, it ſhall ſuffice brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have named them, becauſe I haſten to an end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Then it follows hence,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> by the <hi>rule</hi> of contraries, that the end of all ſuch as either oppugne the glory of Chriſt, or wholly neglecting it, hunt and hawk after the glory of the World, ſhall be ſhame and confuſion. Think on this, ye proud vain-glorious men, who leave no ſtone unmoved, that you may magnifie your ſelves, whoſe only ſtudy and ſtrife is to climb to the height of earthly greatneſs, but if the name of Chriſt lie inglorious in the duſt, will not wag a tongue, ſtir a hand or foot to lift it up. Think on this ye perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Chriſts truth, ways, ſincere ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, ponder it betimes, and believe before you feel. <hi>Though your excellency mount up to Heaven,</hi> and your fame reach unto the ends of the Earth,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:109275:110"/> though all mouths ſhould bleſs you, all tongues extol you to the skies, and all knees bow unto you, yet <hi>ſhall you pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh like your own dung, leave your names as a curſe,</hi> which religious poſterity ſhall abhor and deteſt as the ſmoke of a dunghil, or ſtink of a carcaſe, and in the day of the Lord, if not in this life, be brought to a ſhameful ruine, and clothed with ignominy never to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> This muſt comfort us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſhame of the world, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage us patiently to bear the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Chriſt. Are we ſcoffed at, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled, ſlandered by wicked tongues, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelmed with calumnies and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, becauſe we are zealous for the Lord Jeſus, and do the things are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in his ſight? remember the time will come, when Chriſt ſhall aboliſh our ſhame, and deck us with his own glory, when both our perſons &amp; names, ſhall ſhine as the Sun in his brightneſs. Do the children of this world diſgrace us? Chriſt will honour us. Do we loſe
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:109275:110"/> our credit with men for ſubmitting to Chriſts Laws? We ſhall recover it with advantage, when Chriſt ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit us to ſociety in his own happineſs, <hi>to eat, to drink, and reign with him in his kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> this ſhould admoniſh and provoke us, if we deſire never-fading glory, to be ſtudious and zealous of Chriſts glory. He that will neglect himſelf and all things for honouring Chriſt, ſhall neuer want true honour, tho the world think this the high way to ſhame and diſhonour. Here is a leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for all ambitious ſpirits, thirſting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter renown. Lo this is the path lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the temple of honour. O ye ſons of the mighty, the way to be famous and glorious, is doing homage to the Son of God. <hi>Exalt him</hi> in your hearts, houſes, dominions, and he <hi>ſhall promote you</hi> to greateſt dignity. Advance him by your Councils ſwords, Authority, and he ſhall advance you, yea, <hi>make you an eternal excellency.</hi> Honour him in his ordinances, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:109275:111"/> members, and he ſhall make you high in name, in grace and in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.
<note place="margin"> 1 Sam. 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>The zeal of Gods houſe conſumed</hi> David, <hi>and God made him a great name, like unto the name of the greateſt men of the earth.</hi> Do not think that pomp and Bravery, Wit and Policy, Worldly wealth, preferment, and power of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding many, ſumptuous buildings, ſtately tombes and monuments, much leſs cruelty and tyranny, ſhall immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talize your names: no, no, its bleſſed conformity to Chriſt in true ſpiritual purity, hearty ſubjection to his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and down-right reſolution for his cauſe, which ſhall embalm and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemiſh your memorials, that children unborn may admire the fragrancy and ſplendor of them, and at laſt ſet upon your head an immareſcible crown of glory. Be ſtrong therefore and do it, for if you deſpiſe and pollute the Name of the Lord Jeſus, know for a certain, that he will expoſe your names to contempt, and make <hi>your memory not.
<note place="margin"> De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 9.20.</note> If you tranſgreſs againſt the
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:109275:111"/> Lord, it ſhall not be for your honour: the ſeed of evil doers ſhall never be renowned, the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The cauſe of this glory remaineth in the laſt words, <hi>[according to the grace of our God and of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.]</hi> the meaning is, the which glory cometh and ſhall be beſtowed upon you <hi>(O Theſſalonians)</hi> and all other believers, from the free favour and kindneſs of God, and that unſpeakable love of Chriſt the Mediator, which he ſhewed in giving himſelf for us, that he might bring us to the glory of the Father, and through whom all the effects of that eternal grace of God are derived and conveyed unto us. Obſerve hence only this inſtruction:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heavenly glory is from Gods meer grace. Ye are ſaved by grace.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                  </label> It is your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers good pleaſure to give you the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> Where good pleaſure ſignifies the meer loving kindneſs of God, as a <hi>Jeſuite</hi> confeſſeth againſt himſelf, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Other places we ſhall ſee after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. For,</p>
            <pb n="188" facs="tcp:109275:112"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Predeſtination to glory is meerly from grace, (this a <hi>Papiſt</hi> will not deny) therefore induction into glory is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from grace. The conſequence is good. For firſt, no man can properly be ſaid to be freely choſen to a place of dignity, for which he pays ſweetly (as we ſay) which he procureth by his own mony. Election to life is not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of grace, if collation of life be not wholly from grace. 2. The root is the cauſe of the ſeveral branches that grow out of the ſtock, as well as of the ſtock it ſelf. Grace is the root, Predeſtination the ſtock, wherefore grace hath no leſs a ſtroke in all ſubſequent benefits, whereof glorification is one, than in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Life eternal is an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, following adoption, a childs portion, yea ſuch an inheritance, as is aſſigned by lot, like the ſeveral ſeats of the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> and therefore (as antiquity did hence truly gather) comes not by humane acquiſition, but Gods gracious diſpoſition and donation.</p>
            <pb n="189" facs="tcp:109275:112"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Whatſoever is procured for us by Chriſt, and given us for Chriſt, is from grace. For that which is the cauſe of giving Chriſt, muſt needs be the cauſe of giving all the riches of Chriſt, which cannot be ſeparated from himſelf, and Chriſt cannot make an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect purchaſe. But we attain life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal by and for Chriſt, he hath procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it for his Members, he is <hi>given</hi> to them to be their <hi>redemption</hi> as well as <hi>righteouſneſs and ſanctification, he is our life, our hope, our hope of glory, through his righteouſneſs we continue to reign in life, by his bloud we have liberty to enter into the holieſt.</hi> Hence we are ſaid here and elſewhere <hi>to be ſaved by the grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> If the purchaſe be already made by one ſo ſufficient, there remaineth nothing for us to do, but thankfully to receive what the grace of God is ready to beſtow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Holineſs is the beginning of glory, they differ not in kind, but in degree, holineſs is glory inchoate, glory is holineſs perfected. Now holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:109275:113"/> begun in regeneration, is from grace; if Gods grace give the entrance into glory, why not the upſhot and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation?</p>
            <p>It may be objected <hi>life eternal is from juſtice, becauſe purchaſed by Chriſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The moſt common and received an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is, its from both in divers reſpects: From juſtice, if we look at Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he payed dear for it: from grace in reſpect of us, who bring nothing to our own ſalvation. But others ſay thus: Chriſts ſatisfaction, or the price of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption which he paid, doth not buy life at the hand of juſtice, but remove the bar which juſtice had put into the door of Gods ſtorehouſe, the which being taken away, grace hath full pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to beſtow ſalvation, which before ſhe had not. They explain themſelves thus: God out of meer grace ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed ſome to life. Theſe have defiled themſelves with ſin; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:109275:113"/> juſtice flepping ſorth, puts a caution into the Court of Mercy, I will and muſt be ſatisfied, before Man ſhall ſee life and happineſs. Chriſt comes and gives full contentment to juſtice, whereupon grace may now freely go forward with her dole, and finiſh the work ſhe had intended and begun. The ſumme is; Chriſts ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory obedience doth not put fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation into the hands of Juſtice to beſtow, but enables grace to beſtow it, juſtice not gain ſaying. Let him that readeth, chuſe whether of theſe anſwers he liketh better, or judge, if he be able, whether is the found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>This fighteth againſt that deviliſh doctrine of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> which ſaith, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly happineſs is not to be expected as an inheritance, but won and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by our merits, and conſequently comes not from grace, but from ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:109275:114"/> So that if <hi>Paul</hi> were alive again, the <hi>Italian</hi> Idol (I mean the great Bridge-maker of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Porter of the bottomleſs pit) would compel him to change his ſtile, or elſe anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matize him, and make a bon-fire of his bones. Were there no other difference betwixt us and the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is a ſufficient cauſe why we ſhould abhor them, and damn their Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine to the bottome of Hell, unleſs we will be Traitors to the Grace of God.</p>
            <p>But a <hi>Papiſt</hi> will object, <hi>it may be both from grace and juſtice: from grace, becauſe its the grace of Chriſt which gives power to merit: from ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith,</hi> The juſt Judge will in the laſt day give a crown of Righteouſneſs to all that love him.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, 1. Their <hi>Goliah</hi> ſeems here to ſtagger; for tho ſometimes he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that good works do merit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life by reaſon of an inherent dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which he endeavours to prove by
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:109275:114"/> ſeven moſt ſilly ſophiſmes, yet elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where he ſaith, <hi>We attribute not to works ſuch merit, as hath an anſwerable wages due unto it from Juſtice:</hi> and again, <hi>ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aſide the promiſe of God, he is not bound ſo to accept our works, as to reward them.</hi> 2. That place of the Apoſtle is not to be underſtood of Juſtice com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutative, or diſtributive, reſpecting mans merit, but of Gods verity of fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, who hath promiſed this Crown to all that ſtrive lawfully, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful fulfilling of which promiſe is a part of his Juſtice. For elſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſhould manifeſtly contradict himſelf, as who in other places hath taught moſt plainly, <hi>that grace and debt, grace and mans works</hi> (in reſpect of cauſation of ſalvation) <hi>can never ſtand together, that eternal life is a free gift, not wages</hi> (they ſhall never be able to make other conſtruction of <hi>Pauls</hi> words) yea, ſuch a gift of grace, <hi>as is not any way from our ſelves</hi> (all the wit in the world ſhall never elude ſo perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a paſſage) 3. This will better
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:109275:115"/> appear, if we do briefly ſhew, that the Scriptures do not know, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the doctrine of mans merit, (for themſelves cannot deny, but its a good rule in expounding Scripture, to compare one place with another.) Firſt therefore, the faithful <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did not merit the poſſeſſion of the land of <hi>Canaan.</hi>
               <note place="margin"> Deut 9.4, 5, 6. Pſal. 44.3.</note> 2. Its impoſſible man ſhould merit by paying his debt: but whatſoever we do or can do for God in this preſent world, its debt. 3. They that are but inſtruments doing all things by a power recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from, and continued by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, cannot merit at his hands: but ſuch are we. 4. Could we me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, we might by our works make God a debtor to us: but this may not be granted. <hi>My goodneſs extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to thee,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> which phraſe is not to be expounded by that, <hi>Thy vows are upon me, O God,</hi> that is, have made me obliged and indebted to thee. 5. If the beſt mans beſt works, cannot endure the ſtrict judgment of the Lord, if the beſt men ſhall need
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:109275:115"/> mercy in the laſt day, there is no place for merit. But the firſt is true. 6. We cannot deſerve the leaſt morſel of bread, but muſt ſeek it at Gods hands like beggars. Laſtly, if we muſt not look to have our Prayers heard and granted, much leſs Heaven beſtowed upon us for our merits. But the firſt the Scripture teacheth,
<note place="margin"> Dan. 9.18.</note> and Papiſts confeſs, and therefore in one of their Miſſal-prayers, they intreat God not to weigh their merits, but to pardon their offences.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let us look and truſt only to this grace of God in Chriſt, that we may find ſalvation, renouncing and diſclaiming all meriting cauſes of ſalvation, in our ſelves and all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Let us never think of challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing at Gods hand by deſert, much leſs <hi>the Kingdom that cannot be ſhaken.</hi> They that put confidence in their works, are like little children beginning to go by themſelves, who, that they may ſtand more firmly, take faſt hold on their own clothes, but alas they are never a whit further from
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:109275:116"/> falling: Nay well were it, if it were no worſe, but further <hi>they forſake their own mercy, and are aboliſhed from Chriſt.</hi> Indeed we muſt labour, ſtrive, run, fight before we be crowned: but when we have done all, ſtill we are to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our ſelves <hi>unprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> and confeſs that Heaven is Gods free gift, called a reward, not becauſe by our working it is deſerved, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by God graciouſly promiſed. Hold this faſt, that if Satan object thus unto thee on thy death-bed, How canſt thou hope for any part in the Kingdom of God, who art conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to thy ſelf of ſo great ſins, ſo many haltings and imperfections, thou mayeſt have what to anſwer: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed (Satan) it were ſomething thou ſayſt, and might ſhake me terribly, if I did challenge or expect ſalvation for my own works, my own preaching, praying, holineſs, zeal, ſerving of God, &amp;c. But I abhor my ſelf, my worthineſs is none, my righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſpotted, my merit is hell, I depend aad rely only on the Lords
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:109275:116"/> mercy, and Chriſts purchaſe, this is my rock and portion for ever. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, this hindreth not, but if Satan aſſault us another way, we may lawfully look at Gods image, graces and works in us, as teſtimonies of our faith, ſeals of the truth of our call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, evidences that Gods grace hath not been ineffectual in us, and that we are of the number of thoſe to whom ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is promiſed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
